>> Ladies and gentlemen, welcome
to the 2015 Apple Design Awards
and welcome your host for
this evening, John Geleynse.
[ Applause ]
>> JOHN GELEYNSE:
Well, good evening.
It is -- or good afternoon.
It's still afternoon, actually.
It is great to be here.
It's a great moment
to end off this day.
I know it's been long, many of
you have been waiting in lines
around the building to get
into the Keynote,
and that was a blast.
The Keynote was a blast, too.
And then you came into
-- you got your lunch,
then you had State of the Union,
and that was a great session.
And now we want to finish
the day by taking a moment
to celebrate the work that some
of you have done that's
been extraordinary.
Many of you do -- all of
you do extraordinary work,
but there are some that
stand out from the rest,
and we want to take
a few moments
to just celebrate some
excellence in software design.
Now, to begin this
evening and this ceremony,
I want to just kick off with a
video, which is a retrospective
of the winners from
the last 14 years.
You know, time flies;
doesn't it?
How many of you are familiar
with so many of those apps?
You played with those games.
You played with those
productivity tools,
some of those design tools.
And I had to demo
every one of them
on this stage over the years.
And this is just some
of those that came --
that you saw a moment ago coming
through for the last 14 years.
Those 14 years represent
14 years of Design Awards
since OS X was announced,
Mac OS X entered the stage,
and we had developers creating
apps right from day one.
And then, of course, the
App Store came and iOS
and everything that
we've known since then.
So many of you might be familiar
with the most recent ones
that were shown, and if you
just take a look at this list --
and this isn't to pick off
the best of the 14 years --
but these are some notable
ones that I just wanted
to highlight for a minute.
You know, Starry Night Backyard,
I remember showing that off.
That was incredible in the
first days of Mac OS X.
Macnification, this
great app for science.
Delicious Library 2, this
whole genre of apps that came
out in the early days of Mac OS
X that redefined the experience
for so many of us and actually
forced -- well, not forced --
but got people excited
to purchase a Mac just
to use those apps.
MLB.com At Bat.
Flight Control.
Who didn't play Flight
Control in the first days
of the App Store, right?
Paper for scientific research,
and then Monument Valley,
Infinity Blade, incredible apps.
What's interesting is that
these apps have set the standard
for so many things; right?
They've set the standard
for the user experience
that we expect on
these platforms.
These folks were pioneers in
many ways, not just these apps,
but the apps that showed up
across the last 14 years.
And I think the -- what's really
cool way to think about it is
that in so many ways, each of
the winners each year stood
on the shoulders of the
winners from the previous year.
Because so many of these
apps defined a new standard,
a benchmark in performance
or in usability,
and they inspired the rest of
you, inspired so many people
to go off and create
the next great thing.
Now, these apps every
year we've judged the apps
with the same set of
criteria, basically.
We've looked at delightful apps.
These are apps that
invite people to play
or get real things done; right?
They are satisfying;
they are rewarding.
We've always looked
for innovative apps,
winners that have this spark
of brilliance that it's hard
to define, but you know
it when you see it.
There's state-of-the-art
apps that are modern.
They are platform
differentiating.
They're high performance; they
have high-end capabilities,
and they are superprecise.
We look for apps
that are engaging.
Engagement means that
people keep coming back
to use these apps.
Some of the games
that were shown,
some of the productivity
tools are things
that we can't live without.
We can't live without
playing these games,
and we keep coming back
to them again and again.
We look for apps
that are enabling.
And great Apple Design
Award-winning apps
that are enabling
allow you to do things
that you could never
do before in new ways.
And lastly, we look
for designed apps.
These are apps that are deeply
considered, that are familiar,
they're appealing,
they're attractive,
and they're super intuitive
to use for the people
that they were created for.
So, a quick summary of
how we pick the apps.
We've always picked them
in basically the same way.
We've always used essentially
this set of criteria,
and this is the criteria
that we used for this year
to pick tonight's winners.
I'd like to invite my
colleague, Shaan Pruden,
on stage to award
tonight's winners.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Hello.
This year we will be honoring
ten apps from categories
across the App Store, but first
we wanted to take a moment
and honor two students among
our scholarship winners.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: Now,
the students we are
about to award are scholarship
winners for this year,
but in the process of looking
at the scholarship apps,
we discovered some apps
that they, themselves,
had also written
for the App Store,
and we were pretty impressed
with some of these apps
that were on the App Store
by these scholarship winners.
So the two awards
tonight are going to go
to developer scholarship winners
who have an app on
the App Store.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: And our first
student winner is Elementary
Minute by Klemens Strasser.
>> The idea for the
app came to Klemens
in April 2014 while
sitting in his room thinking
about the possibility of
having a quiz on his wrist.
Since there wasn't
an Apple Watch yet,
Klemens developed
it for the iPhone.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN:
Congratulations.
Here you go.
Elementary Minute is a
fast-paced trivia game
where you are presenting
with statements on topics
that include math,
geography, and famous people.
Quickly swipe up
or down to decide
if the statements
are true or false.
This app was created by Klemens,
who is a computer
science student
at Technical University
in Graz, Austria.
[ Applause ]
>> JOHN GELEYNSE:
Austria, right.
Big cheer down in front here.
We Picked Elementary Minute as
a student Design Award winner
because we loved the design, it
was super simple, and it was one
of the first games that
came out for Apple Watch.
It's built, obviously, on UIKit
and those sorts of technologies.
It's integrated with
Game Center,
and it has a clever
two-game mode.
You can do a quick five-second
quiz, trivia quiz on your wrist,
which is perfect for the Watch,
and you can do a one-minute
quiz both on Apple Watch
and on iPhone, and
we just thought
that the way this was done
was really well executed,
so congratulations.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: And
that's Elementary Minute.
Our other student
Award this evening goes
to jump-O by ByteBrushers.
[ Applause ]
>> Founded in 2013, ByteBrushers
is a two-person game development
team located in Brazil.
In 2012, Victor took a
game development course,
and a year later,
he convinced Gabriel
to attend the same course.
One day while discussing what it
was like when they were bullied
as kids, they decided
to create a game
that reflected their experience.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN:
Congratulations.
Jump-O is a minimalist game
where you play Roundy
the circle,
overcoming the dangers presented
by the squareish world.
It was created by two
university students from Brazil
and features beautiful
hand-drawn puzzles.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: You
know what's really fun
for us actually at Apple
is these folks took some
of the iOS training
courses that are in Brazil
and gained some experience
there to build this game.
We picked jump-O as a
student Design Award winner
because of its unique minimalist
design, as Shaan mentioned.
It's built on Game
Center, it uses Sprite Kit
for scene management
and game physics.
The input of the
game is super simple.
It's tap and device motion.
And it's got great
responsiveness, 68 worlds,
48 levels, just a
really fun game
that we thought was just
really, really well done,
and one of those games
that seems easy to learn
but it's hard to
master in that genre.
So congratulations,
great work, guys.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: And these
are our two student winners.
Now let's move on to the
Design Award winners.
Our first winner is an
imagination-stirring puzzle.
It is Shadowmatic by
Triada Studio Games.
>> Triada Studio was
established in Armenia in 1993
as a computer graphics
and animation studio,
and they successfully work on
TV commercials, visual effects
for movies, and various
other animation projects.
In 2007, they thought about
branching into video games,
began building a game engine.
The four-person game
team started work
on Shadowmatic in March 2012.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN:
Shadowmatic is a unique twist
on shadow puppets.
I don't want to stand
in their way.
Rotate abstract objects
in a spotlight
to find recognizable silhouettes
in the projected shadow
that are relevant to the
surrounding environment.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: All right.
So we picked Shadowmatic
as a winner
since it's ornately crafted
-- bit of feedback --
super imaginative, and
really well executed.
And I'd like to show
this to you now.
So let's get into the
level -- let's turn it off.
Let's get into the main menu.
So what you see here is just
there's device motion that's
affecting the view
into this main menu.
I can interact with objects,
which is no big deal,
but I am just showing
you the attention
to detail that's
even at this level.
And straightaway you hear
this ambient sound track,
and it's a beautiful sound
track throughout the game,
and it's available for
purchase on iTunes even.
So let me just go into
this second level here
and show you how this works.
If you play the game,
you already know.
If you've not played the game,
this is a good level to start
at to show you how it all works.
So basically what we
are doing is taking one
of these objects here, which is
represented at various levels
with ceramics and metal
and wood and all kinds
of different materials that
are beautifully rendered
in the scene, and you take one
finger to rotate it around,
and you take two
fingers to twist it.
And essentially, what you are
trying to do is figure out what,
you know, shadow it is
that you're trying
to build on the wall.
So I am going to
rotate it slightly,
looks like I am getting
some kind of a handle there.
And you'll notice on the bottom
of the screen there's some dots
that may light up here soon
if I get close to what it is
that I'm -- yeah, as
soon as I get close
to the puzzle I am trying to
solve, I get this feedback
on these glowing
dots at the bottom.
And so now I think I am pretty
close to something that looks
like a teapot, so there we go.
I get the six dots, and I
figured out this puzzle.
And every level is like this,
and obviously, you're timed.
As you go up through the levels,
it gets more and
more complicated.
We love the parallax effect
that looks like you are looking
into a window in the scene.
We love the high-resolution
rendering, the high fidelity
of the execution in the app,
and we think this app
totally makes an Apple Design
Award winner.
So congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Available
for both iPad and iPhone.
Our next winner is a
delightful education app.
It's Metamorphabet
by Vectorpark.
[ Applause ]
>> Vectorpark is the one-person
interactive development studio
of artist Patrick Smith.
His educational background
is in painting.
But soon after graduating,
he discovered he could combine
his particular visual imagery
with his lifelong love of
animation to create responsive,
immersive, and dreamlike
experiences.
Metamorphabet launched on the
App Store in February 2015.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN:
Metamorphabet is a playful,
interactive alphabet
for all ages.
Poke, prod, drag,
and spin objects
to reveal surprising vignettes,
where letters are magically
transformed into words.
>> We picked Metamorphabet for
its outstanding creativity,
convincing physics,
smooth animations,
and exploratory design.
I want to show this to you now.
So pick the first letter.
Right from the start you
see this torn fabric effect,
which is the beginning
of the animations.
I tap on these letters,
and they start to interact.
I am simply tapping, pinching,
zooming, whatever I want to do,
whatever the child would want
to do, whatever the student
of letters would want to do, and
you get these scenes that reveal
as you interact with
the letters.
So as I start to stroke
the A and move upwards,
I now get the word Arch, and
the narrator would tell me
that word.
It begins with A.
As I play with the scene,
suddenly it starts to move.
I get this effect of ambling.
So you can continue to
play with these letters,
and you learn more
and more words
that begin with that letter.
And kids, students, you
know, learning English
as a second language, whatever,
are going to learn these
characters and want
to keep coming back
to this game.
Let me just show you the G.
My last name starts with
G, I like the letter.
Let's go in.
We tap on it a few times,
it goes three-dimensional.
I pinch on it, it
becomes a guitar.
You can look at the
attention to detail here
because I can play individual
strings, but if I start
to strum the guitar, a
garden begins to grow.
Kids just love this
stuff, right?
It's just surprising,
unexpected,
and I can pick these flowers,
and they turn into ghosts,
which again begins
with the letter G.
And that's just an example
of the nature of this app,
which is just this bright,
cheerful app with super-great --
you know, with fun sound
effects crafted by one person.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Available
on the Mac, iPad, and iPhone.
Next up, we have a winner
in the finance category,
and it is Robinhood
by Robinhood Markets.
[ Applause ]
>> Robinhood's story
began almost a decade ago
at Stanford University,
where cofounders were
roommates and classmates.
To inspire a new
generation of investors,
they built a brokerage from
the ground up, allowing them
to eliminate commissions
altogether.
Since November's launch,
their team of 30 has introduced
hundreds of thousands of people
to investing, with 25%
of their customers being
first-time investors.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Say good-bye
to commissions and hello
to the future of trading.
Robinhood lets you buy
and sell stocks for free.
It also gives you access to
market data and stock quotes
in real-time and allows you
to build a personalized
stock watch list
with smart notifications.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: All right.
Let's take a look.
So Robinhood distinguishes
itself with this clean,
content-centric design,
beautiful typography,
and a design that
really does a good job
at balancing app branding
with iOS design conventions.
So right out of the gate,
the app just draws you in.
The goal of the app is to
get more people to invest,
and right away, they decide
that there's no need to sign
up to actually do
things in the app.
Let's see here.
Let me go to my backup.
There we go.
Because on the main screen,
if we simply scroll up,
we get a bunch of stock
symbols, and these are
because the app is using
geolocation to come
up with these symbols based
on companies that are nearby.
So let's just tap into
Apple, and you can look
at Apple's performance
over the last little while.
You can tap on this chart and
see the stock performance.
I am not logged in yet.
I am not a customer of theirs.
I am not a member.
I am not -- you know, I
haven't done anything here.
I am just playing around with
this app, exploring with it.
I can just tap and drag on the
chart, get some great feedback
on the values at the top.
I can pinch and get a range
and get an average value.
So that's pretty cool.
I can look at stats
from the company.
I can swipe, do the
page effect to go back
to a different symbol.
Here I am at SPY; right?
I am looking through
all of this.
Right? So I can explore
all of these.
Let's go back to Apple.
And let's say that at this
point we are like yeah,
wonder what it would be like
to buy a stock in this app.
So we tap Buy, we decide
let's buy 25 shares
at the current market price
for a total of $3,195.
We say that's fine.
Review. Robinhood tells us
that this is a simulated trade,
but if we were doing a trade,
we could just swipe
up from the bottom.
The device vibrates,
I get some feedback,
and it says that's
what it would be
like to purchase some
stock in this application.
And at this point, I can
decide this is pretty cool
and I am going to sign
up and you quickly put
in some basic information
about yourself,
you decide how you are going
to fund your transactions,
whether it's a checking
account, savings account,
and then you move on from
there and start investing.
And Robinhood uses Touch ID
for secure authentication,
uses SSL encryption
to protect your data,
and this is just
such a great app.
We just love the design.
So simple, just draws you
in, and really well done.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Available on
both iPhone and Apple Watch.
That's Robinhood.
Switching gears a little bit,
our next winner is a Mac app
for creative professionals.
And the winner is Affinity
Designer by Serif Labs.
[ Applause ]
>> Founded in 2009 with a vision
to develop the next generation
of creative software
for the Mac,
Serif Labs is a passionate
team of seven developers
with a combined 120
years experience
in the graphics design industry.
Based in Nottingham, England,
the team has been
laying the foundation
for the Affinity products
for the last five years.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Affinity
Designer is fast, smooth,
and extremely precise
vector graphics software.
Imagined by designers and
made exclusively for the Mac,
this fresh-faced, multifaceted
illustration app lets
creatives shine.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: This app is
a seriously fast vector drawing
application for creative
professionals,
and there's no way that
I can show you, you know,
very many of the
features in this.
This is a full-featured
vector drawing app.
One of the cool things
that they've got in the --
just to get you oriented
is in the top-left corner
of the screen, there
are three icons,
and these represent
their personas,
basically modes for the app.
So here we have the
draw persona,
which gives us the tools
we need for vector drawing.
We can shift to the pixel
persona, which is the tools
for pixel-based editing.
Then we can move to the export
persona, which allows us
to export layers, groups,
objects, and regions.
Right? Let's go back
to the draw persona.
This app was written
from scratch on OS X
and takes advantage of Grand
Central Dispatch, OpenGL,
Core Graphics, and it's
fully optimized for 64 bit
and multicore, which
means it can do a ton
of stuff super fast.
So just scrolling around in
the document is super quick.
I can zoom in to up to a
million percent if I needed to.
As I scroll around at something
like 5,000 percent right
now, it's very quick.
They've got a great
feature where I can go
into these split views.
Just a second here.
Let's go into view mode
and go into split view,
which lets me split the
screen into two views,
and one of these views I can
actually go into outline view,
which means that in real-time,
I am getting my object --
I can see the full
rendered version or I can go
into outline view and select
individual objects [applause].
So then I can select them,
rotate them, grow them,
whatever I need to do,
and all of this is live.
So I could pick this object here
and grow it into this portion
of the screen, and you would see
the rendering effect right live
across the divide.
And I can just move this
in real-time back
and forth super fast.
Now, I was talking about
how you could do zoom,
and I remember seeing that there
was a spelling error up here,
so I am just going
to zoom in here
and fix something on my design.
Now I am in at about
10,000 percent.
And I am just going to
change this one edit here,
and you know, move back out.
And you are looking
at this image here.
Right? So there's a
ton I could show you.
They've got a great corner tool,
they've got tremendous
functionality,
and we were just blown away
by how modern this app was
and how capable it was
and how great it was --
and how optimized it was for the
most modern Mac hardware today.
Excellent work, guys.
Thank you so much.
Congratulations.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: That's Affinity
Designer available for the Mac.
Next up, a game from
a classic genre.
The winner is Crossy
Road by Hipster Whale.
[ Applause ]
>> Based in Australia,
Hipster Whale was founded
by Matthew and Andrew.
Crossy Road is Andy's
first-ever mobile game.
The game was popular from day
one, but it really struck a cord
in schoolyards around the world.
Since launching, the
team has expanded,
and now six people
work on Crossy Road.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Crossy Road is
an endless arcade hopper game.
It has a retro feel but
with updated twists.
As you hop over endless
freeways, railroads,
and rivers you almost
don't mind getting run
over because the animations
for collisions are absolutely
hysterical, as you will see.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: Great.
So Crossy Road -- let's go
to the iPad -- has this --
you know, it's got
this addictive balance
between a casual puzzle and
arcade game and, you know,
if you haven't played this game
you are missing out big time,
but if you have, you know
exactly what this is all about;
right?
You are this chicken
or some crazy character
that they've drawn, and you are
crossing these multilane roads.
Now, in this particular
case, I am not the chicken,
but let's move anyway.
I am tapping to move forward,
and I can move left and right.
This is the schoolgirl.
See how far I can get here.
Oh, let's go, miss the
train, get out of the way.
Whoa. Let's keep going.
Oh, she got run over.
Okay. I am sorry.
Let's try another one.
Let's try the chicken,
see if the chicken comes
up, love the chicken.
So you have all these
characters that they've created,
and there's some
really good stuff.
Here's the dress,
you know, #thedress.
There is dark lord,
gravedigger, hot shot.
Let's go back to one
of my favorite ones.
I actually own chickens, just
the funniest creatures around,
so this is a real fun game
to play with your chicken.
So if you just look at the
8-bit isometric graphics,
just the sound.
Oh, and if that happens,
I can actually share this
with my friends and
look at the effect.
[ Applause ]
You know, Crossy Road -- I mean,
you could play this
forever; right?
And I know people who
get all the way up to 700
and it kills me because
the highest I can get is
about 70 or something.
But Crossy Road is such
exciting game play.
They have beautiful,
gorgeous 8-bit graphics,
if that even makes sense,
but there's just something
about the way you've designed
your characters, the artwork.
Hilarious collision animations,
expressive characters,
excellent sound design,
and you know what?
I think all of that combines to
create really great personality.
This game has got
tremendous personality,
which is really actually
a great characteristic
for an ADA winner.
So congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Crossy Road
available on iPhone and iPad.
Next up, an app in the
productivity category.
It's by Flexibits,
Fantastical 2.
[ Applause ]
>> Flexibits creates enjoyable
and flexible productivity apps
for Mac, iPhone, and iPad.
Cofounded by Michael
Simmons and Kent Sutherland,
the seven-person Flexibits team
is located around the globe
in San Francisco,
Boston, New York,
Houston, Germany, and Austria.
Fantastical 2 launched
on the Mac App Store
in March of this year.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN:
Fantastical is a calendar app
that strikes the right balance
between features and usability.
With natural language creation
of events and reminders,
beautiful calendar views,
and ultra smart event lists.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: Great.
So we picked Fantastical
for the beautiful
and thoughtfully designed
experience they brought
to OS X Yosemite.
I know that they've
worked really hard on this
because they have supported
prior to this iPad, iPhone,
most recently they just
came out with Apple Watch,
and they have done a great job
at bringing the visual style
of the app across
all of those devices
and at delivering
something fantastic on OS X.
So I want to just show you a
couple of features in this app
that we think make
it really great.
First of all, it's super fast.
So if you just go to the
left side of the screen here,
you scroll through all
your stuff, the entire --
you know, everything
just follows along.
You look at the top-left corner,
it's whipping across the weeks
to indicate the ones
that are selected.
The right side is moving
through your full calendar.
And there's just not a
hesitation to the app.
That's fantastic.
We can examine what's
going on on a specific day.
If you look at the
top-left corner here,
you have dots below
some of these dates.
If I point on the
dates with dots,
and the dots are colored
according to my calendar colors,
I can see exactly what's going
on on those days
from which calendars.
That's pretty cool.
I don't have to collect and
examine and go into that day
and look at what's
happening at that point.
Fantastical 2 makes it super
easy to add new things,
new events or new reminders.
They support both
reminders and events.
So the way to add something
new is if you are in the app,
you tap this Add button, and now
you can use just simple English
language sentences, and they
have a natural language parser
that will just interpret
these and translate, you know,
and interpret those into
the actual event details.
And as I type, I want you
to watch the extra attention
to detail where, as it's
parsing, what I am doing,
it's going to be throwing
down dates and the times
into the spots in that field
in the form that appears.
So let's just do something
like meet with Ron tomorrow
at 6:00 p.m. for 30 minutes.
For example.
Boom. And there it is.
It knows what tomorrow means,
it knows what 30
minutes means, etcetera.
The app is localized
into nine languages,
and the natural language
parser works
in those nine languages as well.
So this is a really great
experience across the world
for people in many,
many countries.
You can also add events.
If you were in another
application, you could just go
up to the menu extra and
just add stuff up here,
so I could do something else,
like pick up sushi next
Tuesday at 7:00 p.m. Boom.
And it throws the date in there,
puts it on my calendar,
and it's gone.
This little guy can
be torn off --
I wouldn't do this with the main
app running, but for the demo,
let me tear this off, and you
can have a Mini Window there
that's really handy to have
sticking around onscreen.
The other thing that they
do is that they've got --
Fantastical has got
multiple calendar sets,
and you can create work sets,
home sets, vacation sets,
whatever sets of
calendars you want,
and these calendars can have
multiple calendars within them,
and each set of calendars
can be activated at any time.
And not only that, you can go
in and say I want this calendar
to be activated on my
arrival at this location.
So I get to work, boom,
my calendar enables.
Or I get home, or I leave home
and some other calendar enables.
Very cool.
So you can see that here when
you go into Manage Calendars,
you can go through, pick the
different ones you've got,
and you can automatically
activate
on a location that
you might want.
Fantastical does a
great job of toggling
between these calendars, and it
also supports a Today widget.
They have Share and
Action extensions.
They support geolocation.
They are deeply integrated
with OS X Yosemite,
and I just think it's a
tremendous productivity app.
You guys have done a fantastic
job and I think set the standard
for what all other Mac
productivity apps should
be like.
So congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Fantastical is
available not only on the Mac
but also supports iPad,
iPhone, and Apple Watch.
Our next winner is a utility
app with a very unique story.
The winner is Workflow
by DeskConnect.
[ Applause ]
>> WWDC scholarship
winners in 2014,
the three-person DeskConnect
team have been huge Apple fans
since their early teens.
Workflow is a result of a
year of work which kicked
into high gear after
attending last year's WWDC.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Workflow
allows you to connect apps
and actions together to
automate the things you do
on your device.
Drag and drop any
combination of over 200 objects
to create powerful workflows.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE:
Workflow was selected
as an Apple Design Award winner
because of its extensive use
of the iOS accessibility API,
and just like a moment ago
I said Fantastical set the
standard for what productivity
apps on the Mac should be like,
Workflow sets the standard
for what accessibility --
what apps should be doing in
terms of adopting accessibility,
to enable these apps
to be used by people
with vision impairment.
And I could do this
demo, but honestly,
it's far more impactful if
it is done by a colleague --
a few colleagues of mine
from the iOS accessibility
engineering team
who can really show you
how this thing is used.
So I would like to invite
Ryan and Dean on stage.
[ Applause ]
>> DEAN HUDSON: All right.
My name is Dean Hudson, along
with my coworker, Ryan Dour.
We are quality engineers
on the Accessibility Team,
and we're really excited
about the accessibility.
It's just amazing work that
the Workflow team has done
in the Workflow app.
Apple is very deeply
committed to accessibility.
We have accessibility in all our
products, including iOS, OS X,
and now even the Watch.
But you know, today I want to
talk about VoiceOver in iOS.
Now, if you don't know,
VoiceOver is a built-in
screen reader
that allows visually
impaired users
to access iOS and your apps.
So you may be asking yourself,
well, how do I use VoiceOver?
What's that?
I mean -- to use
VoiceOver, you really need
to know three gestures --
touch, swipe, and
double-tap to activate.
In a moment, I am going to
have Ryan demo those gestures.
Let's talk about
touch, touch to explore.
It's a way for visually
impaired users
to safely navigate your apps in
iOS without activating anything.
And so they can get
the layout of the app.
And to demonstrate that,
I am going to ask Ryan
to show you touch to explore.
>> Game Center.
Double-tap to open.
>> DEAN HUDSON: The second
gesture we have is swipe
to navigate, and this allows a
user to swipe through buttons,
UI elements within your
application sequentially,
either forwards or backwards,
with a single finger swipe.
Ryan?
>> iBooks.
Settings. Extras
folder to Workflow.
Double-tap to open.
>> DEAN HUDSON: Now, the third
gesture we have is double-tap.
Now, remember, with
VoiceOver on,
touching is not going
to activate the item.
You have to use a double-tap.
What's interesting about
this gesture, though,
is you can have VoiceOver
focused on an element
and double-tap anywhere
else on the screen.
And that's very unique.
It's very crucial for VoiceOver
users because it's hard to find
that focus area again.
And Ryan?
>> Workflow edit dimmed button.
Turns on Workflow editing mode.
>> DEAN HUDSON: So that's
VoiceOver, it's awesome, great,
we love it, we use it, but it's
really only half the story;
right?
You know, the other half is
what you, as a developer,
does in your apps to
make it accessible.
And it's using VoiceOver
together with accessibility
that makes a great
user experience.
Right now I am going to have
Ryan show the Workflow app
with accessibility
using VoiceOver.
>> RYAN DOUR: So as Dean
said, my name is Ryan Dour,
and I am going to take you
through Workflow
using VoiceOver.
First I am going to go ahead
and start creating a Workflow.
You'll notice that
it's a visual button,
for me it's going
to speak a label.
Let's swipe over to our
right and see what it is.
>> Select Gallery button
to create Workflow button.
Creates a new Workflow.
>> RYAN DOUR: I am
going to go ahead
and double-tap to activate that.
>> Create Workflow.
Untitled Workflow.
Actions. Back button.
>> RYAN DOUR: I think what
I want to do here, actually,
I would like to get my current
location, then I think I want
to turn it into a URL so I
can share it with friends.
Finally, I think I'll copy
to my clipboard, actually,
so that it's easy to use
in a bunch of places.
Let's go ahead and start.
I am going to touch
the thing I am looking
for on the left side here.
So I'm going to touch
this sidebar.
>> Contact action.
Draggable.
>> RYAN DOUR: I am going
to pause the speech.
Now I am going to swipe my way
over to the location
that I would like.
>> Get current location action.
>> That's what I am
looking for, so I am going
to go ahead and drag that over.
>> Dragging.
Adding to current
locations to Workflow.
Search local businesses action.
>> RYAN DOUR: So I have
added that first piece.
Now let's go ahead
and go get that URL.
>> Draggable.
Double-tap and hold.
Wait for the sound,
then drag to the right
to add to your Workflow.
Double-tap to read the
action description.
Swipe up or down to
select a custom action,
then double-tap to activate.
>> RYAN DOUR: By the
way, isn't it wonderful
that they've added
those great hints?
They are fantastic.
It's basically a
self-described app.
It's great; isn't it?
[ Applause ]
So let's add it.
Okay. I am going to go ahead
and do a double-tap and hold
and drag it over to the right.
>> Dragging.
Added Get Maps URL
to Workflow below.
Get current location.
>> RYAN DOUR: I know
it's in the right place.
Let's get that third item.
And this time I am
just going to touch
because I know it's
right over here.
>> Copy to Clipboard action.
>> RYAN DOUR: There it is.
I am going to add that.
>> Double-tap and hold.
Wait for the sound.
Dragging. Added copy
to clipboard --
>> RYAN DOUR: Look, I
even know the position.
I am above it.
I am below it.
I am going to let go.
Hey, I have a complete Workflow.
I could run this right
now if I wanted to.
That's Workflow with VoiceOver.
[ Applause ]
>> DEAN HUDSON: They
did an excellent job.
When I first saw the
app, I was just like man,
this accessibility is cra-cra.
This is off the charts
[laughter].
It's interesting because
VoiceOver users are
like any other users.
We go to the store, go
to the same App Store,
look at the same games,
applications, prices,
and we purchase and download
and open your app, it's amazing
when we find it's accessible.
It just really makes
things work out well for us.
If you want to know more about
how to make your app accessible,
you can check out
the WWDC app and see
when the accessibility
sessions are.
We also have a couple of
labs that you can check out
and bring your apps in and
we'll check them out for you.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: And that's
Workflow, available on Mac,
iPhone, and Apple Watch.
This next app has a unique
spin on driving games.
It's Does Not Commute
by Mediocre.
[ Applause ]
>> This Swedish company
was founded in 2011
by Dennis Gustafson
and Heinrich Johansen,
who have known each
other for 20 years.
Their original intention was
to make Does Not
Commute a quick minigame,
but as they progressed,
the game grew
and they became increasingly
attached to it.
While still the only two
employees, they have worked
with various contractors.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Does Not
Commute is a strategic top-down
driving game.
What starts out as a relaxing
commute in a small town
in the '70s quickly
devolves into traffic chaos
with hot dog trucks,
school buses,
and dozens of other vehicles,
and you drive them all.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: All right.
So this is the time
traveler's paradox
in which you are
completing these challenges,
but as you drive -- as you try
to complete the challenges,
you are driving these
different vehicles,
and every time you drive
one and maybe, you know,
veer off the road or whatever,
make a mistake or screw
up somehow, it's going to
get you in the next level.
And so if you succeed
well, you are great.
If you screw up, you get caught,
and it comes back to haunt you
because it's basically
this time paradox.
So here we've got the app,
and we go in -- I am sorry.
Here we are.
There's some really great
visual design here that kind
of evokes the '60s and '70s.
I am on the main level here
to start, the simplest level
for you if you have not
played the game before.
What you are doing is you've
got to follow this arrow,
and you've got 60 seconds
to drive 13 commuters
to their destinations.
So this first car, we'll
just tap and drive.
At this point now it's
just right and left turns.
Right. Great.
Not bad, 53, took me 7
seconds to do that one.
This next one's got to go.
Watch the attention to detail
as the van kind of leans.
There is my first car.
I better watch out.
Okay. Great.
Not doing too bad.
The currency in this
game is time,
so if you ever see a
time token on the road,
you can just go pick that up.
Okay. All right.
We are lucky here we are
on the second street.
Notice it's replaying all of the
driving on my previous turns.
All right.
Now this is where it gets a
little screwy because -- whoops.
Oh, man. Oh, man.
Now, if I screw up,
I can hit the rewind
in the corner, it backs up.
Okay. Here we go.
Let's try it again.
All right, John, pay attention.
Pick up the token.
Boom. Oh, we are good.
Okay. Not bad.
I picked up ten seconds there.
Let's go for the next one.
Here I am an ambulance.
Not bad. That one's good.
All right.
Let's keep going.
Now it starts to
get a little scary
because I am driving an ice
cream truck, I could tip over,
and then the ice
cream would melt.
Okay. We are doing good.
Now, notice all of the
vehicles I have been driving
to date are coming in
to potentially haunt me,
so you know, I'm doing
pretty good, actually, today,
so I could cut through
here -- or not -- you know.
My car is smoking and
I am dropping oil.
All right.
Now here is the school bus, and
if we could just get the volume
up a little bit on this,
this is pretty good
because the kids really
don't like me as a driver.
[ Kids Screaming ]
So there you go.
And I'm just limping
to school here.
Kids are having a great time.
And lastly, you know,
I am scraping the back
of that house, flying
along here.
You get the point.
This game is just so compelling.
Each of the characters
has a personality.
The story goes on and on,
as you finish the level,
you move into a whole
different scene.
You go downtown, you
have different vehicles.
And all of your moves are
constantly coming back
to haunt you, and it's
just so impressive.
We just loved the visual
design of the game.
We loved the art in the game.
We love the attention to detail.
And we think that this is one
of the most unique games to come
out in iOS this year,
and so congratulations.
That's Does Not Commute.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN:
That's Does Not Commute,
available on both
iPad and iPhone.
The last winner from the game
category goes to a company
with probably the
best name ever.
It's Vainglory by
Super Evil Megacorp.
[ Applause ]
>> Headquartered in
San Mateo, California,
the Super Evil Megacorp
team includes 35 developers
from Riot Games, Lizard
Entertainment, Rock Star Games,
Gorilla Games, Playfish,
Supercell, and more.
Vainglory is their
first game and launched
on the App Store in late 2013.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Vainglory is a
multiplayer online battle arena
perfected for touch where
you outplay real opponents.
Fight with lightning-fast
controls using powerful heroes
to destroy the enemy Vain
crystal and claim glory.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: This is a
massive online battle arena
game, and it's going to require,
of course, multiple players
to really come up with
the greatest experience
and the best demo,
and there is only me,
not to mention I would probably
screw it up, so we decided
that we would, instead, get
a bunch of people to play,
we capture it on a device,
and show you the video,
and I can just comment on the
things that you are seeing
in terms of the quality of
work that these guys have done.
So if we could roll the video.
This game has been three years
in the making by
this small team.
The creators are huge MOBA
fans, and their goal was
to create a MOBA game
that they, themselves,
would want to play
on a touch device.
Vainglory uses Metal
on iOS and the A8 chip
to bring incredible game visuals
and a great gaming experience.
In terms of visuals, you are
getting 60-frame-per-second
performance, 1.3 million
polygon rendering.
Check out the environmental
effects.
You've got grass
and trees moving.
You've got particle effects,
gorgeous lighting effects.
I mean, this game is all
about the experience.
The highs, the lows, the
excitement, the anticipation,
the community that's built,
the friendships,
and the competition.
We are just so impressed by
this game pushing the envelope
in terms of performance
on the platform.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: And now we come
to our last award
this afternoon.
It goes to an app in
the music category.
I have to say this is the
demo I've been looking forward
to the most.
The winner is Pacemaker
by Pacemaker Music.
[ Cheers and Applause ]
>> Pacemaker Music is an
eight-person company based
in Stockholm, Sweden.
After the launch of Pacemaker
for iPad in early 2014,
the team soon realized
that their users,
predominantly college
students, wanted to participate
in the party rather than being
stuck with DJing the music.
To solve this, the
Pacemaker team decided
to develop an AI DJ, which
launched in December 2014.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Pacemaker
provides a full range
of music mix creation apps,
everything from instant mobile
mixing on iPhone and Apple Watch
to live, hands-on DJing
with Pacemaker for iPad.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE:
Let's take a look.
This app is set up to
give you the experience
of really making DJ fun and
personal with your music.
This isn't about
running a concert
for 70,000 fans necessarily.
It's more about just, you know,
creating a beat and a groove
at home maybe with some
friends at a party.
So I am going to launch the
app and pick some songs here,
and let's pick this one.
Play that.
See what it sounds like.
We've got sound here.
[ Music ]
I don't know.
That sounds kind of lame.
There is something wrong here.
Hold on a second.
Something's not right.
[ Laughter ]
There. All right.
That's better.
Okay. So let's add
another track here.
Let's try this one,
Mogadishu, and let's move on
and add another track here.
All right.
So this is on iPhone; right?
And I can start a
track playing [music].
Let's skip to the next one.
And it's going to
automatically merge the two
of these tracks together
pretty quickly.
All right.
So we are in Mogadishu here,
and we can turn on the effects.
Right on iPhone, we can start
doing some cool effects.
[ Music ]
Okay. I can do a high-low.
I can do an 8-bit.
Right. Let's move
to the next song.
It's going to do this
autopilot mixing.
So you just say move
on to the next song.
It's got this animation
coming in.
It's going to analyze the
beats, and then it's going
to merge these two songs
together really nicely.
Well, I sped that
up a little bit.
Sorry. Right, so you see the
effect that we've got here.
Right? So I can do some
white noise in the app.
Then you've got that
happening on the iPhone.
But they actually added
Apple Watch support,
so you can take your iPhone,
stick it in the stereo at home,
and now pick up your watch, go
dancing with your friends --
let's switch to the Watch here.
Let's launch Pacemaker
on the Watch.
We can add these effects.
And it knows exactly
which track is playing,
and so we can add
some white noise.
We can stop it.
We can add the chop.
And you notice see the feedback
going right on the watch?
It's all timed with the music
that's playing right now.
I can add the 8-bit effect.
I didn't say I was a DJ, but
you know, you get the point.
And I can apply the low filter
effect, and it will dip.
And you see what's
going on on the watch.
That's Pacemaker for
Apple Watch and iPhone.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> SHAAN PRUDEN: Pacemaker
also available on iPad,
iPhone, and Apple Watch.
So those are our winners
for the 2015 Design Awards.
[ Applause ]
These apps are from
categories across the App Store,
plus our two special
student winners,
and I'd like to invite all
of the winners back on stage
for final acknowledgment of
their great work this year.
[ Applause ]
In addition to the coveted Apple
Design Award trophy they receive
today, you will notice they all
have special Apple Design Award
lanyards they are
wearing, and we invite you
to meet them here
this week and learn
from these award-winning
developers.
Teams also receive almost one
of everything we make
as a prize package.
>> JOHN GELEYNSE: And we just
want to thank you for joining us
at the end of this long
day to celebrate the work
that these guys have
done, these folks.
They have worked really hard to
create some really great apps,
and we are looking forward
to seeing what you are going
to make with iOS
9, with El Capitan,
with watchOS 2.0 next year.
Let's give these
folks a last round
of applause, and thank you.
Have a great week.
>> SHAAN PRUDEN:
[ Cheers and Applause ]