>> Ken Orr: Good morning.
[applause]
>> Ken Orr: Xcode 7 is our
next major release of tools
for building Mac, iPhone,
iPad and Apple Watch apps.
Let's get started this
morning and take a look
at what's new in Xcode.
The biggest news this year
is that we've added support
for a third platform,
Watch OS, and of course,
you can build Apple
Watch apps right
in the same great Xcode
tools that you already know.
Xcode 7 also includes Swift 2,
building on the new programming
language we introduced
last year.
Swift 2 is faster
across the board,
not only will your apps run
faster when you're running
and debugging in
Xcode, more importantly,
they'll run faster
on customer devices.
Swift 2 also includes a number
of new language features,
like Error Handling which
introduces an explicit syntax
that makes it much more natural
to deal with errors in Swift.
Availability, Swift
now has insight
into the minimum OS required for
particular API, making it easier
for you to adopt new API
and also maintaining
support for existing OSs.
Testability.
Test bundles can now
see internal API,
letting you get broader
test coverage without having
to expose anything
additional in your sources.
Protocol Extensions lets
you add methods to any type
that implements a
particular protocol.
You can convert all
of your Swift code
to Swift 2 using
Xcode 7's Migrator.
It works great for projects
as well as playgrounds.
We have also added a couple
of new language features
to Objective-C to make it
work even better with Swift.
Like Generics which let you
specify type information
for collections.
Also Nullability Annotations
which let you specify
when you expect something
it to be nil or non-nil.
In Objective-C which makes it
really seamless when you want
to interact with options
in Swift, really nice.
We have gone ahead, we have
adopted all these language
features in our own SDKs.
So you will start seeing
the benefits today.
Now, if you want to get started
with Swift 2 or maybe some
of those new APIs
you saw yesterday,
well there's no better place to
do that than in the playground.
We introduced playgrounds
last year
and they have come a
long way since then.
Not only can you explore
and play with code,
but now you can explain
an idea or a concept all
from within a playground.
We have introduced
features like Rich Comments
which let you explain
what's going
on in the surrounding code
using a simple mark-up syntax.
They have beautiful
formatting and fonts
which really help
them stand out.
Within these comments you can
include things like web links
or lists or even images.
We have also made it possible
to pull results which were shown
in quick-look popovers,
you can pull them right
into the source code
under the line
of source that generated them.
This really helps tie the cause
and the effect much
more closely together.
This is really nice.
You can add almost unlimited
functionality to a playground
by adding Swift code to the
new supporting sources folder.
This helps you keep
your playground clean
and focused while also
giving you a place
to put the supporting
functionality.
There is also a performance
one here
because the supporting
sources, they can be compiled
down because they're
not run interactively.
They're only there to
support your playground
and that helps them run
really, really fast.
Our newest playground
feature is Pages
which lets you create content
that progresses through a topic.
For example, if you wanted
to author a playground
about sorting, you could add
an introductory page that went
into the fundamentals of sorting
and then you could
add subsequent pages
that covered things
like specific sorting algorithms
quick sort, bubble sort.
Then, when you wanted to provide
navigation through the pages,
you can add some of the
new mark-up syntax we
have introduced.
Playgrounds are a
powerful way to teach.
Last year we introduced the
guided tour as a playground.
This year we have
updated it to use Pages.
That's Swift 2 and
the new playgrounds.
In addition to iOS 9 and OS 10
El Capitan we have added sport
for Watch OS 2.
The new WatchKit will help
make your apps more responsive,
but it also gives
you more control
and flexibility as a developer.
If you haven't already,
I encourage you to check
out What's New in Watch OS 2.
Some really nice stuff.
You can build your entire
watch app, of course,
right in Xcode using storyboards
where you can quickly lay
out how your app will flow
from screen to screen.
You can design and
implement glances
or even the new WatchKit
complications.
For iOS, using things like
the new StackView it never was
easier to create a universal
app that deals with things
such as changing
screen orientation
or different screen sizes.
With the new iPad multitasking,
size classes which you define
in interface builder, they
have never been more important.
Along with iOS 9 we're
introducing a new crosscutting
feature called App Thinning.
The App Store can tailor
your app to deliver the best,
smallest possible version to
each unique customer device.
This will let you focus
more on building a great app
and worry less about size
because you will know
that customers, they'll never
download bits they won't use.
Xcode of course has
great support
to help you configure how
your app will be thinned.
There are three separate
parts to App Thinning,
starting with Bitcode.
When you archive for submission,
Xcode compiles your app
down into an intermediate
representation called Bitcode
which gets sent to the store.
The App Store can later
re-optimize your binary,
helping you future-proof for
things like compiler updates
or even new processer
capabilities.
To take advantage of Bitcode
you don't actually have
to do anything.
Xcode will do all
the hard work here.
The second, there is Slicing.
When the App Store
goes to send your app
to a customer device it will
only include artwork that's
needed for that particular
device.
For example, if you have both
2x and 3x artwork in your app
for an iPhone6 and a 6+ the
iPhone6 will only get the 2x
artwork and the iPhone6+
will only get the 3x artwork.
To take advantage of
Slicing, all you need
to do is use Asset
Catalogs in Xcode.
Third, on-demand resources,
which let you control
when assets are downloaded.
For example, you can
start downloading level 5
of your game just as the
user is finishing up level 4.
It gives you a ton of control.
Really nice.
Here to give us a demo of Watch
OS 2 and App Thinning is Jon.
>> Jon Hess: Good morning.
Today I would like to show you
two of my favorite new features
in Xcode 7; native-watch
extensions
and application thinning.
Let's get started with
our trivia game project.
Now in our trivia game we
already have things set
up for WatchKit 1,
and right now I want
to update it to Watch OS 2.
It looks like Xcode
has the same idea.
Here in the navigator, I can see
a project modernization sequence
already queued up for me.
I going to go ahead
and select it
and begin migrating my
project settings to Watch OS 2.
Here in the panel, Xcode
gives me a brief overview
of everything that's
going to happen.
I would like to go into it
with more detail for you.
Just like Watch OS 1, Watch
OS 2 applications are composed
of an app extension
and application.
Your code goes in
the app extension
and drives the app remotely.
New in Watch OS 2,
both the app extension
and the app run directly
on the watch.
This allows our applications
to be more responsive
and independent.
Sounds great.
I want to perform these changes.
What just happened?
Xcode took care of the details
of migrating my project
settings to Watch OS 2.
It configured my
Watch targets to build
against the new Watch OS SDK
that we released yesterday,
it set their minimum
deployment target to Watch OS 2
and it configured my Watch app
extension to be copied inside
of my Watch app so that
when they're installed
on the Watch itself they
both go over together.
All right.
That's everything with
upgrading my project settings
to Watch OS 2.
Our Watch application
is nice and light,
but our iOS application
is a quite bit bigger.
It is mostly due to all of these
images in my asset catalog.
I want to make it
smaller but don't want
to remove any content.
This is where the new App
Slicing feature comes in play.
You see every one ever
these images has a 1,
2, 3x representation?
Well with App Slicing, Xcode
7 and the App Store are going
to work together to make sure
that each device just gets this
single image that best suits it.
This cuts 30- to 40 percent
off the size of our application
and the best part is it's
pretty much automatic.
All I need to do is use
Xcode 7 in an asset catalog
which I'm already doing.
What about the other
assets you would
like to target for each device.
We have extended the
asset catalog in Xcode 7
to support arbitrary data.
You can put whatever
you want in here.
Down here further
in the catalog,
I have this skylines folder.
It's filled with 3D models of
cities from around the world.
We present them to the
user and they guess
which city they are looking at.
San Francisco, I have a really
high-quality model of the city
of San Francisco I would
like to include in our game,
but I only want to send it
to the most high-end devices.
No problem.
Just like images can vary by
scale factor and size class,
data assets can vary by device
performance characteristics,
things like the amount
of memory on the device,
or the GPU capabilities.
I want to add a specialization
for machines
with 2 gigabytes of memory.
Then I will just
go ahead and drag
in my high-end resource
and I'm good to go.
Each device will get the
resource that best suits it
without double-paying.
All right.
Now I would like to show
you on-demand resources.
On-demand resources allow
us to host the content
for application remotely
on the App Store.
We opt our resources
in to on-demand hosting
by tagging them with strings.
The strings can be
anything we want.
For example, if we're making
a game, we might tag each
of the assets that comprise one
of the levels by
that level's name.
Then, at run time, we use the
new NS Bundle Resource Request
class to fetch and pull down
whole tags worth of content
into our game for
fast, local access.
Let me show you how
to get started
with on-demand resources.
Here I've selected a
folder in the catalog.
It represents all
of the questions
in the world genre of the game.
In the inspector I'm going
to use the new on-demand
resource tag section
and tag this content,
world questions.
I've just opted all of it
in to on-demand hosting.
Now, what kind of things
can you tag in a catalog?
You can tag entire
folders like I just did.
You can tag images and
data assets directly,
you can also tag Sprite
Atlases in the Asset catalog.
Sprite Atlases are
a new component
of the Asset catalog in Xcode 7.
By putting your Sprite
Atlases in the catalog,
it makes them eligible
for the Splicing feature I
mentioned earlier.
You can also tag loose
files in your Xcode project.
This inspector gives me
a great overview of all
of the tags on a
particular file.
What if I want to see
all the files in a tag,
or just all the tags period.
For that, I can head over
to the Project Editor,
by selecting our
Application Target and going
to the New Resource tag section
I can see all of my tags.
As you see, I tagged a
lot of content earlier.
It is a great place
to get an overview
and make sure things are
consistent like I expect.
For example, I see this books
tag doesn't match the format
of the others, they all
have this question suffix.
No problem.
I'll edit this, and update
all the content in one go.
Now with tag to all of our
content for on-demand resources,
and I would like to show you how
to started using it from code.
That's where the new NS Bundle
resource request class comes
into play.
Here in our game class,
we have two callbacks
that will be perfect for this,
start using genre
and stop using genre.
Two reasons they are great for
using on-demand resources first,
they are bracketed
in time, and second,
they happen a just a bit before
the user actually initiates the
game but as soon as when we
know what they're going to play
in the game, It lets us
pre-fetch the on-demand content.
I'll get started with
an instance variable
to hold an NS Bundle
resource request.
NS Bundle resource requests
are substantiated from tags,
and remember, tags are
just simple strings.
I'll use our genre's name
with batch questions appended
to the end to form our tag.
Then I can create the bundle
resource request from that tag.
Finally, I can invoke
the request
with the new begin
accessing resources
with completion handler method.
This is an asynchronous method
that runs in the background.
It downloads all the
content from the store,
and when it's done, it
fires my completion handler.
Once my completion handler
runs, and until I say I'm done
with the resource request,
I have fast local access
to all the content.
This is my favorite part.
I get it all, that content with
the same APIs I'm already using.
Methods like NS Bundle, Path of
Resource, UI Image, Image Name,
Texture, Texture
Name, all continue
to work exactly as
they did before.
I'm not making any
changes to the rest
of the resource lookout code
throughout my application.
Now, I set all that content as
available until I say I'm done
with the NS Bundle
resource request.
How do I do that?
In our stop using genre method,
I'll invoke end accessing
resource
on the NS Bundle
resource request.
This moves all the content
that I fetched into the cache
so it is available for future
access but it also marks it
as available for
purging in the even
that the system runs
out of space.
With that, we have written
all of the code we need
for on-demand resources.
I want to build and
run our game.
We'll start a new game.
I'll show you some of the
debugging functionality
for working with
on-demand resources.
Here in the debug navigator, I'm
going to select the disk gage
to bring up the disk
report to get an overview
of all the ways the
application is using the disk.
We've added a new
section here in Xcode 7,
on-demand resource tags.
You see can see my tags, their
size, and their current status.
All that are currently
marked not downloaded,
Xcode is mimicking the role
of the app store right now.
All of my resources are in
Xcode, not on the simulator yet.
But, when I click
one of these genres,
the code that we just wrote
runs in the background,
downloads the content and now
you see my tag is marked in use.
If I switch to a second genre,
you can see the first
content is moved to the cache,
just marked downloaded, and
now engineering questions are
in use.
That's Slicing and
on-demand resources.
With Application Slicing,
we're able to lower the size
of our iPhone 6 application
from more than 140 megabytes
to less than 100 megabytes.
With on-demand resources
we were able
to further lower the
initial install size
down to just 30 megabytes.
Now users can get started with
our game faster than ever.
Back to you, Ken.
[applause]
>> Ken Orr: Thank you, Jon.
This year we have
introduced a number
of new features targeted
squarely
at helping you enhance
the quality of your app.
Let's start by talking about
debugging and profiling.
In Xcode 7 we have brought
the energy gage to iOS apps.
IOS 9 contracts energy
on a per process basis.
That's reflected right
here in the energy report.
The gages in Xcode are
a great way for you
to match what you
expect to be happening
against what's actually
happening.
If you see a spike in energy
usage and you're sitting
in your app apparently
idle, that's a first clue
that maybe you have a problem.
Sometimes when you have
a problem like that,
you know exactly where to
go looking in your code.
But when you don't, you can jump
right into Instruments from all
of the reports in Xcode.
From the Energy report
we can jump
into the New Location instrument
which lets us make sure
that we're efficiently
using core location APIs.
We can answer questions
like are we asking
for the user's location
too often, are we asking
with too high a precision?
Things like that are
going to cost energy
and we can investigate
those right here.
For iOS, this is also the new
Metal System Trace instrument
letting you see how the
frame rate is being effected
by things like your own code.
The graphics driver, hardware
rendering, it gives you insight
into the entire Graphic
Stack, really powerful.
You may also notice
here in Instruments
that there is a redesigned
track view.
It has a cleaner look,
more importantly it is
more natural to use.
With gestures like
pinch to zoom,
navigating through your
data is really, really easy.
That's a quick peak at
the new Instruments.
I'm willing to bet that every
developer in this room has been
in a situation where a
customer reports a crash
and you just can't reproduce it.
All right.
That happened once
or twice maybe?
The new in Address
Sanitizer in Xcode 7 can help.
Address Sanitizer compiles your
Objective-C in C code in a way
that catch things
like buffer overflows
and it can catch them
immediately when they happen.
Xcode will stop you
right on the line of code
that caused the problem.
This is a powerful
new debugging feature.
Here to give us a demo of
Address Sanitizer is Kate.
>> Kate Stone: Thank you, Ken.
Our trivia game is a great
diversion with friends
but some are experiencing
crashes
when they're setting up a game.
It is unpredictable
enough that it is the kind
of bug that's hard to reproduce
and make heads or tails of.
I'm sure you experienced
something similar
as I've heard anywhere
you have used pointers
to explicitly managed memory.
Our game is looking beautiful.
We can dive on in, start
a new game, pick a genre,
pick a few users to work
with and we're ready to play.
So it seems to work
just fine -- oh.
Being on stage is
perfect to reproduce this.
Hard to find bugs.
So let's have a look at this.
It's crashed, where
is it crashed?
What can I debug?
It's crashed in my main class.
So there's not even I line
of code I've written there.
There's nothing in
the Stack Trace
to give me a place to start.
That's typical of
this kind of bug.
Luckily, Address
Sanitizer can help there.
We have a variety of
these diagnostic tools
that you can get to from Xcode.
All you need to do is go
to the Scheme editor
for running your app.
As that handy shortcut, I'll
hold down Option while I click
on Run to get to
the Scheme Editor.
I can configure how I
run my application here,
including the Diagnostics tab
which lets me select some
potentially familiar tools
as well as the new
tool, Address Sanitizer.
Enabling Address Sanitizer
does something different
in that it recompiles the
application adding a bunch more
Instrumentation showing
me not just where I failed
but why I failed as well.
Let's rerun that application
and see how this works.
Now I'll find when I
select a genre and move
to the next page it
immediately stops my application
because this is where the memory
corruption actually occurred.
Far before the application
finally comes
to a screeching halt I can
find out what went wrong.
In this case I get the exact
Stack of where it stopped
and it turns out that it
is some Objective-C code
that I'm calling.
Not everybody has the luxury
of writing everything in Swift.
In fact, in our case, we have
this C code that's been wrapped
in an Objective-C framework.
That's the source
of our problem.
I'm not familiar with this code.
I'll have a look at the
code that I'm calling it
from written in Swift.
Here I am calling
some logging API.
That tells me where exactly
I'm triggering the failure
but still not yet why.
If I look further down the
Debug navigator though,
I can see that in addition to
Address Sanitizer telling me
that I'm using deallocated
memory
and that that's the actual
source of my problem.
I can also see in the Debug
navigator what memory that is.
I'm accessing the first bite
in a 50-bite heat region
that was previously allocated.
I can go a step further, click
on and actually see the memory,
and see it has been previously
used to store a log message.
Because it is gray, Address
Sanitizer is telling me
that it knows that it is
no longer valid memory,
no longer memory I
should be accessing.
It also gives me the call Stack,
where that memory was originally
allocated and I can see
that it is when I'm creating
a usage log that makes sense,
and more importantly
in this case,
where that memory
was deallocated.
I can tell here that it is
when I call end logging,
the particularly
badly designed API.
I thought it was just to
flush the log but it turns
out it takes down
critical resources.
Let's solve that
problem quickly.
I can take that line of code,
instead of calling it
every time I log a message,
I'm going to call it only
once during tear down.
Now Address Sanitizer rebuilds
the application complete
with Instrumentation, still
very snappy, still possible
to use it interactively, and
I can get a step further.
It all looks good until
it finds my next problem.
Because Address Sanitizer is not
just about deallocated memory.
In this case it is telling me
about a heap buffer
overflow similarly telling me
about under flows and Stack
memory that I'm overflowing
or under flowing, it is an
extraordinarily powerful tool.
It's the kind of
tool you should use
on your applications right now
to find all those
lurking memory issues.
We tried to make that
as easy as possible
because Address Sanitizer
cannot only run
in this interactive
form, but you can use it
with Xcode Servers so you
can set up a suite of tests
with Address Sanitizer
enabled and find those problems
when they creep in your code.
Because you want to minimize
the number of crashes
but let's be realistic, you
can't eliminate them entirely.
So I'm proud to bring
up Itai to talk
about how Xcode helps you
analyze those crash logs you
will get.
[applause]
>> Itai Rom: Thanks, Kate.
Good morning, everyone.
As Apple developer program
members you have access
to the new crash logs in Xcode.
When you distribute your
app through the App Store
or TestFlight and include symbol
information we'll collect crash
logs from your users.
Those crash logs will be fully
aggregated into crash reports
and downloaded into
Xcode wher you can view
and analyze them right
in the organizer window.
The integration here is
seamless making it easier
than ever before to find and
fix your most critical issues.
I would like to show
you how to use it.
Last year we introduced
TestFlight.
TestFlight is a convenient
service
for distributing beta builds
of your apps and works great
with crash logs in Xcode.
We just distributed a beta build
of our trivia game yesterday.
I'll like to find and
fix some of the crashes
that our testers reported.
I'll launch Xcode.
I have already entered
my Apple ID information
into Xcode's Account Preferences
panel, so all I have to do
to view crashes is open
the Organizer window.
On the left side of the window,
Xcode will download information
about all of the apps that my
development team has uploaded
to iTunes Connect for the
App Store or TestFlight.
I'll choose trivia.
On the right, I can
choose which build
of trivia I'm interested in.
This build 55 at the top
of the list is the one
that we distributed through
TestFlight yesterday.
I'll click that.
Underneath Xcode will
download information
about all of the top crashes.
These are sorted by frequency of
occurrence, the one at the top
of the list is naturally the one
that our testers
experienced the most often.
To the right I can see the
back trace for this crash.
Xcode helpfully highlights
one of the Stack frames
in a beautiful orangey
salmon color,
that tells me something
fishy is happening in my app.
In particular that's where
my app crashed inside
of this usage log
and log in method.
That looks similar to the
crash that Kate just found
and fixed using the
Address Sanitizer.
That's my favorite type of
bug report, I don't have
to do anything since
I watched her fix it.
I'm going to go ahead
and mark it as resolved
by clicking this button
on top of the window.
I can have Xcode filter out the
crashes I have already resolved
by clicking the filter in
the bottom of the window.
Now I can focus on the crashes
that I still need to fix.
We have warmed up with
a pretty easy one.
Let's take a look
at the next crash.
This time we're crashing inside
of our splash screen
view controller,
the beautiful landing page in
the app where you see a grid
of your friends' images.
It looks like we're
indexing into an array
and we might have indexed
beyond the array's bounds.
I would like to try
fixing this crash.
I can jump right into my source
code by clicking the Open
and Project button, selecting my
project, and then clicking Open.
Now, Xcode has not
only opened my project,
it has also magically
transported the crash log
that I was just viewing
in the organizer right
into the Debug navigator where
I can click through Stack Frames
and navigate through
my crash log
and source code side-by-side.
It looks like we're crashing
into the next image method.
This looks similar to a
crash I think Jon came
to my office yesterday to
tell me he was hitting.
What we're doing is indexing
through an array of images
of our friends and
incrementing a counter as we go.
When we get to the end
of the end of the array,
we set the counter back to zero.
We have an easy to miss
off by one error here.
This should be a greater
than or equal to check.
I'll fix that.
It looks like you could hit
this crash really easily
if you don't have
very many friends,
which probably explains
why Jon found it.
Now I can go back to the
organizer and fix more crashes.
The new crash logs
feature in Xcode
and TestFlight work great
together to help you find
and fix your most critical
issues before you ship
to your customers.
Now back to Ken.
[applause]
>> Ken Orr: Thank you, Itai.
Testing. Over the past few
years we have continually added
to the testing support in Xcode.
Making it possible
for you to test more
and more parts of
your application.
In Xcode 5 we added
a Test navigator.
When you combine that with the
assistant editor we have a nice
workflow for test-driven
development.
We have introduced XC Test
our unit-testing framework,
along with Bots which let you
automatically run the unit tests
on Xcode Server for
continuous integration.
In Xcode 6, we introduced
performance testing
to quickly let you identify
performance regressions
and added testing for
asynchronous APIs.
In Xcode 7, we're introducing
User Interface testing.
The UI testing lets you
test the part of the app
that users actually
see and touch.
The tests like this
are so important
because they help you ensure
that your app continues
to function the way you
originally intended.
Even as you make changes
and enhancements over time.
Like all the testing features
we have added to Xcode,
UI Tests work grade
with Xcode Server.
This is particularly
important for UI Test
because they may take
a bit longer to run.
Also on Xcode Server you
will oftentimes have access
to many more devices than
you would at your desk.
This will let you get a
broader range of coverage
and let you get that
coverage more often.
Speaking of coverage, to
round things out in Xcode 7,
we have added Code
Coverage for testing.
You can turn on Code Coverage
here in the Schemes Test action,
and when you do, Xcode
will build your app
with special instrumentation
that lets it track exactly
which lines of code
are being executed.
After you run a suite of tests,
you will notice the New
Code Coverage bar here
on the right side of
the source code editor.
This gives you a quick
visual indication
that shows you exactly which
lines of code were called,
more importantly it shows
you which ones were not.
Here to give us a demo of UI
testing in Xcode 7 is Joar.
[applause]
>> Joar Wingfors:
Thank you, Ken.
It is really easy to get started
with UI Testing in Xcode.
You add a new UI Testing
target, like I have done here.
If you have used
unit testing before,
you recognize getting
a test case sub class
and the method created for you.
Had this been a unit
test, you would now have
to write the test method
using your bare hands.
Now we can write this for you
recording the application.
Let's take a look.
I put my curser in the Test
Method and start recording
by clicking the Record button
at the bottom of the window.
While recording any
event received
by my application will result
in source code being
emitted into my Test Method.
For this test I want to
configure a new game.
I'll go ahead, tap the
Start a New Game button.
Note that as I tap the
button, the corresponding line
of code showed up in the
Source Editor right away.
Here I'm asked to pick a genre,
I'll go with sci-fi
for this test.
Tap next. I'll invite a couple
of players, Alice, Brandon,
I'll search for Stacy.
There she is.
I'll tap done.
Tap next. Finally tap the switch
to mark the game as ready.
With this I'm done with -- with
what I wanted to record here.
Let's take a look with
what we ended up with.
This first line of
code contains a query
to find a button label
start a new game,
and it returns what we call an
element, an element is a proxy
of the actual button
in the application.
Using this element I can now
access properties of the button
and also send events,
in this case, a tap.
These next couple of lines
contains the source code
for selecting the sci-fi genre
and for tapping the Next button.
We designed the UI Testing
APIs to be easy to read here,
as you see here,
to be easy to write
and to help you produce
robust tests.
Now for this to be
a test it would have
to actually test something,
and it already does.
If I were to run
this test as-is,
it would implicitly validate
that all the controls
that I interacted with while
recording are still available
to me and fail a
test if they're not.
In addition to this
implicit validation,
I would typically also want
to explicitly validate other
aspects of my application state
at different points
throughout the test.
In this test, I selected
a specific genre
and invited a specific
set of players.
Let's add a couple of
assertions to the test
to make sure that's
what we ended up with.
These assertions validate that
there are elements in the UI
of the last screen
of the application
that contains the
name of the genre
and names of these players.
With these assertions in
place, I will be allowed
to run the test to make sure
it performs as expected.
No hands.
The test passed.
[applause]
>> Joar Wingfors: This
is a quick overview
of testing in Xcode 7.
I think you should all try it.
I think you'll love it.
More importantly, I think
your customers will.
Back to you, Ken.
[applause]
>> Ken Orr: Great.
Thank you, Joar.
We have looked at just a few
of the many new features
this morning.
I hope you're excited
by what you've seen,
and you can see even
more throughout this week
at the many great
sessions which will go
into much more detail
on Xcode 7.
If you haven't already,
I encourage you
to download the new Xcode and
let us know what you think.
Thank you very much.
[applause]