>> IAN FISCH: Good morning, and
welcome to Accessibility on iOS,
my name is Ian Fisch
and I'm an engineer
on the Accessibility team.
So accessibility is really
about making sure all users,
regardless of abilities,
have full access to all
of our products and the great
features you put in your apps,
and that means we get to
focus on users and think
about how users with these
different abilities use
our features.
That, in turn, has allowed
Apple to create great futures
to empower users, like
the girl you see here
with a switch mounted next
to her head which allows her
to control all of iOS,
with just that one button.
And that gives her the
freedom to communicate and play
without the need for assistance.
And as users get older
and older, more and more
of them will be using these
accessibility features,
so the time is really
now to start thinking
about accessibility in
the terms of your app.
So Apple creates these great
accessibility features,
but that's only part
of the story.
We need all of your
apps to be accessible
so we can create a great
ecosystem for accessibility
and empower these users.
Today we will be talking about
the accessibility futures
that Apple provides on iOS.
We will look at what's new
in iOS ,9 and we will go
through what we call
an accessibility audit,
where we will look at an app
and see how accessible
it is already.
Then we will go through
implementing some accessibility
in that app.
But first, let's take a look
at the accessibility
features that Apple provides.
We break those into four large
areas: hearing, learning,
vision, and physical and motor.
So I will go through just a few
of the features that we have,
but there are many more I don't
have time to talk about today.
For hearing, we have
made-for-iPhone hearing aids,
which allow users to stream
high-quality audio directly
from their iOS device
and control the settings
of those hearing aids.
This replaces a lot of extra
hardware the user would have
to carry with them
all of the time
and provides a much more private
experience for setting these
or changing the settings
for hearing aids.
For learning, we have guided
access, which lets teachers,
parents, and caregivers remove
distractions so users can focus
on a specific app or task.
And we even provide time limits
so you can restrict the
time allowed in a task.
For developers, we provide
an API that allows you
to provide specific
restrictions for your app.
For vision, we have
VoiceOver, which lets blind
and low-vision users
touch the screen
and have VoiceOver read
what's under their finger.
So they can use gestures
to interact
with the touchscreen even though
they can't see the screen.
We also have Zoom, which lets
users who may need things
to be just a little bit bigger
but can see the screen magnify
the interface of your app
and the operating system.
And it will even
follow text as you type
and leave the keyboard unzoomed
so you can still have full
access to the keyboard.
Finally for vision, we
have Vision Accommodations,
which adjusts the
interface for users
who might need larger
text, higher contrast,
or reduced motion so users can
more easily orient themselves
with what's on screen.
For physical and motor,
we have Switch Control,
which uses these
switches, or large buttons,
to control the operating system.
It's great for users who may
not be able to fully interact
with the touchscreen,
and it allows them
to sequentially navigate
the items on screen
and perform complex
gestures and even play games.
If a user has difficulty
performing gestures
or pressing a physical
button, we have AssistiveTouch,
which provides a menu to
quickly access recorded gestures
and hardware buttons.
And this even works
with third-party assistive
devices like wheelchairs.
And brand new in iOS 9 we
have Touch Accommodations,
which helps users who may have
difficulty performing precise
gestures by changing the way the
touchscreen responds to touches,
and I would love to give
you a demo of that now.
Like all accessibility
features, you can turn
on Touch Accommodations by
going to Settings, General,
Accessibility, and you
can see the large list
of accessibility
features we provide.
But for now, we will go
into Touch Accommodations.
And you see we have
got three options.
Let's look at Hold Duration.
And this allows people
who may have tremors
and touch the screen more than
they would like to set a timeout
so not all touches are used.
So let's turn on Hold Duration
and Touch Accommodations.
So I go back to the Home
button, you will notice
when I put my finger on the
screen I get this timer icon,
and if I lift up
before the time is up,
the touch isn't passed
to the icon.
But if I tap and hold
for the whole duration,
it will open the app.
So if I have tremors, they
won't be respected as touches.
Great! So if we go
back into Settings,
we can look at Tap Assistance,
which is great for users
who may not be able to land
on exactly the right icon
that they are looking for.
So if we go back
to the Home screen,
you can see that if I press on
Clock and then move to Calendar,
the touch will be passed to
Calendar instead of Clock.
So it's the final touch
location that's respected.
And that's Touch
Accommodations on iOS 9.
So, many of these accessibility
features rely on UIAccessibility
to bridge the gap between
the assistive technology
and your app.
For instance, if a VoiceOver
user taps on the screen,
it will look for the
element under their finger
and ask the element in your app
for its accessibility label.
So when you return the string
Weather, VoiceOver will speak:
>> VOICEOVER: Weather.
>> IAN FISCH: And similarly
with Switch Control,
the Switch Control user
brings up the menu on one
of your elements,
will ask that element
for its accessibility
custom actions,
and when you return the
actions -- move, pass and trade,
if it's a game app, maybe --
it will display those in
the Switch Control menu
so users have fast
access to these actions
on elements in your app.
So you will notice that
UIAccessibility is really
about asking questions
of elements in your app
so the assistive technology
knows how to work with it.
So let's go through a
few of those questions.
The first one is: Do
I serve a purpose?
This is really about
whether an element is useful
or important to the user.
So a line that separates
elements
in a view is very
important visually,
but since the user
can't interact with it
and it doesn't provide
information like a UI label,
it's not really serving
a purpose.
So we answer this question
with Is Accessibility Element.
If we look at the Plus button
in Clock, it's a button,
the user can interact with it,
and so for that we
would return True.
The next most important
question is: What's my name?
We answer that with
Accessibility Label.
This is what VoiceOver
uses to read
to the user what's
under their finger.
If we look at the Plus
button, you might be tempted
to set the label to something
like Button To Add A Clock,
which is a great description
of what the button will do,
but you should think of the
accessibility label more
like the title of a button,
so a better accessibility
label would just be Add.
So what's the personality
of the element in your app?
And this is really about
describing to the user
and the assistive technology
how they can interact
with an element.
So we answer that with
Accessibility Traits.
So we have a whole host
of traits that you can set
on elements that describe
how to interact with them.
So if we look at the Plus
or Add button in Clock,
we would set the trait to
Button, because it's a button,
and VoiceOver would read
it as a button to the user.
Next question is:
What's my value?
So if an element has a state
that changes frequently
over its life, we would
change that or update
that with Accessibility Value.
So if this time we look
at the Clock element,
the value that changes
would be the time,
and so we would return the
string 11:20 a.m. and update
that accordingly as
the time changes.
So the next question is: How
should people interact with me?
If the traits aren't enough
to describe how to interact
with an element, where you
need just a little bit more
information, you can provide
that with Accessibility Hint.
So if we look at the
grabber in World Clock,
we could set the hint to
something like, drag up
or down to change the order.
And this is, this describes
to the user exactly how
they can interact with it,
just a short description
of how to use it.
And finally: Where am I?
You may have noticed
that Switch Control
and VoiceOver have cursors
that move around the screen.
So we need to know where
to display that cursor.
So we answer that with
Accessibility Frame.
And that's how we draw the
beautiful cursor we see here.
It's important to
remember that the frame is
in screen coordinates, so
we provide a helper method
to convert from view
to screen coordinates.
Most of the time we assume this
to just be the frame of a view,
so you won't need to touch
this unless you need it
to be something a
little bit more specific.
And that's it!
Those six methods make up the
basic API for UI accessibility,
and that's enough to get
most of accessibility done,
so just a few lines of
code and a few minutes
to make your app
really accessible.
But the really great news
is we do most of the work.
So if you use standard
controls in UIKit,
most of this is done for you.
If you do custom drawing,
we need you to answer
these questions for us
so accessibility users can know
how to interact with your app.
So just that really
small investment
of those six methods will
give you a large reward
of a lot more people being
able to use your app.
So it's not that much to
make something accessible.
So now your convinced:
accessibility, just six methods,
that's easy, how do I do it?
The first step is
design for accessibility.
So when you are thinking
about your app and thinking
about how users will use
the app you are building,
think about Switch
Control and VoiceOver users
and how they will
interact with your app.
But if you have an app already,
like we assume most of you do,
the best way to start is
do an audit of your app
and see how accessible it is
already, because, like I said,
if you use UIKit
standard controls,
most of this should
be done already.
There are a few ways to
do an accessibility audit.
The first one is the
accessibility inspector
in the simulator.
And you turn that on by
going to Settings, General,
Accessibility, and
turning on the inspector,
and you will notice that it
brings up this beautiful window
that answers those six questions
we have been talking about.
So you can quickly spot check
the elements in your app
and make sure they are
responding as you expect.
The best way to check
for accessibility is
to use the accessibility
features on the device,
like VoiceOver and
Switch Control.
And I would love to
do that with you now.
So back in Settings, we can turn
on VoiceOver by going to the top
of Accessibility Settings, but
I would recommend if you are new
to VoiceOver to come down to the
Accessibility shortcut and turn
on VoiceOver, so that way you
can tap the Home button three
times anywhere in
the operating system
to turn VoiceOver on and off.
So if we go back
to the Home screen,
I will tap the Home
button three times.
There is VoiceOver telling
us it's on Messages,
so I will take one finger
and move it around the screen
and VoiceOver will read
what's under my finger.
>> VOICEOVER: weather, clock,
map, videos, wallet, stocks,
reminders, two tasks due today.
Double-tap to open.
>> IAN FISCH: I have a few
more things to do today.
All right.
So if I take one
finger and swipe right,
it will move to the
next element.
>> VOICEOVER: Stocks,
double-tap to open.
>> IAN FISCH: Tell me about
stocks, and if I take one finger
and slide to the left, it will
move to the previous element.
So double-tap with one finger
will activate an element,
so it will bring up Reminders.
And then the only other gesture
that you will need is a
three-finger gesture to scroll,
so I will take three fingers
and scroll to the next,
and previous, element,
and that's it.
Just the few gestures will
control VoiceOver and allow you
to check your app
for accessibility.
Let's take a look at Clock and
check it for accessibility.
>> VOICEOVER: Clock, 9:15
a.m. Double tap to open.
>> IAN FISCH: Double
tap to open.
>> VOICEOVER: Clock,
edit, button.
>> IAN FISCH: When you are doing
an audit, you want to check
that everything has an
accessibility label,
it has a meaningful value.
If its state changes, you want
to swipe through the elements
and make sure that
the order makes sense
so that it's moving
from, generally,
top left to bottom right if you
are in a left-to-right language
and the reverse if you
are in a right-to-left.
So let's swipe through
and listen
to what VoiceOver
finds in this app.
>> VOICEOVER: World clock,
heading, Cupertino, today,
9:16 a.m. Swipe up or down
to select a custom action,
then double-tap to activate.
>> IAN FISCH: So VoiceOver
is telling us the label
and the value.
>> VOICEOVER: Selected,
world clock, tap.
>> IAN FISCH: This has
the Selected trait.
So that's another
trait you can add.
It tells us that there is three
more elements in the tab bar.
>> VOICEOVER: Alarm, tab.
Stopwatch, tab.
Timer, tab.
Four of four.
>> IAN FISCH: So I can swipe
to everything in World Clock,
or at least on this screen,
everything has a label,
a meaningful value.
The traits are set properly.
So this looks pretty
accessible, that's good.
So I will turn off
VoiceOver now.
>> VOICEOVER: Voiceover off.
>> IAN FISCH: Let's
look at an app
that I brought called
QuakeWatch.
I'm from the Bay Area,
which means I'm obsessed
with earthquakes, so I wrote an
app that will track earthquakes
as they happen in real
time around the world.
Great for a native like me.
So you can see that
earthquakes are happening
or have happened recently.
And it will tell you where it
happened, when it happened,
and the text color tells you
the magnitude of the earthquake,
and we even get a
little map view.
So if I tap in, I can look
at the earthquake on
a map, I zoom out.
I should be able to find other
earthquakes, and I can tap
to get more information
about the earthquake.
There is even an Info button
that will take me to USGS
and give me even
more information.
I can tap and hold on a set
of earthquakes to add them
to my favorite list
and even compare them.
Pretty cool app!
Best earthquake app
I have ever seen.
So if I triple-tap
with VoiceOver,
let's see what the VoiceOver
user would see with this app.
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver on,
QuakeWatch, earthquakes,
heading.
>> IAN FISCH: Earthquakes,
heading, so far so good.
>> VOICEOVER: Favorites, button.
>> IAN FISCH: Favorites,
button, that's pretty good.
So these are standard
UIKit controls,
so I get them for free.
That's great.
Now, I will take my one
finger and slide around
and see what we find
with the cells.
[Tapping noise]
So that sound you are hearing
is VoiceOver telling you
that it can't find anything
to touch under that finger,
so the cells aren't accessible.
That's no good.
Let's go into the
favorites, look at that graph.
[Tapping noise]
>> IAN FISCH: It looks like the
graph isn't accessible either.
That's unfortunate,
such a beautiful graph.
So there is one more
gesture that might help you
as you are looking at your app,
if you do a double tap and hold,
VoiceOver will pass through
the touch and just push it
through to whatever
is under your finger.
So even though the
cell isn't accessible,
we can jump in and --
>> VOICEOVER: Earthquake,
shows more info, detail.
>> IAN FISCH: Get to the view.
>> VOICEOVER: Detail,
earthquakes, back button.
Earthquake.
Show more info.
Use the rotor to access
points of interest.
>> IAN FISCH: All right.
Nice.
>> VOICEOVER: Earthquake,
location, 74 kilometers,
felt by zero people,
magnitude 1.50.
Dismiss pop up.
Double-tap to --
>> IAN FISCH: It looks like the
Info button isn't accessible,
so VoiceOver just
doesn't see it.
So it's not very accessible
to a VoiceOver user.
They can't really get to
any of the information,
so it's mostly useless.
Let's turn off VoiceOver.
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver off.
>> IAN FISCH: So
what did we find
with our accessibility audit?
We have got that earthquake
cell that just isn't accessible,
VoiceOver couldn't
see it at all,
and the text color is
communicating magnitude,
which isn't a great way
to communicate magnitude
because not everyone
can see all colors
and it's also just really
ugly and difficult to read,
as you can see with
the yellow here.
There is that map detail
view, where the labels need
to be a little more
specific about their purpose.
And that Info button
is completely invisible
to VoiceOver users.
So that's no good.
But the great news is those six
methods we have been talking
about so far are enough
to fix all of these issues
with just a few lines of
code in a few minutes.
So let's do that together now.
All right.
So here is QuakeWatch and
the first thing we will look
at is that earthquake cell.
The earthquake cell is
written in Swift and the rest
of the p roject is
in Objective-C,
so accessibility works
in both languages
and it can coexist just
like the rest of your code.
So let's see.
It's not accessible.
If we look down, we can see
that the reason it's not
accessible is I'm taking a
string and drawing
it at a point.
So if I used UI labels instead,
this would be accessible for me,
but because I'm drawing
the strings directly
into the view, it's
not accessible.
And then I'm grabbing
the alert color and using
that as the text color
for all of these strings.
So the first thing we
should do is get rid of that
and instead use UI
color black color.
Now, we will all
be able to read it.
Won't that be great?
And now that we aren't using
that for the magnitude,
let's just keep up with that
trend and add a magnitude string
that we draw directly
to the view.
Why not? All right.
So that will take care
of the text color.
How do we make it accessible?
If we come up here to where we
set the earthquake on the cell,
we can grab the date that
the earthquake happened,
and a handy event
description that will tell us
where it happened, and format
it correctly, obviously.
We will set Is Accessibility
Element to True on the cell
so VoiceOver will
be able to find it,
and then we will set the label
to the description
we just built.
Okay. Great!
The only other thing
we might want
to add is a value
for that favorite.
When you add something
to a favorites list,
obviously a VoiceOver user
would want to know that.
Down here where we
toggle the favorite,
we can add a little bit of code
that sets the accessibility
value
to Favorite if it's a favorite.
So let's take a look
at the popover view.
I happen to know it's here.
So it looks like that button
is actually a UI control,
which would explain why
it's not accessible.
If I had used a UI button,
this would be accessible
from the start, but we
need a little bit of help
to make it accessible.
So let's do that now.
So we will take the More Info
button, set Is Accessibility
to Yes, add the Button trait,
and then we'll set the label
to More Info and the
hint to Double-Tap
To View More Information.
And obviously you would
want to localize this,
but for now we will
leave it this way.
The only other thing we want to
do here is set the Header trait
on the location and felt
header, so it's clear what's
in that view and
what information is
being communicated.
That was just a few minutes
of work, and that should clean
up quite a few issues.
Let's build and check it out.
All right.
Let's triple-tap home to
turn VoiceOver back on.
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver on.
FaceTime, QuakeWatch,
double-tap to open,
QuakeWatch, earthquakes,
heading.
>> IAN FISCH: The first
thing you notice is
that ugly yellow
color is finally gone.
Thank goodness!
So let's swipe around with one
finger and see what happens.
>> VOICEOVER: Favorites,
button, 12 kilometers,
Oklahoma, 2015, 10:57 a.m.
>> IAN FISCH: So earthquake
finds the cell now.
That's good if we come
to the detail view.
>> VOICEOVER: Dismiss
earthquake, location, heading.
>> IAN FISCH: Location
now has the heading trait,
so it's clear what's
happening in the view.
>> VOICEOVER: 12 kilometers.
Felt by, heading, zero people.
Magnitude 3.00.
More info, button.
Double-tap to view
more information.
>> IAN FISCH: The More Info
button is now accessible
and tells us how to use
it and what it will do.
Great! Just a few lines of
code and we were able to clean
up the app and make
it pretty accessible.
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver off.
>> IAN FISCH: So where
did we get so far?
The earthquake cell
is now accessible,
we are not communicating
anything
with text color anymore,
which is really great,
that ugly yellow
is finally gone.
The map detail view now
has meaningful traits
on those labels so it's clear
to the VoiceOver user what's
happening and they can navigate
by headings if they like.
That Info button it accessible.
We still need a way to add
something to the favorite list,
and the favorite graph
is still inaccessible.
How would we make
this graph accessible?
So let's start by going back
to those questions we were
talking about earlier.
The first one was:
Do I serve a purpose?
So there is a lot of
information being communicated
in this graph, but not all of
it is really serving a purpose
or really important to the user.
So what's the most
important bits in this graph?
I think that's the points,
because they tell us exactly
what we are comparing,
so that's probably what
we should make accessible.
The next question that's worth
talking about is: Where am I?
So what do we set for
the accessibility frame
for these points?
So you might think
that the orange boxes
that you see now are a
good idea, but if you look
at the view as a whole,
most of it isn't accessible.
So most of it is
just dead space,
and so as a VoiceOver
user slides their finger
around the screen to search for
points, it will be mostly empty.
A better frame might
be something like this.
So a VoiceOver user can
slide his or her finger
across the screen,
and they will hit all
of the points as they do so.
And then as long as we set
the accessibility value
to the magnitude, we
haven't lost anything.
We haven't lost any information.
So that seems like a good plan.
Unfortunately, I happen to know
that the graph view
is just one big view,
and everything is drawn
directly into the view.
So how do we make one view
accessible into multiple parts?
And the good news is we have
got an API for that as well,
UIAccessibility element.
So this is a great way to
create specific objects just
for accessibility to break
up a view into subelements
and still answer those great
six questions we have been
talking about.
The only new part is the
accessibility container,
which you would just set
to the containing view.
Great! So with this API, we
can make the graph accessible.
How do we add something
to that favorite list
so there is something
to display on the graph?
For that I think we should use
Accessibility Perform Magic Tap,
which is this really cool API
to just do the right thing
in the right context.
A good example of that is
when a VoiceOver user
gets a phone call,
they can do the Magic Tap
gesture, which is two fingers,
double-tap on the screen, and
that will do the magic thing,
which is answer the phone call.
So that will allow us to add
something to the favorite list,
but what do we add to the list?
And for that we can
use some brand-new API
in iOS 9 called Accessibility
Focus.
This will allow you to get
the currently focused element
for a given assistive technology
like VoiceOver or
Switch Control.
If you are interested in
tracking focus as it moves
around your app, we
provide a notification
that will tell you the
currently focused element
and the previously
focused element
for a given assistive
technology.
We know what to add
to the favorites list,
we know how to add it, and
then we can explore the graph.
So let's look at
implementing that now.
All right.
Back in Xcode.
So let's add something
to the favorite list.
So if we go to the app delegate,
we can add Accessibility
Perform Magic Tap.
So we will grab the currently
focused element for VoiceOver,
check if that element
responds to toggle favorite,
like the cell, and if it
does, we will ask it to toggle
as favorite and then return Yes.
Otherwise, we return No,
and VoiceOver will do the
next-most-magical thing
in that context,
whatever that may be.
So that will allow us to add
something to the favorite list.
Now, let's look at the graph.
All right.
So it looks like I'm
drawing it with CAShapeLayer,
which is a great way to draw
a graph, but not a great way
to draw an accessible graph.
So down here I'm actually
grabbing the point
and drawing it.
So that seems like a good place
to create my UIAccessibility
element.
So I create a UIAccessibility
element, setting its container
to Self, the graph view.
And then I set its label to a
formatted version of the date.
So we know when it happened.
We will set the value to
the magnitude description.
That's good.
And then like we talked about,
I will take the frame and set it
to slightly wider
than the point,
and the full height
of the graph.
I will set that as the
frame after converting it
to screen coordinates.
And finally add that to
an array that I had ready,
and set that as the
accessibility elements
for the graph view.
So just a few more
lines of code.
Let's see what that looks like.
All right.
So I will triple-tap
Home and start VoiceOver.
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver on.
FaceTime, QuakeWatch.
Double-tap to open.
QuakeWatch.
Earthquakes, heading.
>> IAN FISCH: There's
those beautiful cells.
I will do the Magic Tap
gesture, which is two fingers,
double-tap on the screen.
And there it is,
now it's a favorite.
>> VOICEOVER: 12 kilometers.
California 2015.
11:10 a.m. Favorite.
>> IAN FISCH: It
says it's a favorite.
That's good.
So let's add a few more.
First, we have to wait
for earthquakes to happen.
All right.
Three should be enough.
>> VOICEOVER: Detail,
back button.
>> IAN FISCH: Let's
see what happens
when we swipe around the graph.
>> VOICEOVER: 2005, 2/5, 2015.
Pacific Time.
Magnitude 0.43.
>> IAN FISCH: As I
slide my finger across,
I should hit all of them.
And that's how you make
a graphic accessible,
an earthquake graph
accessible, at least.
So just a few lines of
code, and we were able
to clean all of that up.
Let's take one more look,
we have the earthquake
cell is now accessible,
not using yellow
anymore, thank goodness.
The map detail is accessible.
We can add a favorite
using the Magic Tap,
and we can even explore the
graph and compare earthquakes,
our favorite earthquakes,
at least.
So just a few lines of
code, just a few minutes,
and we were able to take an app
that was completely unusable
for VoiceOver users and make
it probably the most accessible
earthquake tracking
app out there.
Remember that accessibility
is about users.
Thinking about how users
of all abilities will
interact with your app.
Remember everyone that's
going to be using your app
as you are designing it.
Apple has been embracing
accessibility
for so long that's
it's expected of us
that we are fully accessible
with all of the products
and features that we release.
And we really strive hard
to make that possible.
We would like to invite you
to join us in that endeavor
and make the ecosystem as
a whole really accessible.
If you would like more
information, you can search
for UIAccessibility
on developer.apple
or check the developer forums.
We also have an Apple
Watch session later today
and an Accessibility and
Speech Lab right after that.
So you can bring your app,
and we will help you
make certain parts
of your app accessible,
or you can just sit
with an accessibility expert and
go through an audit of your app
and see how accessible
it is already.
So we look forward to
seeing everyone there.
Thanks, have a great conference.
[Applause]