[Cheering and applause]
>> BRITTANY PAINE: Hi, everyone.
My name is Brittany Paine,
and later you will
meet Jon Drummond.
We are engineers on
the SpringBoard team.
Today we are going to talk to
you about optimizing your app
for multitasking
on iPad and iOS 9.
This is actually the third talk
in the series related
to multitasking.
The first two already happened.
If you didn't get a
chance to watch them,
you should go watch them.
So I have a lot to say today.
Jon does too.
We are going to go pretty fast.
Put on your listening ears.
So this is your app.
In iOS 8, your app had the
full device at your disposal.
It could use as much
system resources
as the device had available.
However, in multitasking in iOS
9 this is no longer the case.
There can and probably
will be more
than one app on screen
at a time.
And all of the apps
on screen now have
to share the system resources.
Some system resources
like CPU, GPU,
and disk I/O degrade gradually
as multiple processes
compete for them.
Let's look at an example of CPU.
So for the new developers in
the audience, the Holy Grail
of app responsiveness is to
be able to update your UI
at 60 frames per
second, or 60 FPS.
This means you have
about 16 milliseconds
to get all your work done
in response to a user event.
So if this is your app,
let's say it is doing a great
job rendering at 60 FPS.
It can get all its work done
in only 10 milliseconds.
Each of these slices
represents one millisecond.
Then, the user brings
in a secondary app.
That app is also doing a
great job updating at 60 FPS.
And it gets all its work
finished in 6 milliseconds.
Both apps combined, as you
can see, are already using
up all 16 milliseconds
that we have in order
to be able to render at 60 FPS.
And then the user starts a PiP,
and the PiP is also
doing a great job,
and he needs eight
milliseconds to render his UI.
The combined total
of all three apps
on screen are 24
milliseconds, and that means
that the rendering is actually
at about 40 FIPS instead
of the 60 FIPS that we want.
The user will notice stuttering.
The same type of problem
applies to the GPU.
However, some system resources
like memory can result
in a much worse user experience
when multiple processes
are competing for them.
Look at the example again.
Here is the app again.
Below the iPad is the
system memory footprint.
You can see on the very left
we have the system using some
amount of memory.
In the middle, we have
your app, the blue app,
using some amount of memory.
Then we have all
of this free space.
There is so much
room for activities.
You can do all kind of stuff.
And then, the user
brings in a secondary app,
and the secondary app
needs memory, too.
But we are still in good shape.
We have a tiny bit
of free memory left.
Then guess what happens next?
The PiP happens.
Now we are out of memory.
When the system can't
find free memory,
it has to kill a process.
In that instance, the user gets
ripped out of his or her --
we'll say her --
current context,
and we are taken
back to SpringBoard.
In my opinion, that is a
much worse user experience
than just the stuttering
UI that can happen
when multiple processes
compete for CPU or GPU.
So now you may be asking
yourself, what is SpringBoard,
and why are SpringBoard
engineers here today to talk
to you about multitasking?
Well, SpringBoard
is a lot of things.
It is the Home screen.
The Lock screen.
Icons, wallpaper, system
gestures, notification center.
Control center.
I got lost.
Okay, all of these
things and more.
But most importantly, we are a
UI application just like y'all.
SpringBoard is also the
original multitasking app.
Prior to iOS 9 and
also in iOS 9,
SpringBoard is always considered
to be running in the foreground,
even though your app
is visible to the user.
Because of that, we
face the same challenges
that y'all do today in the
new multitasking environment.
And we've learned a lot
of lessons along the way.
And we would like to share
some of those lessons
with y'all today so you
don't make the same mistakes.
Let's get started.
Optimizing your app, the
easy stuff, part one.
First thing, use the
Leaks instrument and find
and fix your memory leaks.
How many of you have
forgotten to write DIALEK?
There has to be more
hands than that.
Well, I have.
Happens to the best of us.
And the Leaks instrument can
help you find those problems,
and they are usually
really easy to fix.
However, the best way to
avoid leaks is to use Swift.
You should do that instead.
Next, you should use the
Allocations instrument to find
and fix retained cycles and
unbounded memory growth.
Last, you should use the Time
Profiler instrument to find
and fix inefficient algorithms.
I'm not going to talk about
any of these problems today.
These types of problems apply
to all apps, not just apps
that are interested
in multitasking.
Instead, we are going to focus
on the things most important
in the new multitasking
environment.
In our experience, the
biggest lesson we learned is
that great performance
involves trade-offs.
Are you going to precompute
your data and keep it in memory?
Or are you going to calculate
it on the fly and use CPU?
Are you going to keep all your
resources locally on disk?
Or are you going to
keep them in the cloud
and fetch them whenever
you need them?
Are you going to
run your animations
on the CPU or on the GPU?
Let's look at an example
of a sample app we have been
working on called IconReel.
So here is our app
right out of the box.
It starts with a
handful of icons.
When the user taps on an
icon, we zoom up the icon
to show a more detailed view.
There is a sticky
dock at the bottom
where users can save
their favorite icons.
When a user adds more
icons, we add more pages,
and the user can scroll
between the pages.
Does this look familiar
to anyone?
Yeah, that was on purpose
[Laughter]
>> BRITTANY PAINE: So we
can keep all of these icons
in memory because each icon
is only about 60 kilobytes.
We will store them all
in an NSDictionary.
It turns out scrolling is great.
Why? Because we have no
other pages to scroll to.
So some of our users
like to add more icons.
So we add a few dozen more
icons to our NSDictionary.
So far scrolling is okay.
Now, this animation may
look familiar to you.
That's because there
are a lot of apps
that have an animation
like this.
Think of photos scrolling around
in a photos or videos app.
You may have an animation
like this in your app.
Everything is going great.
Some of our really good
customers download even
more icons.
And now we have several dozen
more icons in our NSDictionary,
and it turns out
scrolling is still perfect.
That is, until sometimes we
are seeing IconReel crash,
and sometimes in a multitasking
environment we are seeing other
foreground apps crash.
Let's invest what
is going on here.
We took a time profiler
trace and saw that CPU
and disk I/O were
minimal while scrolling.
But the Allocations instrument
showed us our memory usage was
very high because all of our
icons were kept in memory.
What is happening here is
that IconReel is quickly
exhausting the available system
memory, and when the system
gets short on free memory,
it tries to free some up.
If there's none it can find,
it has to terminate processes.
Sometimes this means
terminating IconReel,
and sometimes this means
terminating another
foreground app.
But all of the time this is
a horrible user experience.
We want to avoid this.
As a good multitasking
citizen, IconReel needs
to get its memory usage
under control so all the apps
on screen can coexist and
create the great user experience
that our users expect.
This brings me to the
idea of the working set.
One of the most important
things you can do
to optimize your memory
usage is to understand
and manage your working set.
Your working set should consist
of only the critical objects
and resources that your
app needs right now.
You should keep it
small in order
to keep your memory usage low.
It might change based
on context.
For example, your working set
may contain different objects
when the app is in
the foreground
versus when the app is in the
background, or it might change
when you change view
controllers.
Last, you shouldn't
let it grow unbounded.
We saw what happens when the
system runs out of memory.
We don't want you
to be that app.
Let's look at IconReel's
working set.
At the end of the last example,
IconReel's working set was every
icon we were keeping in memory.
Is this the best working set?
No. So what do we
really need right now?
Well, all we really need is
the current page of icons
that the user is viewing.
So this is a much
better working set.
So now let's try scrolling
with our working set
of only one page of icons.
Oh! Oh! Okay.
That was horrible.
And if you didn't see it
because maybe I was standing
in your way, scrolling
was horrible.
There was a multisecond
hang before the next page
of icons scrolled into view.
Let's investigate
what is going on.
We took another time profiler
trace, and we saw that CPU
and disk I/O are actually
very high while scrolling,
and Allocation showed us that
our memory usage is very low.
This is the exact opposite
problem from what we just had.
Like I said, great performance
involves making a series
of trade-offs.
What can we do to fix this?
The answer is to manage
our CPU time better.
So the most important
thing you can do
to keep your app responsive
is to do as little work
as possible on your main thread.
The main thread's top priority
is to respond to user events,
and doing unnecessary work
on your main thread means
that the main thread has less
time to respond to user events.
Because you're sharing the
CPU time with all of the apps
on screen, you need
to be hyperaware
of what your main
thread is doing.
Any work being performed on the
main thread that is not directly
in response to a user event
should be performed elsewhere.
What tools can we use to make
sure that we keep responding
to user events but also make
sure we get the extra work
finished in a timely manner?
Well, the answer is we can use
GCD and Quality of Service.
There was a great talk
last year at WWDC 2014,
and there's a great talk
coming up on Friday on GCD
and Quality of Service.
So I'm not going to go
into a lot of detail here.
There's two important things.
The first thing is that
your main thread is running
at the highest priority, that's
the user interactive priority.
The other thing is
that the Quality
of Service bands are shared
across all foreground
applications.
So everyone's user-initiated
queues get equal access
to the CPU, and everyone's
background queues get equal
access to the CPU.
No single foreground app is
prioritized above any other.
If you prioritize your
work appropriately,
the system can guarantee
that we get the best possible
performance while there are
multiple apps on screen.
So how does this
apply to IconReel?
Well, we are going
to load the icons
on a separate thread using GCD
at the user-initiated
Quality of Service.
The first thing we do, we
create our dispatch queue,
called Icon Generation Queue,
and it's a serial queue.
While we are on the main thread,
we're going to dispatch async,
generating each icon on the
next page onto our icon queue.
It isn't obvious from
this code snippet,
but dispatch asyncing work
from the main thread to a queue
like this downgrades
the quality of service
to the user-initiated
quality of service,
which is the second-highest
quality of service.
So this code is effectively
loading all the icons
at the user-initiated
quality of service.
Okay. So let's try
scrolling again.
All right.
That was better.
This solution could work
for you and your apps
if your design allows for it.
Let's say you can show
placeholder images while you are
waiting for the real
content to load.
However, IconReel's design
doesn't allow for it.
We have to have the icon
already loaded before it scrolls
on screen.
So what we really
need, we need a way
to temporarily boost the
icon generation queue
up to the same priority
as the main thread,
right before the icon
scrolls on to screen
so that it can finish
generating the icon faster.
There's a way to do that, too.
It's by using the quality
of service overrides.
This comes in handy when we have
this type of priority inversion
where we have a high-priority
thread or queue blocked,
waiting on a low-priority thread
or queue to finish some work.
And the awesome part
is that quality
of service overrides can
happen for you automatically
if you provide the system
with enough information.
You may be thinking: Brittany,
how can I provide the system
with enough information?
Well, here is a handy chart.
Again, the talk from last
year and the talk coming
up on Friday go into
this in more depth.
But the take-home here is
that Dispatch Group Wait
and Dispatch Semaphore
Wait are not your friends.
You should audit your code
for uses of these functions
and be aware that they
don't fix these types
of priority inversions.
So let's look at what we
are going to do in IconReel.
Right before that first column
of icons scroll on screen,
on the main thread we are going
to dispatch sync this empty
block onto our icon queue.
What that will do is boost
the priority of the icon queue
up to match the priority
of the main thread
until that block executes,
at which point the
icon queue will go back
down to its normal priority.
Now let's look at scrolling
and see what it looks like.
Oh, yeah, looks great,
with a nice slow swipe.
So let's try a slow swipe
followed by a fast swipe.
Oh, man! We are right
back to where we started
where that next page, there's
like a hang before
it comes on screen.
So now what?
There is a pattern here.
Pulled out Instruments again.
We took another trace.
This time we also
got a calculator,
and we did some math, and we
found that we just can't load,
read the icon image from
disk, decode the icon image,
and make the icon nice and
pretty in the amount of time
that it takes for a fast user
to swipe to the next page.
So now what?
I guess we can just
wait for faster devices.
[Laughter]
[Applause]
>> BRITTANY PAINE:
Some applause for that.
Just kidding.
We can do better.
We have to be smarter.
Math calculations told us
we would have much better
performance if we
had the next page
of icons already
loaded in memory.
This ensures that even when
you are scrolling quickly
through multiple pages,
we have enough time
to load the next page of icons
before the user can swipe again.
So let's increase our
working set size from one page
to three pages: the page
you're currently viewing
and the page on either side.
We don't have a magic
eight ball.
So we don't know which way
the user is about to scroll.
Having one page on either side
seems like the best compromise.
Now let's try scrolling.
All right.
That looks much better.
Now by the time the user
gets to the next page,
we've already started loading
the next page of icons.
However, this actually
increases our memory usage.
When we had our working set
that contained only one page,
we had this memory footprint.
Now we have this
memory footprint.
We need to be aware of how
we are affecting other apps.
So now let's look at what
happens when the user brings
in a secondary app with
IconReel already on screen.
IconReel resizes to show only
three columns instead of four.
This is a great opportunity
to reassess our working set.
Do we still need three
pages of four columns
of icons in memory at a time?
No. We only need three
pages of three columns
of icons in memory at a time.
So effectively it looks
a little bit like this.
Now, I could go through
and manually throw away
those extra columns of icons
that we don't need
anymore, but it was a lot
of work to generate them.
I don't want to redo
it if I don't have to.
It would be great
if there was a place
where I could put
these icons where,
if the system needed the memory,
we could get rid of them.
If the system didn't need the
memory, then they could stay
in memory for us so that
we could use them again
when we need them.
There is a way to do that,
and that is by listening
to memory warnings.
Memory warnings happen when the
system is under memory pressure
or your process is
approaching its memory limit.
I'd really like to give you
a number that you could code
to for your memory limit.
Unfortunately, there's
no such number.
The limit is different
per device
and per application context.
So my best advice
is to just listen
for memory warnings
and do things.
So what should you do?
Well, you should remove anything
not in your working set.
This includes clearing cache
data, releasing images,
and releasing view controllers.
Here is the APIs that
you can use to listen
for memory warnings, and I
want to make it clear that none
of these are new in iOS 9.
They have been around
for a while.
Hopefully y'all are
already using all of them.
I could go through on a memory
warning and manually get rid
of these icons myself.
I'm lazy and don't
want to do that.
It would be great if there was a
tool that managed all that crap
for me so I didn't
have to do it.
Turns out we have
one of those, too.
It is called NSCache.
It is similar to an
NSDictionary, and it's great
for objects that can
be re-created quickly.
It also handles the
memory warnings for you
by automatically evicting items
from itself, and it's also aware
of application context like
foreground versus background
and evicts items when necessary.
It does other cool stuff,
too, but we don't have time
to talk about that today.
Make sure to check out
the NSCache documentation.
Now when we have IconReel
up in a split view,
instead of throwing
away these icons,
let's put them in an NSCache.
In fact, let's just put every
icon we ever generate that's not
in our working set in NSCache.
And when we have
a memory warning,
we can let NSCache do all the
work of evicting all those icons
that are not in our working set.
Let's recap.
We started here, where we
had every icon in memory.
So our memory usage was high,
but scrolling was great and CUP
and disk I/O were low.
But sometimes we were
seeing apps crash,
and that is not good.
So then we adjusted our working
set size to only one page
of icons, so the memory
usage was low, but our CPU
and disk I/O were very
high while scrolling,
and this resulted in crappy
scrolling performance.
Then, we revised our working set
size to be three pages of icons,
which increased our
memory usage a little bit.
And then every other icon
that we generated that was not
in our working set we
threw into NSCache.
We have increased our
overall memory usage,
but most of our increase
is now adaptable
to the surrounding
circumstances.
For many of you this
is good enough.
If your app can run in a
multitasking environment
with Maps running Flyover, then
you are probably in great shape.
I presented a bunch of things
that your app can do today
to be a good multitasking
citizen,
but sometimes these
things are not enough.
To talk to you about
what you should do next,
I would like to present
Jon Drummond.
[Applause]
>> JON DRUMMOND:
Thank you, Brittany.
Hi, everybody.
So understanding how your
app uses memory can pay off
tremendously for both
your app's performance
and the rest of the system.
But sometimes that
just isn't enough.
What if you are doing
everything we talked about
and doing it all correctly, but
things are still going wrong?
We will talk about some ways
to be even more adaptive
with the way that your apps
manage their memory footprint.
To start, I would like to go
back to the multitasking example
where we have a primary
and a secondary app.
We are under memory
pressure right now,
so the system issues a
memory warning and the apps,
being good multitasking
citizens, will take care
of trimming their caches and
other objects they don't need.
Great. Now, the user
brings in a PiP, okay?
We have space, it's good.
We are not under pressure,
but we are getting close.
Now the user goes and
resizes the secondary app
to be fifty-fifty
with the primary.
This causes a spike in memory
growth, and CPU for that matter.
The system did not have
time to react to this.
Unfortunately, it was forced
to kill the primary app here
even though the primary app was
not the cause of
the memory growth.
Dropping back into SpringBoard
is never a good experience,
as Brittany showed us.
Before I finish or
keep going here,
I want to share a
quote with you.
That is that "the world outside
your process should be regarded
as hostile and bent
upon your destruction."
I don't mean that to sound
ominous and I don't want you
to think I'm paranoid, but part
of being a good multitasking
citizen is adapting
to everything that is
happening around you.
Sometimes what is happening
around you is extreme.
You might be doing
everything fine,
but the system might
conspire to terminate you.
It is not really, but being
prepared for this kind
of situation will
help you survive.
So first things first.
Memory is the most
constrained resource on iOS.
That is not to say that other
resources are not constrained.
They are, but they just
degrade differently.
When the system runs
out of memory,
it's like hitting a wall.
Something has to go.
It's got to get the memory back.
As we saw from the
previous example,
sometimes the system can
acquire memory faster
than it can be released.
Even if we had time to issue
a memory warning there,
and even if the apps, all
three of them running,
had time to respond
to it, it's not clear
that they would have
had enough CPU cycles
to actually do something
meaningful and clean
up enough memory to
accommodate the growth.
To understand how the
system can reclaim memory,
we have to understand
how memory is classified.
I'm going to break it down
into three different groups,
the first of which
we call dirty.
This is memory in active
use by your process.
These are your objects, these
are your heap allocations,
statics, globals,
everything you have cached,
actually pretty much everything.
And it is not reclaimable
by the system
because it's in use by you.
The second is called purgeable.
This is otherwise dirty memory
that has been explicitly marked
as not in use by the app,
so the system knows it can
take it back if needed.
The third type we call clean,
and that is read-only memory
that is backed by files on disk.
The system can reclaim
the memory
because it can always bring it
back because the file is there.
Back to our system memory bars.
What does this look like?
We have a scenario with very,
very little free memory.
But it doesn't look
like that to the system.
The system knows it has leeway
to use anytime it wants to free
up memory for growth,
and it can do this
without issuing memory warnings
or requiring the
apps to intervene.
The goals for your app and for
adapting the memory usage here
are minimize your dirty memory
and maximize your
purgeable and clean memory.
We are going to start
with minimizing dirty.
First, yeah, use less of it.
I know that's really easy for
me to say standing up here,
but if you manage
your working set
and track the objects you are
allocating, use Instruments,
do all that, once you've taken
care of that, the next step is
about reclassifying this
dirty memory as purgeable.
If you do this, it can be
automatically reclaimed
by the system, and it is
best for nice-to-have data,
data that you don't need right
now, might need in the future,
and anything you might otherwise
put in a cache, for example.
Let's apply this to IconReel.
This resembles the
scenario we left off.
We have caches of icons on
either side in our working set.
For this example, I'm going
to reclassify our data a bit.
Rather than working
on a per-icon chunk,
I'm going to group the
icons into sets of columns,
just because it makes
this a bit easier here
but it doesn't otherwise
change the dynamic of our app.
As the user scrolls around,
we update our working set,
things get cached,
things get pulled
out of the cache,
it's all the same.
Let's classify this memory use.
First, we've got
our memory in use.
Classified as dirty.
That's our working set.
We've got all the objects in
our caches, those are purgeable.
This presents us with an
interesting opportunity
to be even fancier with
the way we classify memory.
Let's, for example, mark even
more of the data as in use
or dirty, even some
that's in the cache.
What this has done for us
is introduced a second level
of caching.
The first one, the
outside-most icons,
the ones we are least
likely to need soon,
we'll let the system reclaim
whenever the system needs it.
We don't care.
But we'd like to
retain some control
over icons we might need soon.
So even though they're
still in the cache,
we're going to mark them in use
so the system can't take
them without asking.
These are the ones we'll release
when we respond to
a memory warning.
This leaves us with
the working set,
which we absolutely
need right now,
and there's nothing
to do about that.
What does this look like in
the multitasking example?
I'll return to the scenario
where things went wrong before.
The PiP has come in.
We're out of memory.
But now, the system knows
that both the primary
and the secondary app, being
good multitasking citizens,
have this region of purgeable
memory that can be cleared.
The system, without asking
or telling anybody anything,
can take that from the app
and return the system
to a good state.
But of course, the user
keeps using the device
and memory grows again.
We have another memory warning.
But since the apps have only
lost the purgeable data,
they are free to respond to
memory warnings and clear
up the caches, thus returning
the system to a good state.
How can you use purgeable
data in your apps?
It is simple.
There's a class, and
it's Purgeable Data.
And it is a subclass
of NS immutable data
with no other properties,
it is simple.
The only additions are
these three methods,
the first being Begin
Content Access.
This tells the system
you are using the memory,
and don't take it away from me.
The second, to go along with
it, is End Content Access.
The memory is now
considered purgeable,
and you may lose it at any time.
And the third, to figure out if
the system has taken it from you
when you weren't using it.
To return to the system resource
bars, this is pretty much
where we left off with Brittany.
I haven't changed anything.
The height of these
bars is all the same.
What we have done is take a
segment of our adaptive memory
and reclassified
it as purgeable.
This has made us a much
better multitasking citizen
because the system can do
work for us on our behalf
but has the same intrinsic
performance characteristic
where, if I've lost
my purgeable memory
and I've cleared my caches,
what am I going to do now?
I need to rebuild
any data I need,
and we've established
that's very expensive.
Disk I/O and CPU
spike, that's not great.
Let's, though, analyze the
data we use in our app to see
if there's something
more we can do with that.
Well, what is the data
that IconReel uses?
Well, they are icons,
and the first property is
that they are absolutely
essential.
We don't have an app
if we don't have icons.
At some point, the user
will scroll to them.
We need them.
No getting away from it.
Second, they are
expensive to generate.
Read them off the
disk, decode them,
do nice rounded corners,
whatever you want.
Expensive.
The third point, though, they
can actually be precomputed.
We know ahead of time what
the images are going to be.
If we have the spare cycles,
we can calculate them.
And the last point is that
they are largely static.
There is a very,
very good chance
if I pregenerated something,
it is going to be the same
when I actually need it because
it doesn't change frequently.
All of these points combine
to make this data a perfect
candidate for caching to a file.
Before I move on from this,
I want to make the point
this is still a cache even
if it's a file.
Don't go writing such caches
to the user's documents folder.
Keep it for your
app's cache folder
or the system's temp directory.
Back to our system resources.
We just introduced a new one.
That is disk space.
We can trade some CPU cycles
up front to generate the data,
save it off, and then when we
actually need to pull it in,
we virtually eliminated the
need for the CPU at all.
Now, you may have noticed
that I/O went up a bit there
because the fully rendered
images may be larger
than the source files.
That's okay.
These things are all
about trade-offs.
That leads me directly to
maximizing clean memory.
You may recall I said earlier
that memory backed by a file
on disk is considered clean.
Well, we have a file
on disk now.
What a coincidence.
Data in such a file
can be memory mapped.
The system will allocate
a chunk of memory for you
that directly maps the file, the
contents of the file, on disk.
It is most definitely
worth noting that memory
in the file contents
must match exactly.
You cannot memory map a file
that needs further decoding,
or what have you,
after it is loaded in.
This is ideal for read-only
data, as I mentioned,
that doesn't change frequently.
The coolest part about
all of this is the same
with purgeable memory,
the system can reclaim any
free memory from you as needed.
But, it is not gone.
When you need it again,
when you access again,
the system loads it
back from the disk,
and it's like it
never went away.
Furthermore, it has great
random access properties.
Just because your working set
is here and you need a piece
of data over here,
doesn't matter.
The system can just read
that portion of the file,
hand it off to you,
and you're good to go.
What does this look like?
We start with our
data in memory.
And you write it out to disk.
The system now considers
this, that memory map.
If you go to access a chunk
of it, all it does is load
that in, hand it off to you.
When you are not using it
anymore, it takes it away.
How can we apply
this to IconReel?
We'll start with the working
set, but actually we are going
to combine the working set
with every other icon
image we generated
and create one big data
file and write that to disk.
Now, back in our app, we
bring back our working set.
Three pages.
We access those three
pages of memory,
and the system just loads
only that portion of the file
into memory for us, keeping
the rest of this clean.
Doesn't matter if that file goes
out for hundreds of megabytes.
It is not there in memory.
As we scroll around,
the same happens.
System loads in the
data we need.
Say if we introduce a feature
that shows notifications
for icons that may be
elsewhere on the home screen,
we can pull those
in without worrying
about where they
are, what they are.
Virtual memory system does
all the heavy lifting for us.
How does this change our
system resource bars?
We've already killed CPU there.
But now our cache
is actually on disk.
So that goes away, too.
And now our only memory
footprint is the working set.
Everything else is
considered clean
and thus does not
count against us.
It is also worth noting that we
effectively eliminated the CPU
requirements on both
the front and back end
of our data's life cycle.
We no longer need CPU
to generate data to show
to the user, nor do we
need CPU to clean it
up in response to
memory warnings.
The system is doing
all of that for us.
How can you use memory map data?
Once again, it's a
simple API on NSData.
There are some options
you can use
to initialize the data object.
If you specified the mapped
option in your initializer,
you will get a memory
map data file.
I would be remiss, however,
if I did not mention
that there were caveats
with using this system.
The first being that
it is not appropriate
for small chunks of data.
The virtual memory
itself works on pages,
which are small chunks of data.
If yours are even smaller,
you will introduce problems
that overshadow what you are
actually trying to solve.
Furthermore, from
memory map files,
if you memory mapped a
thousand icon files, say,
there is actually a limit to the
open files any process can have.
You can get yourself
into trouble that way.
That's one of the main reasons
in our examples we grouped
the data into larger chunks
to make it more manageable
for the VM system.
You can also just misuse
the virtual memory system.
Each purgeable data object
you create creates a region
in your virtual memory space.
If you create too many of
these memory map files, too,
you can fragment
your entire space.
You can similarly exhaust it.
If you decide to memory map
a file that is ten gigabytes,
you're going to run
out of space entirely.
Unfortunately, abusing the
virtual memory system results
in your process being
terminated,
which is what we are here to
avoid in the first place, right?
In order to give the best
multitasking experience
to the user, it is really
important to understand the data
and the characteristics of
the data that your app uses.
You must be able to
differentiate nice-to-have data
from the essential data
you need right now.
Can your data be precomputed?
How expensive is
it to re-create?
How frequently does it change?
Understanding this about the
data you use can help you pick
the right tools to make your
memory as adaptable as possible.
Together we can improve
the adaptivity of our apps
and provide the best
multitasking experience
for our users.
In the coming weeks, as
you're update your apps
for multitasking in iOS 9,
I hope you keep these
topics in mind.
First, using Instruments
to identify and fix bugs.
This is the easy stuff.
Your leaks, inefficient
data structures, algorithms,
abandoned memory, too.
Get that stuff fixed.
Second, prioritize
your work appropriately
and don't block the main thread.
I don't know how many of
you caught the first session
in this series, but the system
may actually terminate you
for blocking the main
thread for too long.
It is best to understand
where your work should
go and put it there.
The third was identifying and
managing your working set,
and be aware that this
working set may change based
on the application's
current executing context:
are you foreground, are you
background, are you a PiP?
Understand where
you are right now
because your working set
is likely not the same.
The fourth is to use caches and
response to memory warnings.
This is the basics for being
a good multitasking citizen.
Please respond to them.
Next, leverage the
virtual memory system,
which is what we talked about.
Understand the data
characteristics of your app,
and see if you can
leverage these tools
to let the system manage
your memory for you.
The last is that great
performance requires trade-offs.
Your apps have requirements.
The apps running next to
you have requirements.
The system has limitations.
Identify ways your app can
adapt to the environment
with more constrained
resources as this is the key
to improving the user
experience for everybody.
Because I started with a quote,
I'm going to end with one.
I found this on the Internet.
Allegedly attributed to Charles
Darwin: "It is not the strongest
or most intelligent who survive,
but those who can
best manage change."
Multitasking is about
adapting, and the apps
that best adapt are going
to provide the best
user experience.
For more information I
really encourage you to check
out the documentation.
There's a new Adopting
Multitasking guide
that is great.
Technical support,
come to the forums.
If you have any general
questions,
there's Curt Rothert,
contact him.
He's also an ex-SpringBoard
engineer, by the way,
so I'm sure he would
love to hear from you.
[Laughter]
We had two sessions
earlier in this track.
I encourage you to watch them.
There are also Performance
and GCD talks coming up.
Thank you, everybody,
for coming out!
I can't wait to see your apps!
[Applause]