[Applause]
&gt;&gt; JESSE DONALDSON:
Hi, everyone.
Thanks for coming.
My name is Jesse, and I am
responsible for Auto Layout
in the AppKit and
Foundation frameworks.
Layout is one of the
most fundamental tasks
that we perform when we build an
application, and Auto Layout is
about the neatest thing ever,
but sometimes it can seem kind
of mysterious, and so today I
want to look at a few aspects
of Auto Layout that are
less well understood and go
through them in some detail.
This is the second part
of our two-part series,
and here's a brief list
of the topics we're
going to be looking at.
I would like to start
with the layout cycle.
You probably know how to
configure your user interface,
but Auto Layout can still be
a little bit of a black box.
You kind of configure things,
you run your application,
you get some layout.
Hopefully it's the layout that
you want, but if it's not,
it can be hard to
know where to look.
So I want to look at what
happens in the middle here,
how we actually go from
having constraints on the view
to having the frames
assigned to those views.
So here is a high-level
overview of the process.
We start with the application
run loop cheerfully iterating
until the constraints
change in such a way
that the calculated layout
needs to be different.
This causes a deferred
layout pass to be scheduled.
When that layout pass
eventually comes around,
we go through the hierarchy
and update all the
frames for the views.
This is a little abstract, so
I made a simple example here.
The idea is that when we
uncheck this top checkbox,
we'll modify a constraint
to shrink the window
and hide the checkboxes
on the bottom.
So we start with frames
looking like this.
When we change the constraint,
the layout engine's notion
of where everything is
has already changed,
but the UI hasn't updated yet.
And then when the
layout pass comes along,
the UI actually changes to
match what the engine thinks
should be.
So let's talk about
constraint changes.
The constraints that
you create are converted
to mathematical expressions and
kept inside the Layout Engine.
So a constraints change
is really just anything
that affects these expressions,
and so that includes some
of the obvious things
like activating
or deactivating constraints
or changing the priority
or the constant on a constraint,
but also less obvious things
like manipulating
the view hierarchy
or reconfiguring certain
kinds of controls.
Because those may cause
constraint changes indirectly.
So what happens when
a constraint changes?
Well, the first thing
that happens is
that the Layout Engine
will recompute the layout.
These expressions are made up of
variables that represent things
like the origin or the
size of a particular view.
And when we recalculate
the layout,
these variables may
receive new values.
When this happens, the views
that they represent
are notified,
and they mark their
superview as needing layout.
This is actually what causes
the deferred layout pass
to be scheduled.
So if we look at
the example here,
this is where you see
the frame actually change
in the Layout Engine but not
yet in the view hierarchy.
So when the deferred
layout pass comes along,
the purpose of this, of course,
is to reposition any views
that are not in the right place.
So when we are finished,
everything is in the right spot.
And a pass is actually a
little bit of a misnomer.
There are a couple of
passes that happen here.
The first is for
updating constraints.
The idea with this
is to make sure
that if there are any pending
changes to constraints,
they happen now, before
we go to all the trouble
to traverse the view hierarchy
and reposition all the views.
And then the second pass is when
we do that view repositioning.
So let's talk about
update constraints.
Views need to explicitly request
that their update
constraints method be called.
And this pretty much works the
same way as setNeedsDisplay.
You call
setNeedsUpdateConstraints,
and then some time later your
update constraints method will
be called.
Really, all this is is a way
for views to have a chance
to make changes to
constraints just in time
for the next layout pass, but
it's often not actually needed.
All of your initial constraint
setup should ideally happen
inside Interface Builder.
Or if you really
find that you need
to allocate your
constraints programmatically,
some place like viewDidLoad
is much better.
Update constraints is really
just for work that needs
to be repeated periodically.
Also, it's pretty
straightforward
to just change constraints when
you find the need to do that;
whereas, if you take
that logic apart
from the other code that's
related to it and you move it
into a separate method that
gets executed at a later time,
your code becomes a lot harder
to follow, so it will be harder
for you to maintain,
it will be a lot harder
for other people to understand.
So when would you need to
use update constraints?
Well, it boils down
to performance.
If you find that just
changing your constraints
in place is too slow,
then update constraints might
be able to help you out.
It turns out that changing
a constraint inside update
constraints is actually faster
than changing a constraint
at other times.
The reason for that is
because the engine is able
to treat all the constraint
changes that happen
in this pass as a batch.
This is the same kind of
performance benefit that you get
by calling activate
constraints on an entire array
of constraints as
opposed to activating each
of those constraints
individually.
One of the common
patterns where we find
that this is really useful
is if you have a view
that will rebuild constraints
in response to some kind
of a configuration change.
It turns out to be very common
for clients of these kinds
of views to need to configure
more than one property,
so it's very easy
for the view, then,
to end up rebuilding its
constraints multiple times.
That's just a lot
of wasted work.
It's much more efficient in
these kinds of situations
to have the view just call
setNeedsUpdateConstraints
and then when the update
constraints pass comes along,
it can rebuild its
constraints once
to match whatever the
current configuration is.
In any case, once
this pass is complete,
we know the constraints are
all up-to-date, we are ready
to proceed with repositioning
the views.
So this is where we
traverse the view hierarchy
from the top down, and
we'll call layoutSubviews
on any view marked
as needing layout.
On OS X, this method
is called layout,
but the idea is the same.
The purpose is for the receiver
to reposition its subviews.
It's not for the receiver
to reposition itself.
So what the framework
implementation does is it will
read frames for the subviews
out of the Layout Engine
and then assign them.
On the Mac we use setFrame for
this, and on iOS, it's setBounds
and setCenter, but
the idea is the same.
So if we look at
the example again,
this is where you
actually see the UI update
to match the frames that
are in the Layout Engine.
One other note about
layoutSubviews:
A lot of people will override
this in order to get some kind
of a custom layout, and it's
fine if you need to do this,
but there are some things
that you need to know
because it can be very
easy to do things here
that can get you into trouble.
So I want to look at this
in a little more detail.
You should really only need
to override layoutSubviews
if you need some
kind of a layout
that just can't be
expressed using constraints.
If you can find a way to
do it using constraints,
that's usually more
robust, more trouble free.
If you do choose to override
this, you should keep in mind
that we're in the middle of the
layout ceremony at this point.
Some views have already
been laid out,
other views haven't been, but
they probably will be soon,
and so it's a bit of
a delicate moment.
There are some special
rules to follow.
One is that you need to invoke
the superclass implementation.
We need that for various
bookkeeping purposes.
Also, it's fine to
invalidate the layout of views
within your subtree, but you
should do that before you call
through to the superclass
implementation.
Second, you don't want to call
setNeedsUpdateConstraints.
There was an update
constraints pass.
We went through that,
we finished it, and
so we missed it.
If we still need it
now, it's too late.
Also, you want to make sure
you don't invalidate the layout
of views outside your subtree.
If you do this, it
can be very easy
to cause layout feedback
loops where the act
of performing layout
actually causes the layout
to be dirtied again.
Then we can just end
up iterating forever,
and that's no fun for anybody.
You'll often find inside
a layoutSubviews override
that you need to modify
constraints in order
to get your views in the right
places, and that's fine too,
but again, you need
to be careful.
It can be difficult to predict
when you modify a
constraint what other views
in the hierarchy
might be affected.
So if you are changing
constraints, it's very easy
to accidentally invalidate
layout outside your subtree.
In any case, assuming that
all this goes smoothly,
layout cycle is complete at
this point, everything is
in the right place, and our
constraints change has been
fully applied.
So some things to remember
about the layout cycle: First,
don't expect view frames
to change immediately
when you modify a constraint.
We've just been through
this whole process
about how that happens later.
And if you do find that you
need to override layoutSubviews,
be very careful to avoid
layout feedback loops
because they can
be a pain to debug.
So next I'd like to talk about
how Auto Layout interacts
with the Legacy Layout system.
Traditionally we positioned
views just by setting the frame,
then we have an autoresizingMask
that specifies how the
view should be resized
when its superview changes size.
Then under Auto Layout, we just
do everything with constraints.
And in fact, subframe
doesn't even work the way you
might expect.
You can still set the
frame of view, but --
and it will move
where you put it,
but that frame may be
overwritten at any time
if a layout pass comes along and
the framework copies the frame
from the Layout Engine and
applies it to that view.
The trouble with this is
that sometimes you just
need to set the frame.
For example, if you are
overriding layoutSubviews,
you may need to set the
frame of those views.
And so luckily, there's
a flag for that.
It's called
translatesAutoResizingMask
IntoConstraints [without space].
It's a bit of a mouthful, but it
pretty much does what it says.
It makes views behave
the way that they did
under the Legacy Layout system
but in an Auto Layout world.
So if you set the frame
on a view with this flag,
the framework will actually
generate constraints
that enforce that frame
in the Layout Engine.
What this means is that you
can set the frame as often
as you like, and you
can count on Auto Layout
to keep the view
where you put it.
Furthermore, these constraints
actually implement the behavior
of the autoresizingMask.
So if you have some portion of
your application, for example,
that isn't updated to Auto
Layout yet and you are depending
on this auto-resizing behavior,
it should still behave
the way that you expect.
And finally, by actually
using the Auto Layout Engine
to enforce the frame that
you set, it makes it possible
to use constraints to
position other views relative
to this one.
Since you set the frame,
you can't move the view
around itself, but if we
didn't tell the Layout Engine
where this view needed to be,
then as soon as you reference it
with a constraint, we
can run into problems
where you'll see the size or
the origin collapse to zero.
And that kind of behavior
can be very confusing
if you are not expecting it.
So another note here is
that when you are planning
to position your view
using constraints,
you need to make sure
that this is off.
And if you are building your
UI in Interface Builder,
it will take good care of you
and set this flag appropriately.
But if you are allocating
your UI programmatically,
this actually defaults
to being on.
It needs to because
there's just a lot of code
that allocates a view
and then expects it
to behave in a certain way.
So it defaults to on, and if
you are allocating your UI
programmatically and you
forget to turn this off,
it can cause a number
of unexpected problems.
Let's look at what
happens if you forget.
So this is a pretty
simple piece of code.
We just allocate a
button and configure it,
and then we create
two constraints
that position this button
ten points from the top,
ten points from the left.
So it's very straightforward,
but if you run it,
this is what you get.
The window is too small,
it doesn't behave the way
that you expect, the button
is nowhere to be seen.
And you get all this
spew in the console.
So there's actually a hint
about the problem in this spew.
You can see this is an
NSAutoresizingMaskLayout
Constraint [without space].
This is the class
of layout constraint
that the framework
will create for views
that have
translatesAutoResizingMask
IntoConstraints [without
space] set.
What actually happened
here is because we forgot
to clear this flag, the
framework generated constraints
for the initial frame
on this button.
That frame was empty, the origin
and the size were both zero,
so it's not very useful,
but the real problem came
up when we then added
constraints to try
to position the button at 10,10.
It can't be at 0,0 and
10,10 simultaneously,
so the Layout Engine
suddenly can't satisfy all the
constraints, and things go
wrong in unexpected ways.
If we go back to the code
and we just add a line
to clear this flag, then
things get much better.
We get the layout that we
are expecting, the button is
in the right place, the window
behaves the way we would expect.
So some things to keep in mind
about translatesAutoResizingMask
IntoConstraints [without space]:
You usually won't need this
flag at all, but if you find
that you have a view
that you need to position
by setting the frame directly,
then this will help you out.
And again, if you are
planning to position things
with constraints, you need
to make sure that this is off
if you are not using
Interface Builder.
So next I'd like to talk
about constraint creation.
We can do that most easily,
I think, just by looking
at the code we just
had up on the screen,
specifically the
piece at the end,
where we are building
these constraints.
This is the same constraint
factory method that we've had
since the beginning
of Auto Layout,
and it's perfectly effective,
but it can be a little
bit awkward to use.
The code is pretty verbose,
and it's a little bit
difficult to read.
What we are really trying
to express here is just
that we want to position the
button ten points from the top
and ten points from the left.
But in order to understand
that, you need to read
through this code
pretty carefully and kind
of put the pieces together.
So in the new release
of OS X and iOS,
we are introducing a
new, more concise syntax
for creating constraints.
Here is what it looks like.
This syntax works using
objects called layout anchors.
[Applause]
Thanks. I am glad you like them.
[Laughter]
A layout anchor represents
a particular attribute
of a particular view, and
anchor objects expose a variety
of factory methods for creating
different forms of constraints.
So in this case we see we are
constraining the top anchor
to be the same as the top
anchor of the view plus ten.
If you are working
in Objective-C still,
they are available
there as well,
and the difference is
even more striking.
We go from nearly seven
lines down to just two.
So this new syntax
still conforms
to all our naming conventions,
but it reads a lot more
like an expression and, I
think, makes it a lot easier
to see the intent of the code.
All valid forms of constraints
can be created using this
syntax, and you'll actually even
get compiler errors for many
of the invalid forms
of constraints.
So at the moment, you only
get the errors in Objective-C,
but they will be
coming to Swift as well.
For example, it doesn't
make sense to say
that the leading edge
of a view should be 100
because there's no context in
which to interpret that 100.
So you get an error that
this method isn't available
on a location anchor.
Similarly, it doesn't make
sense to say the leading edge
of your view is the same as
the width of a different view.
Locations and sizes are
fundamentally incompatible types
in Auto Layout, so you get
an incompatible pointer type.
So previously, these
things were still errors,
but they would only
show up at runtime,
so I think making them compile
time errors will help us all get
our constraints right
the first time,
as well as write more readable,
more maintainable code.
[Applause]
So next I'd like to talk about
constraining negative space.
There are a few different
kinds of layouts that come
up from time to time where it's
not immediately obvious how
to achieve them.
Here's a couple examples.
In the first case here, the goal
is to make sure that the space
between these buttons
remains the same
when the window is resized.
And in the bottom, we
have an image and a label,
and we want to center
them as a group rather
than center each piece of
the content individually.
So it turns out that
the solution
to these layout problems
is the same,
and that's to use dummy views.
We actually allocate empty
views, and we constrain them
to fill the spaces
between the buttons.
Once we have views
in these spots,
we can use an equal width
constraint to make sure
that their size remains the
same as the window is resized.
And in the bottom case,
we can do the same thing.
We use an empty view, and
we constrain it to the edges
of the image and the label,
and then we can place
a centering constraint
on that empty view
rather than on any
of the content views themselves.
So this works, and it's how
we've traditionally solved these
layout problems, but
it's a little bit
of an obscure trick, right?
And it's also inefficient,
especially on iOS,
where every view has a
layer associated with it.
And so in the new release,
we are exposing a new public
class for layout guides.
A layout guide simply
represents a rectangle
in the Layout Engine.
They're very easy to use.
All you need to do is
allocate them and then add them
to an owning view, and then
you can constrain them just
like you can a view.
They expose anchor
objects, so they work
with the new constraint
creation syntax,
but you can also just pass them
to the existing constraint
factory methods.
So they will work with
visual format language
and things like that.
We are converting
existing layout guides
to use these internally, and
here is a good example of that.
UIView, you may notice, doesn't
actually expose layout anchors
for the margin attributes.
Instead, UI View has a
new layout margins guide.
This layout guide just
represents the area
of the view inside the margins.
And so if you need to constrain
something to the margins,
it's easiest to just go
through this layout guide.
So layout guides don't really
enable any fundamentally
new behavior.
You can do all of these
things today using views.
But they let you solve
these kinds of problems
in a much more lightweight
manner and also
without cluttering your
view hierarchy with views
that don't actually
need to draw.
So next I'd like to invite Kasia
back on stage to talk to you
about some debugging
strategies for problems
that come up with Auto Layout.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; KASIA WAWER: Hello.
I saw some of you
this morning, I think.
My name is Kasia.
I am on the iOS Keyboards Team,
and I am here to talk to you
about debugging your
layout, what you should do
when something goes wrong.
Those of you who have used
Auto Layout in the past --
which I hope is most of you --
have probably run into something
like this: You design a
UI, and it's beautiful,
and you're trying to
implement it in your code,
and you put in all your
constraints carefully,
and you adjust things.
And you hit build and
run, and this happens.
Totally the wrong thing,
and in the debugger,
you see something like this.
That's a lot of text; it can
be a little intimidating.
But it's actually a
really useful log.
And this happens when you hit an
unsatisfiable constraint error.
The engine has looked at the set
of constraints you've given it
and decided that it can't
actually solve your layout
because something is
conflicting with something else,
so it needs to break
one of your constraints
in order to solve your view.
And so it throws this error
to tell you what it did,
and you know, then you need
to go and dig in and find
that extra competing constraint.
So let's try reading
this log a little bit.
So here's the view we just
saw and the log we got.
We've moved some
stuff from the top
to make it fit on the screen.
But the first place to start
is by looking at the bottom.
The last thing you
see is the constraint
that was actually broken.
This is not necessarily the
constraint that's causing the
problem but the one the
engine had to break in order
to solve your layout, so it's
a really good place to start.
You start with checking
translatesAutoResizingMask
IntoConstraints [without
space] on that view.
As you saw with Jesse's
example, that will show up also
in the log, but it's
usually a good thing
to make sure you've
done that first.
In this case, we have an
aspect ratio constraint
on Saturn that was broken.
So let's highlight that
higher up in the log.
It will show up in
the log itself.
The next thing to do is to
find the other constraints
that are affecting that view
that show up in the log.
So in this case, we next see a
leading to superview constraint
and a trailing to superview
constraint, and one to the top,
and then one to the
label view underneath it.
And all of these are fine.
None of these are
directly conflicting.
So the next thing to look at
are the views it's tied to,
in this case, the label.
So this label has the same
constraint that ties it
to the bottom of Saturn, and the
next constraint it has is one
that ties it to the
top of a superview.
And this is a problem because
Saturn is supposed to be more
than 100 points tall, and
this constraint is telling it
to be that way.
You'll notice that
the constraint next
to the label there tells you
exactly what the constraint
looks like in something
very similar
to the visual format language
that you may have used
for creating your
constraints in the past.
So we see that it's 100 points
from the top of the superview,
and again, since Saturn
needs to be more than that,
it had to break one
of the constraints
in order to solve your layout.
So it's actually not
that difficult to read.
Now, I have made it
a little bit easier
because you probably are used
to seeing constraints logs
that look more like this,
where there's just a bunch
of memory addresses and class
names and there's nothing really
to tell you what's what unless
you have nav text in your view.
It's much easier if it
looks something like this.
In order to achieve
that, all you need
to do is add identifiers
to your constraints.
And there's a couple
easy ways to do that.
If you are using
explicit constraints,
it's just a property.
I suggest naming the
identifier the same thing
as you are naming your
constraint just so it's easy
to find later if you need
to dig it out of your code.
But you can name it anything
you want, so go forth and do so.
If you are using Visual Format
Language, you get an array back,
you don't get a constraint
back, so you have to loop
through that array and set the
identifier on every constraint.
You can set the same
identifier on every constraint
in the array, and that's
generally a good idea.
If you try to pick out the
individual constraints there
and set identifiers on them
and you change something
in that array later, the
ordering is going to change
and you are going
to have to go back
and change your identifier
order as well.
Plus once you see that phrase
in your log, you know exactly
where you are going to
look for the problem,
so you don't really need to have
each specific constraint laid
out there.
Finally, Interface Builder
in the constraint inspector just
has an identifier property right
there, so that's super easy.
Let's see.
So let's talk about, you
know, understanding this log,
and making it even easier
to know what's going on.
First, if you set accessibility
identifiers on your views,
those identifiers will
show up in the log paired
with those views, so you
can find the view you are
looking for.
That's how I got Saturn from
the constraints we saw earlier.
It has an accessibility
identifier called Saturn.
You can also set identifiers
on our new layout guides,
and that's just a flat-out
identifier property,
nothing special about it, which
makes it super easy, again,
to debug layouts that
are using layout guides,
and since they're awesome I'm
pretty sure all of you are going
to be using them at some point.
Add them as you go.
If you try and take a very
complex layout now and throw all
of your identifiers
in, you can do it.
It will take time.
It's worth it because you will
be able to read this log later.
But if you are doing it as
you go, that's a lot less work
down the road because
you can't really predict
when you are going to run into
this problem, necessarily,
and you want to have it
there when you need it.
Finally, if you have an
unsatisfiable constraints log
that just has too
much information,
you have a very complex
layout, there are hundreds
of lines there, you
can take that view
at the bottom especially and
other views that you are looking
at and actually view the
constraints affecting them one
at a time in the debugger.
On iOS,
it's constraintsAffectingLayout
ForAxis [without space],
and on OS X,
it's constraintsAffectingLayout
ForOrientation [without space].
And that will tell you just the
constraints that are affecting
that view in one
axis or another.
So let's look at how
that works for here.
So I've got that view
that we just looked at.
We see the same log down here.
But let's wipe that out for the
moment because I really want
to show you how else
to look at this.
I have set a two-finger
double-tap just to break here
so I don't have to
use memory addresses.
I can use the names I've set up.
So we are going to break into
the debugger here and ask it
to print out Saturn's
constraintsAffectingLayout
ForAxis [without space]
and its vertical axis.
Vertical is 1, horizontal is 0.
If you use the wrong one, you
only have one other option,
so it's pretty easy
to get back to it.
So here we see the
view has a layout guide
at the top, and that's fine.
That's the view's constraints.
One of the other benefits
to naming your constraints
in your views is that
you know pretty quickly
which ones were set up
outside of your constraints
and which ones were
set up by you.
So our vertical layout for
Saturn tells us that it's tied
to the top layout guide.
That's great.
It also tells us that Saturn is
tied to the label underneath it.
And then in another
constraint that affects Saturn
but isn't directly
related to Saturn,
we see that constraint
that's tying the label
to the top of the view.
Since it doesn't
mention Saturn anywhere,
that's a pretty good clue
that it's the wrong one --
also that whole Saturn
is supposed to be more
than a hundred points thing,
which I happen to know
since I wrote this code.
Now that I've got this
nice handy label here,
I can simply search for
it, find the constraint
that I made, and there we go.
I have tied it to the top
anchor by a hundred points.
And find out where
it's activated.
And get rid of it.
Build again.
That's much better.
That's exactly what
I was looking for.
And so it's really
easy to kind of drill
down into those problems,
even when you have a
very complex layout,
if you are using
identifiers properly.
So where are we with this log?
Start from the bottom.
Finding the constraint that
was broken gives you a lot
of information about
why it was broken.
Check translatesAutoResizingMask
IntoConstraints [without
space] first.
It is the culprit
in many situations.
Set identifiers on both your
constraints and your views,
and finally, if the log
is just too complex,
go
for constraintsAffectingLayout
ForAxis [without space]
to narrow it down.
Okay. So that's what
happens when the engine looks
at your constraints and knows
that it can't get a solution.
There is no solution that
fits all of your constraints.
But what happens if it has
more than one solution?
That's when we hit ambiguity.
This is our final
mystery, so congratulations
for making it this far.
We don't have that
much farther to go.
Let's see.
So, ambiguous layouts.
A couple of possible causes
of ambiguous layouts are
simply too few constraints.
If you are doing a planets'
layout like this and you know
that you want Saturn
in the middle
but your horizontal constraints
aren't set up properly,
the view may have to
guess where to put it.
Again, reminder, it
should be in the middle.
The engine put it
off to the side.
The other solution it has for
it is off to the other side,
and it never actually
lands in the middle.
And that can be a problem
because if it doesn't know
where to put it, it's just
going to put it somewhere.
That's not what you want.
You need to go back and add
constraints on that view.
Another cause of
ambiguous layouts is
conflicting priorities.
We talked about this a
little bit in Part 1.
At the bottom of this view that
we just fixed here, you will see
that it can actually end up in
a situation where the text field
and button are kind of
the wrong proportions.
I want it to look
more like this,
where the text field is
taking up most of the view.
And the reason that it ended up
that way is that the engine had
to make a choice between
those two layouts for me.
And it did that because the
content hugging priorities
on these two views are the same.
They are both 250, and I
don't have any other way --
I am not telling the
engine any other way
to size those views
horizontally.
So it had to kind of take
a guess, and it guessed
that maybe I wanted the text
view to hug its content closely
and go ahead and let
the label spread out,
but I really wanted
it to do this
and hug the button
content closely.
So as I -- this is going to
be repeat for a couple of you,
but if the content
hugging priority
on the button is set lower
than that on the text field,
the edges of the view are able
to stretch away from its content
because it's less important
that it hug its content closely.
Or you are telling the
engine it's less important
that that view hug
its content closely.
Meanwhile, if you set it above,
the content hugging priority
of the text view, the
button now hugs it closely
and the text field stretches.
This is consistently how the
engine will solve the layout
in this particular circumstance.
So if you set these priorities
properly, you can resolve some
of these ambiguous
layouts that you run into.
We have a couple of tools
for resolving ambiguity.
Interface Builder
is a big help here.
It has these little icons on the
edge, and if you click on those,
it will tell you what's
going on with your layout
that it doesn't understand.
And in many cases,
it will tell you
that you are missing constraints
and what it can't solve for.
I need constraints for
the Y position or height.
When you build and run an
app that has this issue,
you are going to end up
with these views somewhere
in the Y-axis, where the engine
kind of decided it had to go
because it didn't have
any information from you.
That makes it really easy.
When you are not using Interface
Builder or when you get passed
and you are still
running into this,
we have a really cool method
called autolayoutTrace,
and you just use that in
the debugger on a view,
and it will just tell you in
all caps that you have a view
that has an ambiguous
layout, and you can then go
about diagnosing the
problem with that view.
We also have the view
debugger in the debug menu,
which will allow you to view the
frames and the alignment recs
that the layout engine has
calculated for your view.
It will look something
like this.
It will just draw
it right on the view
that it's looking at right now.
Here you can see that
Saturn, who is supposed
to have an alignment rect
that comes very closely
to its content, is
stretched very wide.
And that's problematic because
that's not what I wanted.
But over here, its actual size
is correct; it's just pinned
to the side which is,
again, not what I wanted,
but I know it's not
a size problem,
it's a tied-to-where
sort of problem.
The other solution is to
look in the view debugger;
right next to all of your
breakpoint navigation,
you have this little
button here.
When you press that, it
pulls up your layout in a way
that you can click through and
view things like constraints,
just the wireframes for the
views, you can see stuff in 3D.
It gives you a really nice
view of all your layers,
and that can really help with a
lot of view debugging scenarios.
Finally, we have
another debugger method,
because I really
like using LLDB,
called
exerciseAmbiguityInLayout.
If you have a view that you know
is ambiguous and you run this
on that view in the
debugger and continue,
the Layout Engine will show
you the other solution it had,
which is a great clue when
you are trying to figure
out where the problem
is coming from.
And I will show you
how that looks now.
Okay. So we are back to this
view that we just saw a bit ago,
and when it's in its regular
layout, Saturn is flying off
to the side, so I have,
again, my debug gesture
that I can use just because
I need an easy way to break.
The first thing I can
do is see what's going
on with the whole view by
running auto layout trace on it,
and you see that everything
is okay, except for Saturn,
which has an ambiguous layout.
That's where I am going
to concentrate my efforts.
There's also a Boolean
that will tell you view
by view whether it has
an ambiguous layout.
And that's just
hasAmbiguousLayout --
pretty easy to remember, and
in Saturn's case, it's true.
And if you have that happening,
you can also exercise ambiguity
in layout and continue,
and it will show you the other
solution it had for that issue.
So let's run that again.
And -- oops.
Wrong thing to run again.
And now it's over
to the side again.
So in this case, it looks
like the layout guides I put
on either side of Saturn
aren't working for some reason,
so I am going to go up
and find my constraints
that are tying my planets
to their specific areas,
and they are doing that by
having a ratio of layout guides
on either side in order
to determine where it is.
I've got one for
Saturn right here,
and it should have equal
layout guides on either side,
which should put it pretty
much exactly in the middle.
The problem appears to be that
I did not actually add this
to the constraints array I
am activating for that view.
And so if I add it,
things go much better.
Saturn stays put exactly
where I wanted it to be.
And that's really
all that's involved
in diagnosing ambiguity.
It's pretty easy
once you start kind
of working with it a little bit.
So, debugging your layout.
The most important thing
is to think carefully
about the information
that your engine needs.
This morning we talked a lot
about giving the Layout
Engine all of its information
so that it can calculate
your layout properly
in various adaptive scenarios.
If you can kind of pull that all
together, you are going to run
into a lot fewer problems
as opposed to just trying
to make a couple
of constraints here
and there and throwing it in.
But if you do run into
problems, use the logs
if constraints are
unsatisfiable.
It gives you a lot of
really good information.
In order to make good use of
those logs, add identifiers
for all those constraints
and views.
You also want to regularly
check for ambiguity.
You won't necessarily
see it on the first run.
This is a good thing to put
in something like a unit test
and just run it on all your
views regularly, so if you run
into ambiguous layout, you can
diagnose it before you see it.
And then we have several tools
to help you resolve
these issues.
Interface builder is helpful,
as always, the view debugger,
and our various methods in lldb.
All right.
So we have come a
very long way today.
If you were with us this
morning, you saw us talking
about maintainable
layouts with stack views
and changing constraints
properly,
working with view sizing and
making self-sizing views,
and then using priorities
and alignment to make sure
that your layout stays
exactly the way you want it
to in various adaptive
environments.
And then just now, we talked
about the layout cycle in depth,
interacting with legacy
layout, creating constraints
with layout anchors rather
than the old methods,
and constraining negative
space with layout guides.
And we just now talked about
unsatisfiable constraints
and resolving ambiguity,
which are two problems
that people tend to
run into regularly
when they are using Auto Layout.
So those are all
of our mysteries.
I hope we laid them all out
for you pretty well here.
If you haven't seen Part
1, I recommend going back
and viewing it because there
was a lot of information there
that can be very useful to
you, and the video should be
up at some point
in the near future,
or you can travel
back in time to 11:00.
Either way.
So to get more information on
all of this, we, of course,
have documentation up on
the website, and we do have
that planets code, which is
more for the first session
but we also used here.
The planets code that you
see here is not broken.
It actually works properly.
You will have to break it if you
want to play around with some
of the debugging
methods you saw here.
We have some related sessions.
So again, Part 1 was earlier
today, and we have a couple
of sessions tomorrow that
you might be interested in.
We are also going to head
down to the lab after this,
and we will be there to
answer questions that you have
about Auto Layout and
Interface Builder.
And that's what we've
got for you today.
Have a good one.
[Applause]