>> ANDERS BERTELRUD:
Good morning.
My name is Anders.
I would like to welcome
you to session 404,
App Thinning in Xcode.
Now, app thinning
has been mentioned
on this stage several
times this week,
but judging from your questions
and the number of questions
in the lab yesterday, a lot
of you are interested
and have questions.
So we are going to go into a
lot more detail in this session.
In particular we
are going to talk
about how app thinning
affects today's app
distribution pipeline.
We'll look at how it works today
and how it is being improved.
We are going to talk about
what you can do in order
to make app thinning as
efficient as possible.
And to make your apps
as small as possible.
Then we are going to talk
about what this means
for your work flow
as you develop
and test your applications and
submit them to the App Store.
So very quickly let's
take a look
at how app distribution
works today.
You use Xcode and
build and iOS app.
You test it and submit
it to the App Store.
When you submit it,
the app is signed
with the developer certificate
so we know it came from you.
After it has been approved,
the App Store re-signs it
with the store certificate and
hosts it for apps to download.
So along comes a device
and downloads your app.
What it gets is exactly the
same thing as what you uploaded.
Let's take a look
at what's in that.
First of all, there's your
executable code, of course.
And there's resources, broadly
everything can be categorized
into that.
Some of your apps are code
heavy, have a lot of code
and not so many resources
and others are the other way
around where they are media
rich and have some code
but it's mostly assets.
We are going to take a look
at one of those as an example.
Now, with your code you
most likely have 64-bit
and 32-bit versions.
In fact, you may have RMV7.
RMV7 has NRV 64 slices in order
to run as well as possible
on all the hardware
that Apple shares.
Of course, your assets, if
you have images, you will want
to use 1X, 2X, and 3X, Retina,
art work to look as great
as possible on every
type of device.
You may further differentiate
the art work
so that you have some
for the iPhone idiom
and others for the iPad idiom.
If you have a game or other 3D
graphics oriented app, maybe 1X,
2X doesn't mean as much to
you as text compression does
and number of polygons.
In fact, if you want to
take advantage of OpenGL AS
and metal, you may
have different assets,
different textures for that, and
you may further differentiate
between low quality and high
quality so you run as well
as possible and look
as great as possible
on whatever device you have
depending on the memory
and graphics capability.
You probably have audio as
well and you may differentiate
that too in terms of bit rates.
Of course, there's other data
such as the levels of your game.
Or if you have a
documented application,
you might have templates
and other information
that doesn't make sense to
differentiate by device.
It is the same for all devices.
And many real world
apps actually have a bit
of everything.
So you may have spent a lot of
good effort categorizing things
into asset catalogs,
annotating your assets
so the right ones get
loaded on the right device.
That's great.
That's actually what app
slicing takes advantage of.
If you have an ipad Mini,
at runtime it will load the RMV7
slice, for the iPad, et cetera.
What we are doing with app
slicing is making the runtime
decision of what assets to load,
moving that up into the store.
Right now the content goes onto
the device, always is stored
on the device, even though
it will never be loaded
on an iPad 1, so the RM 64 slice
won't get used on the ipad Mini.
Therefore, why send it at all?
So in the store, it is going
to prebuild a version
tailored for the ipad Mini.
Same thing with an iPhone 6+.
In that case, we have 3X
art work, RM 64, et cetera.
Similar thing.
What is important to note here,
you still will be uploading
one universal app with all
of the different variants of
art work and other resources
as you have today, and
it is in the App Store
that the slicing happens.
And what the App Store
does actually is to look
at all the different device
traits of the different devices
that your app can support.
Then it looks at the
actual content of your app
to see how you annotated
it with 1X, 2X, et cetera,
and it builds premade, separate
IPAs that get downloaded.
Let's take a look at an
example you've seen already,
which is demo box, which was
shown in the state of the union.
In this case, we have an app
that is 74-megabytes
when built universal.
That is for all architectures
and for all types of devices.
And by thinning it
out, we get between 16
and 29-megabytes,
22 on the average.
This is an app that
we run the slicing on.
There is actually 19 different
variants that are produced
for all the various
combinations of traits.
All of that happens invisibly
to you or without your effort.
That happens just by how
you annotated your contents
of the app.
So that's one level of savings.
That's pretty good.
Can we do better?
Of course, the answer is yes.
There are some things
that we want
to have all the time
on the device.
So the code, for one thing.
Then there may be some art work,
like a story board that is shown
when you launch your app or
some art work for a main menu,
let's say, that you'll
always want to have there.
Then there are these
other things that yeah,
this app will need, but it is
not going to need it right now.
A typical example that you've
heard before is level 19
of a game.
The user who is beginning
to just play level 1 is
not going to need that yet.
There are other examples, too.
There could be media
rich templates
if you have a document
rich application.
You may want to ship
a lot of those.
In order to provide a rich
experience, you may have a lot
of templates, but they
might take a lot of space.
You may want to load
those on-demand.
Same with audio for instruments,
those kinds of things.
There is a good example
of tutorial
that the user may watch once,
and you don't want it to take
up space on the device anymore.
If we take a look at one of
the slices that we talked
about before, it already
has been thinned down,
sliced so it has
one architecture
and it has one quality
variant of every type of asset.
The next level of partitioning
we can do is something
that only you know based on the
particular domain of your app,
which is what you are going
to need at any given time,
because that is based on
the logic in your code.
So in this example,
we have images,
Metal shaders, those
kind of things.
We can divide those into
those that are shared
and always needed that we want
to keep in the app itself.
We can have things
that come in on demand.
By splitting this up, then you
can actually shrink the base
footprint of your app and
still have access to content.
In this particular case, the
asset packs that are built
by Xcode based on your
asset tags get moved off.
They are stored separately
from your IPA in the App Store.
You can download them on-demand.
You can designate some
of them as being part
of the initial download so when
the user downloads the appear
app and see the progress
bar go to 100 percent,
by the time they are ready
to startnusing your app,
they already have some
of the initial content.
You can bring in more
content on-demand as needed.
Now, this is not stored in
your app's bundle on the device
and also not on the container
that gets backed up to iCloud.
This is stored in memory
managed by the system
that can cache the
on-demand resources
from the different
applications on the device.
So now in this case if you,
in this scenario we
actually have space
to have more than three levels.
We can have more levels
than would normally fit
if you didn't use
on-demand resources.
When we bring in level 4, the
system can automatically get rid
of the least recentl used asset
pack containing your level
1 resources.
Same thing for level 5.
Of course, if the user hasn't
used your app for awhile
and some other app needs to
download on-demand resources,
it can reclaim the space.
When your app is used again,
it will be downloaded
one more time.
So some things about
on-demand resources.
You build asset packs by
tagging assets in Xcode.
You saw a brief demo
of this in the state
of the union yesterday.
And there will be
a whole session
on on-demand resources
later today.
Asset packs can contain
any nonexecutable assets.
App slicing works on
the asset catalogs
in the assets you've
put in there.
For on-demand resources you
can have any loose files
and tag them, and they will
be part of the asset packs,
downloaded from the App Store.
They're hosted by the App Store.
You submit it all together
to the App Store as part
of one IPA, but the App
Store splits it apart
and hosts it separately.
They are downloaded when
needed based on your code.
They are reclaimed as necessary.
And they are sliced just
like all the other content.
So you can put asset
packs in there.
In fact, if you tag assets
that are in asset packs,
Xcode will automatically build
them for you in asset catalogs.
Let's take a look at
the size savings --
oh, right, there will be
a session this afternoon
which will be in
Pacific Heights at 4:30.
Let's take a look at what kind
of slice savings we get then.
After slicing, we had
on average 22 megabytes
for one of the slices.
In this case, we get
down to between 11
and 18-megabytes
depending on the device
for the core application and
the assets themselves are
between 5 and 11.
The point is that
not all of those are
on the device at the same time.
So the sum total is about
eight megabytes in this case.
This is a fairly small
app that you can see
that for a large application
especially one with lots
of media, the savings
really add up.
Some obvious advantages
of making your app smaller
is a better user experience.
There are affordable devices
that have eight gigabytes
of storage, and you really want
to make the most use of that.
You don't want anything
on the device
that isn't actually
going to be needed.
By using app thinning, you can
support more of those devices.
Also this means shorter
download times, less to send
over the wire which is great.
That makes it easier for you
to stay under the 100-megabyte
over the air size limit,
the cellular limit.
What this means really
for you is
that you can support more types
of devices with less compromise.
If you have been thinking about
I really want to use Metal
and run great on high powered
devices but I also want
to be able to use the
less powerful devices,
have customers run well
on those, what do I do?
This frees you from
some of that compromise.
You can now submit, it matters
a lot less how much you submit
to the store as it does what
each user gets from the store.
What this means for you
in the longer term is you
can actually now use some
of that reclaimed space
to add those features
that you couldn't fit
in because of size.
This doesn't mean you
make it huge again,
but it means it is less
compromise for you when you look
at your size versus the things
you want to put into your app.
So after that overview, I
would like to ask Patrick,
my colleague Patrick Heynen
to come in and give you some
of the details on
how to do that.
[Applause]
>> PATRICK HEYNEN:
Thank you, Anders.
Hi. I'm Patrick Heynen.
I would like to talk
a little bit more
in detail about asset slicing.
How does it work?
Well, I'm happy to
say that asset slicing
and app thinning have
been seamlessly integrated
into all the build, publish and
export and workflows of Xcode
that you may already be familiar
with in building
your applications.
All that really happens
to actually make you
realize asset slicing
and app thinning is that
we do a post process
of your build products,
of your asset catalog
and executable files
to tailor the variants
for all the different devices
that you are trying
to build for.
So what do you need to do?
Well, the good news is that you
are probably doing it already,
or doing it already.
If you have been developing
iOS apps for a while,
you have already been
incorporating 1X, 2X,
and 3X art work to capture
the range of displays
on the embedded devices and may
even be using asset catalogs
which have been around
since iOS 7.
That's really all
you need to have.
What are asset catalogs
and what role do they play?
Asset catalogues are a facility
to organize your
resources according
to the relevant device
traits of those resources
that they are important
and pertinent for.
There's an important note here.
In order to take
advantage of app thinning,
your resources must be
contained within asset catalogs.
We do not thin loose resources.
This is not as strong a
constraint as you might imagine.
I'll get to that
in a little moment.
It is an important note.
So I mentioned device traits.
So in the asset catalog
world, devices have a key set
of characteristics for which
assets can be optimized for.
These include things that
you are familiar with,
screen resolutions, 2X and
3X and also device family.
Whether it is an iPad or
an iPhone device idiom.
New to iOS 9 in Xcode 7, we
are also exposing a new set
of device traits that are based
on the hardware characteristics
of our devices.
In particular, graphics
capabilities and memory levels.
This really arises
out of two needs.
One, the range of devices we
support now have a huge range
of performance characteristics,
different between the lowest end
device and highest end device.
It is not the case that a single
resource is appropriate for all
of those classes of devices.
It becomes really hard to make
the right compromise in terms
of what your end user
experience is going to be.
The same goes for memory levels
between the low end
and high end devices.
The new device traits
allow you to tailor assets
to those different capabilities.
What kind of content goes
into an asset catalog?
Well, the most popular
by far is the one
that we debuted asset catalogs
with, and that's named images.
This basically is your art work
resources for your application
in typically bitmap resources
or vectors, in the png,
jpg or pdf format that you
integrate into your project.
These get compiled into an
optimized delivery format using
advanced compression codex
with really good space saving
characteristics and delivered
to your application
through the UI kit APIs.
New to iOS 9 and Xcode
7 is a new data class,
at least one new data class.
That is name data.
What is this for?
Name data allows you to
store arbitrary file content.
Now, this in fact
alleviates some
of the concern you might
have had at my statement
that we only thin asset
catalogue based content.
You ask: What if I'm trying to
thin non-image based resources?
That is what name data is for.
It allows you to put any
arbitrary file content stored
in your asset catalog
and classified according
to those hardware capabilities
I mentioned to you earlier.
And then at runtime you use
the new NS DataAsset class
in the UI kit in OS X, by the
way, to retrieve this content
into your application.
Brief side bar here
for a moment.
The asset catalog features
I'm describing, the name data
and some of the ones coming up,
are available in OS X as well.
We don't thin applications
for OS X,
but since at the catalog store
our source artifact formats are
intended to capture your
sources across all your targets,
including possibly
OS X and Watch.
All these features work there.
The APIs are present
on all the platforms.
Just the thinning is
particular to iOS.
Side bar end.
There's another new exciting
data class that we introduced
in Xcode 7 and iOS 9 and
that's Sprite atlases.
What this represents is
an exciting combination
of asset catalogs and
SpriteKit, allowing you
to organize your image
assets in the normal way
in asset catalogs,
and group them,
name them into a Sprite atlas,
and what this does is
automatically creates texture
atlases at build time
that you can retrieve
through the SK texture atlas
class from those image assets.
The key thing here is,
if you have done all the usual
organization on iPhone, iPad,
it will automatically
create a thinned version
of those compiled texture
atlases and treat those
as thinnable resources that
will be thinned automatically
by the App Store and by the
other workflows I'm going
to talk about in a moment.
So how do we get from asset
catalogs to app thinning?
Well, it is really quite simple
and you may have
guessed it already.
Every asset in the asset catalog
has trademark up information
that describes what
characteristics
that resource is
pertinent and useful for.
At build time when we
do the post processing,
these traits are used
to route those resources
to the relevant thinned
app variants.
It's as simple as that.
I would like to point
out an important note.
Asset catalogs have
been around for awhile.
They have always given
you the ability at runtime
to select the right resource
appropriate at runtime
to the device that's
requesting that resource.
It is this very same algorithm
and the very same selection
criteria used to do the routing
of the rich thinned
app variants.
If your application is behaving
correctly today on a range
of devices, odds are it will
work well with app thinning,
because it is reallythe
same mechanism.
Okay. I mentioned
the word organization
in conjunction a
little while ago.
I would like to emphasize
that for a moment.
Cataloging efficiently in asset
catalogs is absolutely key.
Why is that?
Because a robust mark up
of your resources means
that there is less redundancy
in the slice application
variants that are produced.
You don't have extra
payload being produced
in those app variants that
are never going to be used
at runtime on the target device
that app variant is built for.
For example, even though it
might have worked perfectly
before, it may not make sense
to leave an asset as universal
if they are only used
on one device family.
Consider, for example, some
button art work for a pop
over UI for your iPad
version of your app,
but that never gets presented
on the iPhone versions
of the application.
It would have worked
fine before to have it
as a universal asset
and drop it in there.
However, it may now be a good
idea to revisit and categorize
that appropriately so you
don't have it delivered
to the iPhone versions
of your apps
where it doesn't
make much sense.
Okay. So those are the basics.
Those are the theories
of how this system works.
Let's get practical and talk
about some real world workflows
and how this impacts them.
Let's talk first about creation.
How do you create
asset catalogs?
The predominant way in which you
create asset catalog content is
through the asset
catalog editor in Xcode.
This is easy to use user
interface in the IDE.
You may be familiar with it.
All it takes to create a new
asset is to add a new item,
and there's a range
you can see here.
Here we see the data sets, image
sets, Sprite atlases as well
as the other data types
for other platforms.
When you add this to your
project, you are presented
with an organization array
and spectrum on the left
that shows you the device traits
that you can catalogue under,
and expose how varied
and diverse you want
to provide resources for.
You drop your assets into
the appropriate wells,
and you are off to the
races, and you're done.
So that's great.
That's really easy to use.
What if your team cannot use
Xcode for asset production?
What if you are a game studio
that has a heavy investment
in an existing asset
tool chain or pipeline
where it is not practical
to put Xcode in front
of the content engineers or the
designers that are producing
and are needing to attribute
the art work appropriately?
I'm happy to say that
we consider this,
and we carefully designed
the asset catalog feature
in conjunction with thinning
to accommodate these scenarios.
Specifically, we've
designed it in a way
where it should be very easy to
export image sets and data sets
from existing asset pipelines.
How are we going
to accomplish this?
We are going to do this
through the XC asset source
artifact format.
I'm happy to say that we
are going to be documenting
and publishing to allow
external tool chains
to implement this format easily.
Now, it really is
not much of a format
because it is a simple folder
structure in JSON markup
and really easy to work with.
I want to emphasize, this is
not some kind of import format
that you sort of create and
then you import into Xcode
and then it becomes
a project artifact.
This is literally the
source artifact format
that the Xcode build
system works with natively
at build time to process
and produce your final
runtime artifacts.
Let's take a look at what
this means in detail.
We take the previous example
of the AirPlay icon
art work and look.
This is what it looks
like on disk.
This is in fact the format.
Very simple.
All it consists of is a
folder naming convention,
consisting of the
name of the asset,
this is the name you
retrieve it from in code
with UI image names, and
then the individual art work
resources contained
within that folder.
And I want to point out that
even though this particular
example uses a pretty well-known
semi-canonical file naming
convention for showing scale
factor and device idiom,
there is no requirement
to have any specific file
naming convention.
You can use whatever is
natural to your workflow
or tool chain or
whatever you like.
Why is that?
Because there's this all
important third element
to this design, which is
the contents.JSON file.
The contents.JSON
file is the file
that contains all the
asset markup information
and joins everything together
and tells the system
what traits are relevant
for a particular resource.
So if we were to actually look
at the AirPlay icon
example we showed
in the Xcode editor before,
this is what it looks like.
As you can see, it
is straightforward.
It is just an array of
the individual images.
You can see the individual file
names and then the device idiom
and scale factor
markup information.
These properties, these key
value pairs that you see here,
these are the things
that will be documented
in the SES source
artifact format.
Taking the example one
level further, name data,
what we call data sets,
look unsurprisingly similar.
Again, the file names are
for the individual resources are
there and then the attribution
of universal type
identifier and memory
or graphics future set class.
And you can see it is really
quite easy to work with.
You can see from
the way this works,
how they join the file
names with the properties
that this is why it doesn't
matter what file name you put
into those data sets
and image sets.
What is important is that you
get this contents.JSON correct.
What does this allow you to do?
What is this for?
I would like to work through
a hypothetical example here
of image set creation
with Xcode.
The hypothetical
workflow I'm going
to show here is using the
PhotoShop CC generator
in PhotoShop.
So let's say your designer
created beautiful art work
and they decided iPads
are going to be blue today
and iPhones will be red.
That's just the way we roll.
Designers do that sometimes.
They have the beautiful
master file and they set
out all these variants here.
They actually set
their master file
up with a generator workflow,
turned on image asset
generation,
and have their layer
list constructed
with the appropriate naming
coventions and default layer
to export directly
into an image set,
and they have a special hacked
version of the generator
that they carefully extended,
this is the hypothetical piece
of my example, to
produce the contents.JSON.
Here is what the output would
be from the PhotoShop workflow.
For those who used
generator before,
the photo layout
will be familiar.
There is the assets folder.
Inside is the image
set that was generated,
all of the different art work
entities and the contents.JSON.
All of that is required to make
this work is drag that image set
over and drop it
into the folder,
underneath the XE assets folder
and you're off to the races.
That's it.
A few words about this
kind of dynamic integration
with your Xcode project.
The only requirement is
that your project must
have an XE asset folder.
That's really the
only requirement
from a project file level, from
an Xcode project file level.
Anything contained within that
can have an arbitrary hierarchy,
arbitrary structure.
It has to conform to the image
set and data set, you can nest
that arbitrarily deep and you
can use your own file system
organization underneath that.
At build time, Xcode
will recursively descend
that hierarchy, discover all
the image sets and data sets,
the spread atlases and
automatically build them,
providing that you
authored the image sets
and data sets correctly.
Now we know how to
create asset catalogs.
Let's move to the
next step, building.
So perhaps the most common
and most important
build workflow is just
when you are sitting
there working
on your app you have a tether
device or you are working
in a simulator, working
on a feature.
How does thinning apply
in that situation?
I'm happy to say that the build
and run workflow
automatically thins resources
for the currently active
run destination in Xcode.
So what this means is that
every time you hit build,
it is actually only going
to consider and produce
and automatically create the
proper runtime asset catalog
for the target device
that you are using.
And this is supported
for all simulator
and device run destinations.
So it is a really great way
to immediately take
advantage of thinning.
This functionality is also
triggered by or controlled
by a new build setting
that has been exposed
in the asset catalog
sections of the target editor.
It is called enable building
only active resources.
This is handy.
What if you're trying to figure
out if a problem is being
introduced by thinning
or what the impact of
thinning is overall
on a particular target device.
You can toggle this on
and off for that purpose.
Some other benefits of
this build workflow is
that it dramatically
can speed up iterative
or incremental builds especially
if your application
is very content heavy.
It really only processes
and works with the resources
that are appropriate for that
target device at the time.
It doesn't have to go through
everything like it used
to before when it was
building universal,
a universal version
of your application.
Another key benefit
is this allows you
to easily test the impact
of cataloging changes
on the thinned outputs
for a particular device
or set of devices.
If you are trying to understand
the impact of the sizing
of your overall built
application or other aspects
of your user experience, you can
make those cataloging changes
quickly, build and
run for that device
and then check other
devices by switching
between the other devices and
the run destination in Xcode
and test those changes
fairly quickly and easily.
Now we've covered build.
What's next?
Well, distribution.
This is the essential
step involved
with thinned applications.
Now, there are many
ways that we allow you
to distribute your
iOS applications.
Enable you to distribute
your iOS applications.
The biggest and most
significant one, of course,
is the one that your end
users, the customers are using
through the App Store purchase.
This is the mechanism
Anders alluded
to where you supply
your universal IPA.
The store does the work,
processes all the
thinned variants.
When the user is
purchasing the app,
it's going to automatically
select the right device variant
from the store, and
download and installs it.
You're done, fully automatic.
Nothing to worry about.
Before you release the
application, you may want
to make that same exact
experience available
to your beta C testers.
We will be supporting test
distribution through --
thinned distribution
through TestFlight as well.
Then, of course, there is ad
hoc and enterprise distribution
which is a very common way for
you to distribute applications
in your organization or to
your team for QA testing
or that kind of thing.
That's an incredibly
important way of distribution.
We have built thinning
support into that as well.
Finally, there's the Xcode
service and ECos server.
That has been upgraded
to support distributing
thinned applications as well.
I'll go into some
details in a moment.
All of the methods I
outlined are fairly automatic.
You don't have to
really do much.
Ad hoc enterprise solution
is something I want
to focus on for a moment.
That is the one where you will
be hosting this distribution
flow yourself and you may need
to understand some of the pieces
of how this is put
together and how it works.
Let's talk about that.
How does that work?
Well, one functionality
we've added to Xcode is
that you can now export
for a specific device
from the organizer.
This is great if you are
trying to test a build
or hand off a build to
somebody with a specific device.
You can immediately
create an IPA
for that specific device
directly from the organizer,
correctly provisioned
for that device.
Coming in a future seed we
will be providing you a way
to export all of the
thinned variants for all
of the compatible devices giving
you one complete distribution
unit for all the possible
supportive devices
of your application
for a given release.
This is important.
You may not know or be
able to generate all
of the thinned variants
for all the devices.
You want to get the full set.
What this will do
is actually process
that universal app build
archive that you have,
produce all of the thinned
variants that are appropriate
for all of the different
compatible devices and put them
into one set of products.
But now you've got a big
bushel full of applications.
You may ask yourself how do
I get the right application
to the right device?
That's kind of a
big problem now.
Well, the most common way that
apps are delivered to devices
with enterprise and
ad hoc, of course,
is over the air installation.
I would like to go through
that and how that works
with thinning for a moment.
The first step is to save for ad
hoc or enterprise distribution.
It is important here that
you include the distribution
manifest option, the check
box on the lower left there.
What does this do?
Well, what this does is
when Xcode is generating
that exported set of IPAs,
it is going to generate a
manifest list containing URLs
for each of the app
variants that it produces.
What's more, it is going
to index all of these URLs
by the supported product
type of that app variant.
The impact of this is that when
a device tries to pull that,
tries to install
one of the apps,
using the over the air
manifest PO list, it will walk
through the list, find the
appropriate URL for its device,
product type, and install
it and pull that one down.
That's how it works.
This is a mechanism
conceptually very similar
to what actually
happens with the store
with your thinned application,
but all of these moving
pieces are all hosted by you
on your Web server and
through the mechanisms produced
by Xcode.
What if we take it
one step even further?
That's what the Xcode server
continuous integration
service does.
What Xcode server
does is it turns all
of this mechanism
I just described
into one turnkey solution
for building, hosting
and distributing thinned apps,
including hosting
on-demand asset packs.
It is quite simple.
The Xcode server, you set up
your integration box in Xcode
in conjunction with your
Xcode server deployment.
The bot builds your application
automatically, produces all
of the variants, produces
the manifest P list
and even wraps a nice
Web service around it
where you point the device
at the Xcode server website
and select a particular build,
all you need to do is click
on the install button and all
of the mechanism I previously
described of referencing
through the manifest P list,
pulling the appropriate variant,
it all happens automatically.
It is simple as pointing
your device at the
to the Web server
portal and going.
I encourage you if
you want to get a feel
for how everything moves around,
when it becomes available,
I encourage you to look at this.
This is the same
pattern you might use
to build your own
enterprise distribution
or ad hoc distribution workflow
where you host things yourself.
None of these pieces are things
that you couldn't
build yourself.
The Xcode service, to
wrap that piece up,
is a streamlined
installation method
for thinned app variants using
the over the air manifest.
Nice, simple solution, one stop.
Okay. So now we've talked about
how to create asset catalogs
to enable app slicing.
We talked about how
that integrates
with your build workflows
and we talked
about the different
methods for distribution
and how app thinning
interacts with those.
With that I will hand it back
over to Anders for
the conclusion.
[Applause]
>> ANDERS BERTELRUD:
Thank you, Patrick.
All right.
So in this session we have seen
quickly how the app distribution
workflow works today, how app
thinning is improving on that;
the ways in which you can
help this be more efficient
by tagging your assets
properly and by using some
of the distribution
features we have.
And what this means for your
workflow in terms of testing
and then submitting
to the App Store.
So a bit of a call
to action here.
What you should do,
keep creating tailored
versions of assets.
That's great because you want
your app to look its very best
and run its very best
on every kind of device.
With app thinning we are
freeing you a little bit
from the size restriction
of uploading now.
Every user is going to
get only what they need.
Keep creating tailored
versions of assets.
Use the asset catalogs
to organize your assets.
You can now also put data
and Sprite atlases in there
and have those tailored for the
device as Patrick mentioned.
Also test your thinned
app variants using Xcode.
This will become important now
because we are only
delivering the bits
that every device needs.
You can do this using Xcode's
destination as Patrick mentioned
and using Xcode server to
build the various thin variants
and testing them
on real devices.
And take advantage of on-demand
resources to tag your assets
and to have those
built into asset packs
for later on-demand loading.
I want to call out a
couple of places to go
for more information here.
One is the app thinning guide,
the chapter in the
app distribution guide
that you will find on the
developer website at Apple,
and the other is the asset
catalogue format documentation
that's going to be put up on
the Apple developer website.
We have related sessions.
The first couple of
ones have already been,
but you can catch them on video.
There is another one, What's
New In SpriteKit that is going
to talk about this
some more starting
in 20 minutes in Mission.
It focuses on the
on-demand resources part
in Pacific Heights
at 4:30 today,
so I encourage you
all to check that out.
And DemoBots will be talked
about in greater detail
in Mission tomorrow at 1:30.
We have a couple of labs.
Come down and see us in the
Labs to learn more about this
and have a great
rest of the WWDC.
[Applause]