[Applause]
>> Good morning.
Welcome to Continuous
Integration
and Code Coverage in Xcode.
My name is Matt Moriarity.
I am an engineer
on the Xcode team.
I am really excited to
be here today to talk
about some tools we have in
Xcode to help you get more
out of testing and
hopefully motivate you
to write more tests.
Today we are going
to start by talking
about what Xcode Server is.
Xcode Server is a
continuous integration product
that we bundle with Xcode.
Then we will step into what's
new in Xcode Server and Xcode 7,
with a special focus on the
new code coverage feature
that we introduced this year.
Then we will spend the second
half of the session talking
about some more advanced
features of Xcode Server
that will allow you to
integrate it into some
of your team's unique workflows.
And of course, all throughout,
we will have demos showing
you how all this great stuff
is done.
So let's jump right in.
So Xcode Server is a feature
we introduced in Xcode
with Xcode 5, and it's all
about supporting a process known
as continuous integration.
And continuous integration
is all
about improving collaboration
with your team to allow you
to build better software.
So what does that mean?
It means pulling down all
of your code regularly
and then building and testing
it and surfacing issues
like build errors or test
failures as soon as possible
so you can fix things
right away.
Now, there's a lot of ways you
can do continuous integration
out there, but we think Xcode
Server is especially great
for app developers like
you for two reasons.
First of all, it's
really easy to set up.
Thanks to integration
with OS X Server,
if you've got OS X Server
and Xcode on your Mac,
you are minutes away from having
a continuous integration server
testing your project regularly.
And second, Xcode Server
has deep integration
with Xcode itself.
We know a lot about how
Xcode projects are built,
how we work with devices
and things like that,
so we can ask you as few
questions as possible to get up
and running with your code
checking out regularly.
So before we go any
further, I want to talk
about a few concepts
that we talk
about when we are talking
about Xcode Server.
The first is something you are
probably familiar with even
if you have never used
Xcode Server before,
and that is a scheme.
Every time you run your
project or run tests in Xcode,
you are running a scheme.
A lot of times they are
auto created for you,
but you can create your
own custom schemes,
and they basically form a recipe
for building your project,
so they tell you what targets to
build, what test bundles to run,
arguments to pass to your
executables, things like that.
Schemes are important
for Xcode Server
when it comes time
to set up a bot.
Now, a bot is -- we
like to think about it
as having another
member of your team,
that it's basically taking a
particular scheme and building
and running it on the
schedule you define
and doing exactly the
actions you tell it to
and then reporting those
results back to you.
And each time that schedule goes
off and we run your project,
we call that an integration.
It's like the act of
integrating all the changes
from every member of
your team together
and seeing how everything
comes together.
Now that we are all
on the same page,
let's talk about what's new
in Xcode 7 and Xcode Server.
To start, if you've used Xcode
Server before in Xcode 6,
you know when you go to edit one
of your bots, we would take you
through the entire workflow
for creating a bot again,
just with a lot of the
values already filled in.
Now, that's a little
tedious when you want
to make a simple change
like adding a trigger,
changing your schedule,
something like that.
Now we have this tabbed
interface that allows you
to get right in, make the change
you want to do, and get out.
[Applause]
A lot of fans of tagged
workflows out there.
We've also made improvements
to source control in Xcode 7.
So whereas previously
we would kind of try
to automatically handle
all your source control
and hide the details from you,
we now surface more of that
to you so you can see exactly
which repositories your
bot is going to check out,
and you can select to not
include some of those.
And for the repositories you are
checking out, you can now see
and choose which branch you'll
check out instead of just -
[Applause]
Thank you.
Instead of just hoping that
Xcode figured it out correctly.
We also made improvements to
security in source control,
specifically when it comes
to SSH fingerprinting
and self-signed certificates.
Both of these are not
automatically secure methods
of transportation.
They require you to trust the
server you are connecting to,
so that if the server
changes later, you will know
that they have a new fingerprint
and may be impersonating the
server you thought you were
connecting to.
Previously Xcode would
automatically trust the servers
and not do any verification.
Now we require you to explicitly
trust any of these servers
and then we store the
fingerprint so if it changes
in the future, we won't check
out from the wrong server.
And we've also updated
many of the reports
that you see in your
integrations.
So the test report has been
cleaned up and compacted.
It's now easier to see
any assertion failures
that come up in your tests.
And the logs view
has gotten drastic
performance improvements.
Previously we would try to
show you a stacked view of all
of your logs, but that has
some significant performance
penalties when you try to
expand one of those logs.
We now show you one log at
a time that you can choose
from a pop-up button
in the left corner,
and now viewing large
log files is super fast.
[Applause]
One of the other great things
that makes Xcode Server special
when it comes to continuous
integration is it knows what
kinds of issues Xcode
projects can produce
and knows what a build error
looks like, a test failure.
It's not just showing you
some raw plain text log file
and having you go
through and figure
out what actually happened.
So we do a lot of smart things
when it comes to these issues
in order to surface that
and make that issue useful.
When you run an integration --
this is true in Xcode
6 as well --
we show you this nice report
showing you all the issues
that came up in your build.
And we surface which ones are
new because we can compare them
to the previous integration,
and that allows us
to pinpoint exactly what
integration and thus
which commits introduce
a particular issue,
and that makes it much
easier to find the cause,
track it down, and make a fix.
We have added some new stuff
in Xcode 7 around issues.
Now if you see an
issue that comes up
and you either know it was your
fault and you want to go fix it
or you can see just from
looking at the issue,
like I know what's
wrong there, I can go in
and fix it real quick
and get this cleared up.
Then you can claim issues,
and that puts your name on it
so everyone on your team will
see that when they go look
at the report, and they will
know that they don't have
to worry about it;
you are on the case.
For issues that are
either intermittent
or know have been alre fixed,
you can silence those issues
for a certain period of time,
and they will disappear
from the report.
That allows you to focus
on exactly the things
that actually need your
attention without cluttering it
up with things you know
are already handled.
But one of the best things
about Xcode Server is
how well we interact
with all the other features
that Xcode introduces.
And since there are some
great new features in Xcode 7,
we have taken the special time
to integrate those features
in Xcode Server as well.
I want to look at
a few of those.
So user interface
testing is new in Xcode 7.
And we've taken special
care to make sure
that works perfectly
in Xcode Server.
When you run Mac tests
or iOS simulator tests,
we create a full window session
in the background
on your server.
That's where all
of your tests run.
That means you don't have
to worry about is it going
to be the right environment for
Xcode 2, launch my application,
we'll make sure it works fine.
If you are using
real iOS devices,
then you will see
the UI test stepping
through the application
right on the device.
[Applause]
So user interface
testing is a great way
to test your application
at a high level,
the same way your
users will see it,
and test all the different
layers interacting together.
It's even better when you have
a server running those tests
across multiple devices
at the same time.
And on a schedule.
On-demand resources is a new
feature in iOS 9 that allows you
to make your apps bundle
smaller by not storing
as many resources in the bundle.
Instead the App Store
will host them for you
when your app is on the Store.
Then your application can
download those resources
when they are needed
and they can be removed
from disk when you are done.
Now, that's great for when
your app is in the App Store,
but when you are doing QA
internally before you release
and you need to test out the
builds of your application,
what happens to the
resources then?
The App Store is not going
to be hosting them then.
You are changing too fast for
that to really be practical.
But if you get your QA
builds from Xcode Server,
if you let your integrations
produce IPAS that you install
on your devices, then this is
handled completely automatically
for you.
You don't have to check a box,
you don't have to do anything.
Xcode Server will see you
have on-demand resources
in your application, it will
host them on its own server
and will teach your
application where to find them.
[Applause]
Finally, I want to dig
deeper into another one
of the new features in
Xcode 7 that goes great
with Xcode Server and
continuous integration,
and that's code coverage.
So code coverage is
a tool that's all
about measuring the value
of your tests, specifically,
we want to know what
code is actually running
when we run tests.
Because it's easy to go about
building up a big test suite
for your application and feel
like you are resilient to change
and that regressions
aren't going to come
up that you won't notice.
But how do you really know how
many tests is enough tests?
Say I've got an application
that's got 2,000 unit tests,
but only 20% of my application
is actually getting run
by those tests?
Well, that's still not as
useful as I might think it is.
So code coverage is all about
surfacing this information
to you so you can make
informed decisions.
So it allows you to run your
tests and measure exactly
which code is getting exercised
there and, more importantly,
which code is completely
untested and, thus,
that's code that could
have a regression
as you go adding new
features, and you wouldn't know
about it from your tests.
So we think code coverage is
really important for teams
that are serious about testing,
and that's why we've integrated
code coverage into Xcode.
So like most great
Xcode features,
code coverage is built off of
tight integration with LLVM.
So when you have gathering code
coverage enabled in your scheme,
the compiler will
instrument your code
so we can count how often
each expression is executed,
then we will surface
this information
to you right in the IDE.
Now, there's two ways
we are going to do that.
The first is if you go to the
report navigator for your test,
you could do this in
Xcode 6, but now in 7,
there is a new tab will
labeled "coverage."
If you look at that report, you
can see by target and then file
and then method exactly how
well covered the different parts
of your application are.
This is a great way to look at
your application at a high level
and then drill down and identify
which parts need your attention.
But if I get down to finding a
method that has 75% coverage,
well, that's good to know,
but I don't really know what
I need to know to fix that.
I don't know which branches
of my code are tested
and which ones aren't.
So if I hit the arrow that
shows up when you hover over one
of these methods or
files, it will jump right
to the source code editor
where we show inline annotations
highlighting exactly which parts
of your application
are uncovered.
For the parts that are covered,
we'll tell you how many times
that executed in your test.
[Applause]
So code coverage is really great
on its own in the Xcode IDE,
but I think it gets even better
when you put it on Xcode Server
where you have a bot running
your project over time
across multiple devices.
So that's one of the
things that's special
about integrations and bots is
that you can set them up to run
on a suite of devices
instead of just one
at a time, like you do in Xcode.
So when you do that, we'll show
you the coverage data for all
of your devices together,
and we'll highlight
in orange any methods
or targets or files
that had different coverage
across your devices,
so you can identify where
things are different and decide
if that's a bug or maybe
that's expected behavior.
It could be fairly
common for you
to have code coverage that's
different on different devices,
especially in user
interface code,
where you might be doing
something different on, say,
an iPad versus an iPhone.
One of the things that
Xcode Server provides you
as well is a history
that's stored
and tracked along the
life of your project.
This allows us to, when you are
looking at the code coverage
for an integration, highlight
when changes happen and exactly
which methods and files had
those changes in coverage
so you can pinpoint that down
to a specific set of commits.
This history also allows us
to show trends, so in Xcode 6,
we had build history and test
history charts for your bot.
That shows as you're
adding more tests,
you can see the chart grow,
and you can see how well
your issues have been going
and how stable your
bot has been.
But now we also have a
new code coverage graph
that shows the overall coverage
of your project trending
over time.
Now this is great to know if,
for instance, if it's improving,
then you know as
you add features,
you are either adding
tests for those features
or you're adding
tests for features
that previously had no coverage.
Or maybe it's trending downward
because you are moving
a little too fast
and not testing the
features you are adding now.
This can help you make
informed decisions going forward
about what you want
to do and how you want
to spend your development time.
And of course, if you are using
big screen in your workspace
to show your overall bot status,
right below the number of tests
in your project we'll also
show you your overall coverage
percentage, so you can
keep an eye on that.
All right.
So now I'd like to bring
up my colleague, Eric,
to demonstrate some of
the code coverage features
in Xcode and Xcode Server.
[Applause]
>> ERIC DUDIAK: Thank you, Matt.
I am going to show you an
application that we've built
for internal use that we
use to track coffee owed
from one person to another.
You may have seen this
application last year,
we've made a few
enhancements to it since then.
Basically, the rule is you owe
someone coffee if they fix a bug
for you or otherwise
owe you a favor.
So we have a whole
application to track that.
And like any good application,
we have unit testing
to make sure as we are
adding features to it,
we are not impacting
existing working code.
So having you test those is
really only half the battle.
I don't know how many unit tests
I am comfortable with in terms
of when this application
is actually fully tested,
and I want to look at coverage
and see what we have here.
Because maybe we don't
have that many tests.
So let's take a look at it.
I actually ran the test
earlier before I got up here.
We can just take a
look on the device.
We only have about seven tests.
That's pretty bad.
But it's a small application.
Maybe that's enough
to cover everything.
They are all passing at
least, so that's a good start.
Let's look at coverage.
So if we look at the
coverage report here,
we see the application is
broken down into two targets.
We have a UI-level
application, coffeeboard.app,
which doesn't have
much coverage.
But that's okay.
It's a UI application.
I should write some
UI tests for that.
I am more concerned about this
foundation level framework.
Here we see only
about 50% coverage.
Now, that's pretty sad because
this could be 100% covered
if we tried hard.
And it looks like the class
that's really falling behind is
this transaction class.
And if we look at the
transaction class,
we see we have a bunch
of methods in here
that aren't getting called
at all in our unit tests.
We are creating a few
transactions, and we can see
that in the initializers
being called,
but we are never actually
doing anything with them.
So I should explain a
little bit about our app.
It has a really neat feature,
which is using a proprietary
algorithm that we have.
If I owe Matt two coffees
and he owes me one coffee,
we actually merge that down
to just a single
coffee that I owe Matt.
Really secret algorithm
that I want
to make sure is very well
tested, and also I am not
that good at math, so
I have to make sure.
So let's see and look at the
actual source file for this,
and just like Matt said, I
am going to use the arrow
that shows up on hover and jump
straight into my source editor.
Here we see a whole lot of these
dark, highlighted sections.
Anything that's using
the default background
of my source editor --
white in this case --
is code that's already
covered, and I don't really need
to worry about it too much.
I am really more concerned about
all of this code that's showing
up with a gray background.
I can confirm it's uncovered
because on the right side here,
we see a bunch of
zeros indicating
that this code was never passed
over inside any of
my unit tests.
So that's not good.
Now let's navigate
over to the unit test
and take a look at this.
If I go to the transaction
tests,
I see that I just
don't have any tests.
That's kind of a problem.
So let's fix that right now.
I am going to go ahead and
create a little blank space here
and write in a little
bit of Swift.
And of course, I assume
you all have magic macros
that add all your
unit tests for you.
That's how we all
develop, right?
[Applause]
I am going to go ahead and
run the test on the device.
It's going to take a second.
As Matt said, we are
using LLVM to go ahead
and instrument your code while
it's running so we know exactly
which expressions are being run.
When that runs on my device, I
am going to look at the scheme.
One thing to keep in mind,
since it is a feature of LLVM,
it's optional in Xcode.
The way I turned it on is
went into the scheme editor
and selected the test action.
I then made sure
that check box for
"gather data coverage"
is selected.
That ensures I get
coverage data.
Perfect timing.
All my tests succeeded.
Great, they always do when I
build them with magic macros.
If I look at the
test report now,
I see I have more unit tests.
But that's not really
the whole story.
Let's look at that
coverage report again.
Here we see a much
prettier picture.
If I zoom in on that, we will
see I am now at 76% covered,
not all the way there
but doing a lot better
than we were before.
I'm going to go ahead
and disclose the
transaction class again,
and here we see a lot more
of these methods
are getting covered.
I am testing that merge code
that I was worried about earlier
and was causing me to
lose a lot of sleep.
Now one interesting thing, if
we go back to the source editor,
if we look at the
is equal method,
if you noticed before it
was only partially covered.
We can see here exactly
why that is.
If we look at the is equal,
we don't actually compare our
transaction class to something
that isn't a transaction class,
so this return false
is never getting called
in any of our unit tests.
So being able to see
this coverage as you go
through different branches is
very useful if you have a lot
of branching logic in your code
that you know has edge cases.
This way you can ensure that
every edge case is covered
when you are writing
your unit tests.
We can also see a lot of this
code is getting covered multiple
times, and that's really
important to make sure
if you know there are multiple
cases that hit the same path
in your code but
ultimately are different,
you are getting coverage
on all of them.
Now, everything I just
did was a bit tedious,
and I wish I could just have
someone run these unit tests all
day not have to worry about it,
not to compare them
one to the other.
I was told there wasn't
money in the budget
for an intern to do that.
Let's look at Xcode Server.
I already set up a bot for this
and it's on a different branch
that already has the commit,
so let's look at the bot.
Here just like Matt was
showing in the slides earlier,
we see a high-level overview of
my project as it's been running
for the past 24 hours
and over the past amount
of time I have been
running this bot.
At the top we surface
high-level statistics,
and you can show the statistics
for any period of time, week,
hour, month, year, or since
the beginning of your bot.
Then we see build history.
This is where we
surface errors, warnings,
analysis issues over time.
In this case, I had a
few warnings earlier,
but I've gone ahead
and fixed those,
so we are currently
showing no issues.
The next two graphs are
probably most important
for continuous integrations,
assuming your project
is building cleanly
with no warnings or errors.
And that is your tests.
In this case we see I had
a few test failures earlier
but I've been steadily
adding tests.
That's great, but what we really
want to see is a steady increase
in tests all passing, but
also a steady increase
in code coverage
with those tests.
If you are adding tests
but not adding coverage,
you are not really
adding as much value
as you might think you are.
If I look at the coverage,
the last integration --
this is that commit I
just made you didn't see,
but I promise I made it --
we can actually go straight
into the coverage report.
So this looks a lot like
what we just saw in Xcode
when I ran my tests locally.
Just like in Xcode, we
break it down by target
and across different classes.
And I can expand that
transaction class
and see the exact same
methods getting the same level
of coverage.
But there are two
big differences.
So in this case,
I can see change
over time right in the report.
So instead of having to go
through two different reports
to see whether I actually
increased the coverage,
especially if it's a
less drastic change
than the one I just made, we
can surface that right here.
So my coverage is now 22% better
in CB foundation.framework
than it was before.
And in particular,
that transaction class
increased 48% more covered.
Now we highlight down here in
orange an interesting thing,
which is difference
between devices.
And actually, in Xcode
Server's reports,
I can click this checkbox and
show the device differences
and highlight that immediately.
Now, in this case, it looks
like this detail view
controller isn't showing
up at all on my iPhone.
That's actually to be expected.
In this case, our application
uses the split view,
and that second view
controller doesn't show
up on the iPhone unless
someone actually were to tap it.
And our unit tests don't
exercise that code.
This isn't particularly unusual,
but it's important to make sure
that every time you see
something like this,
that you expect it to happen.
That's why we make it
very easy in Xcode Server
to see differences between
different classes of devices.
It makes it very easy
to determine when code
that should be covered isn't.
That's continuous integration
showing code coverage.
With that, I am going to
let Matt talk about some
of the more advanced
features of Xcode Server.
[Applause]
>> MATT MORIARITY:
Thank you, Eric.
So like Eric said,
I want to talk
about some more advanced
features in Xcode Server.
I know that many of you
developers are very interested
in extending Xcode Server
and integrating it to parts
of your team's workflows.
We know Xcode Server is
not the only tools you use
to get things done, so we want
to provide ways for Xcode Server
to work with everything you use
and be a perfect
fit for your tetam.
So we have two ways I am going
to talk about today in terms
of integrating Xcode into
everything else you are using.
The first one is triggers.
So triggers were introduced
in Xcode 6, and they are all
about providing custom actions
that integrate in the lifecycle
of your bots and
your integrations.
So triggers can either
be email notifications
that provide details and
configurable information
about your integrations
and how they ran,
what issues they produced,
committers, things like that.
Or more interestingly, they can
be arbitrary scripts written
in the programming
language of your choice.
So by default, we will run
these scripts using Bash
so you can type any
old shell command
into your triggers
and that should work.
But if you include a hash
bang at the top of your script
like you would if you were
writing a command line tool,
then we will use that, and
you can use any interpreter
you like.
You can even write your triggers
in Swift if you so choose.
Eric will demonstrate
that later.
A trigger can run either before
or after your integration runs,
and each of those phases
provides a unique opportunity
to do something cool
with your bots.
Triggers that run
before integration run
after your source
code checks out.
That's important because it
means you have full access
to your project and you can make
any automated changes you want
to do before the build
actually happens.
And triggers that run after
integration can be gated
on the result of
that integration,
so they can run perhaps
only on success or only
when test failures happen.
And they also have access
to a lot of information
about what happened
in your integration.
And one of the ways we provide
access to that information is
through environment variables.
This is just a sample of some of
the variables that are defined
when your scripts run.
Any scripting language
worth using is going
to give you an easy way to get
at those environment
variables and use them.
So as an example of what
you can do with these,
last year we demonstrated a
trigger that posted a message
to a jabber chat room every
time an integration completed.
We used the bot name,
integration number,
and result to do that.
It was really easy,
very quick to set up.
There's two things up
here that I think I want
to call your attention to,
because they seem a little
weird and out of place.
So we have a bot ID
and integration ID
for the integration
running and its bot.
That's a little weird if
this is all we give you.
You can't really do
much with just an ID.
It's an arbitrary
string of characters.
What good is that?
No user wants to see that.
So they don't do a lot on their
own but are very interesting
when combined with
the Xcode Server API.
So the Xcode Server API
forms the underpinnings
of how the Xcode ID and
Xcode Server communicate.
You can also harness
this API for your own use
and do some pretty
interesting things with it.
So like most web services
APIs, it's built off of open,
well-established standards.
We use HTTPS to do secure
communication back and forth
between client and server.
And we use basic authentication
over that encrypted
channel for authentication.
Our API follows a REST pattern,
so it's all about interacting
with resources, like
bots and integrations
and using the standard HTTP
verbs like get, post, patch,
and delete, to perform
operations on those resources.
And of course, we communicate
data back and forth using JSON.
It's easy to use,
it's easy to parse,
it's the lingua franca
of Web Services.
Everybody is using it.
This is great news for
you, the aspiring extender
of Xcode Server because it
means no matter your preferred
programming language
or environment,
you surely have a way
to speak HTTPS and JSON,
which means you can make almost
anything talk to Xcode Server.
Let's walk through how
we might use this API.
So what's the simplest question
we could ask our server?
Let's start with what
bots are on my server?
And this is very easy to do.
We make a get request
to the bots resource.
If you look at the URL there,
you will see that we communicate
over port 20,343, and all our
API requests have a /api prefix.
It's not important here,
but I want you to remember
that when you try out the API
yourself on your own server.
When we make that request,
we get a JSON object
that tells us the count
of the results we have
and gives us an array of
the results themselves.
Each of these JSON
objects represents one
of the bots that's set up
and configured on our server.
Like most resources, bots
have an ID, they have a name
like you gave it in Xcode
when you created it,
and they have all the
configuration parameters
that you set up when you
are setting up your bot.
All right.
So what's something
else we can do?
Now that we have a bot,
let's see what integrations
have run for this bot.
So now we access the integration
subresource for that bot.
And we do that, we get
a very similar result
as what we saw before,
except now the results are --
represent integrations,
not bots.
But integrations are resources
as well, they also have IDs.
One interesting thing is that we
also keep a snapshot of the bot
on the integration, and that's
important because as your --
your project changes over time
or maybe you adopt new Xcode
features, things like that,
the bot configuration might
change when you edit it,
so we store a snapshot
on the integration
so that you know exactly
how your bot was configured
when that integration ran.
So we also keep track of the
step in the build process
that your integration is at.
If it's completed, you
will see a result there,
and also a breakdown of all
the different issue types
that your integration can
produce and the changes
from the previous integration.
So these are both get
requests I've shown you so far.
That's great for
collecting information,
but if you are using the
API, you probably want
to do something with it.
So what's something we could do
to actually have an
impact on our server?
Well, we could trigger
an integration manually.
Maybe we have some kind of other
automated process that's not the
built-in scheduler in Xcode
Server, and we want to use
that to trigger integrations
for certain bots.
That's easy to do.
We can use the same URL
and change our HTTP
method to a post.
When we do that, we've
gone from saying I want
to list the integrations
for this bot to I want
to create a new integration
for this bot.
If we make that request,
we get an object
representing an integration,
much like you saw before,
but a lot lighter this time.
There's a lot of
properties that get set
on the integration during
the process of building,
but this integration is
only in a pending state
until the builder picks
it up in the queue
and actually starts
running with it.
Now, most of the post end points
in our API actually require you
to put some JSON
data in the body
that says this is the
properties of this resource,
the attributes I want set
on the thing I am creating.
Integrations are a bit
of a special case here
because bots are
essentially already that.
They are already the template
for each new integration,
and so they know
everything they need to know
to create a new integration.
Or at least they know everything
they need in the general case.
You can have a bit of an
impact on your integrations.
For instance, if you want
to have an integration
that specifically runs cleanly
with no leftover build
artifacts, then you can do
that by passing some
JSON in the body to tell
that this integration
should clean before it runs.
All right.
So that's an example of some
of the things you
can do with our API.
Now I'd like to bring Eric back
up to do a demonstration of some
of these advanced
Xcode features.
[Applause]
>> ERIC DUDIAK: Thank
you again, Matt.
So like Matt said, we
are going to show some
of the advanced features of
Xcode Server with this project.
Now, like many of you,
we developed this
app both internally,
but we also distribute
it, and I want to be able
to easily differentiate
my internal builds
from my external builds.
Now, one common strategy
for that is if we look
at our Asset Catalog, we
see two different images.
In the first case, we see
the standard app icon,
which is this white coffee cup.
In the case of our
internal builds,
we want to always show this
icon as an internal flag
and a black coffee cup.
This way when we are running
internal builds on our device,
we know that they are internal
and not the ones we might have
shipped through the App Store
or somehow distributed
through our normal channels.
It's very useful so we
know when we find a bug,
we are hopefully the
only ones seeing it.
Now, the other way we want
to differentiate
our internal app is
that when we're running
internally,
we normally have
a settings bundle,
and in that settings bundle, we
define, like many applications,
a version, in this
case version 2.0,
since we've made some
recent major changes.
Now, 2.0 is perfectly sufficient
for our external users to see,
we'll bump this version every
time we submit to the App Store.
But for internal use,
we probably want a little bit
more fine-grain information.
More specifically, we want some
unique identifier for the build.
In this case, I think I
want to use Xcode Server
to actually distinguish
which integration the build
came from on my server.
I am going to go ahead
and go to the bot.
And this is the same
bot I was using before.
I am going to go into
the edit workflow.
And just like Matt said, this
is now completely nonlinear,
so since I am most
interested in the triggers,
I can jump straight there.
So let's take our first --
our first step is to
get the icon changed.
I am going to open up a trigger
script I have already written.
In this case, it's a
simple batch script
because all we are going to
do is simple file operations.
We are going to go ahead and
use the XES source directory
environment variable to figure
out the path to that app icon,
and we are going to go
ahead and delete it.
Then we are going to
take our server version
and move it into its place.
So this will be a before
integration trigger
because we want this to run
after our source code is checked
out and ready to build but
before we actually do build.
So I am going to
go ahead and copy
that as a run script trigger.
Now, setting up the
settings bundle is going
to be a little trickier.
I could do that with a batch
script, but that's editing a lot
of batch script code manually,
or letting a lot of plist code
in a batch script
would be painful.
So I am going to go ahead
and pull up a Swift trigger.
In this case, just like the bash
trigger, I go ahead and set it
up using the hash bang
for user bin swift.
I haven't finished writing it,
so bear with me while I do that.
I am going to get
import foundation.
This is where I am going
to get all the extra
power I want from Swift.
With the foundation imported,
I am going to go ahead
and use NSProcess info to get
those environment variables
that I was using in the
other script through bash,
in this case, the
XCS source directory.
After that I am going to find
the settings bundle I had.
This is where things get
more interesting with Swift.
I can load the plist as a
dictionary right in Swift.
I don't have to do
any manual editing
of the plist file myself.
That gets particularly useful
when I want to add something
to it, I simply just create a
new dictionary literal in swift
and go ahead and shove
that into my dictionary.
Here we grab the
environment variable
for the integration number to
set as this build number title.
Finally, I am going to go
ahead and write that out
to disk before the
script finishes so that
when we actually go to
build, that will be picked
up in my settings bundle.
And to do that, I am just going
to add another trigger below.
All right.
So I now have two triggers.
Now, this is where I could
push the integrate now button
and get a new integration,
but I want to use some
of the API Matt was talking
about on the server to do that.
I am going to go ahead and pull
up another application I have.
And if we look here,
we see an application
that actually is connected
to a serial device
plugged into my computer.
And it's using some of
the I/O kit sample code,
and we are just going
to read that buffer,
and whenever we see something
on it, we are going to go ahead
and run through this
block of code.
So I am going to open up an
NSURL session, and I am going
to call the API for
getting all of the bots.
This is just local host.
The port Matt mentioned
earlier, API/bots,
and it's going to
be the get method.
I go ahead and call that,
and using the NS JSON
serialization API, go ahead
and read in each bot and find
the ID for coffee board bot.
That's the bot I
want to integrate.
With that ID, I am going
to build up a new URL
like Matt was showing earlier
with the bots/my
UUID/integrations and switch
that request to be a post
request, so this is going
to create a new integration.
For the purpose of this,
we don't really care what the
integration is going to do.
Now, in order to trigger this,
I managed to sneak past
security a fun little button,
and this button, I am going
to plug it into my Mac.
And I am going to
run this application.
Let's try that one more time.
Make sure it's fully
connected before I run.
Don't want to get
ahead of myself.
All right.
Good. So that application
is now running.
We have the modem picked up.
So I am just going to zoom in
here on my bot and step away
for a second, and
just with the button,
create a new integration.
[Applause]
So that was entirely with
the button in our API.
I am not going to wait for
that integration to finish just
to show you what happened,
here we see the integration,
I can install that on my local
device I was using earlier
to test.
Install. And if I open up
QuickTime to see the --
so you guys can see
what I see -- all right.
There's my device.
You see that we have the
internal icon on the device,
even though I never
switched it locally.
We downloaded it from the
server, and now our app,
we know, is an internal build.
So that's some of the
more advanced features
of Xcode Server, and I am going
to let Matt talk a little bit
more about where you can find us
in the labs and things
like that.
Matt?
[Applause]
>> MATT MORIARITY: All right.
Thank you, Eric.
That was great.
I love pressing big red
buttons to make integrations.
All right.
So here are some more of the
endpoints we have available
in our API, at least to you
guys, developers out there.
There's a few more that are
available, but they're locked
down so that they
are internal use.
We want to be really
secure and make sure
that integrations
don't get messed
with too much while
they are running,
especially with the
client server interaction
where you might have your
server exposed in more places
than just your network.
But I encourage you to
reference this slide later
when we've uploaded the videos
and the slides and try out some
of these endpoints
yourself on your own servers
and see what you
can come up with
and what's interesting
for your team.
All right.
So today we looked at Xcode
Server improvements we've made
in Xcode 7, both around quality
and adopting new testing
features that have been added
in Xcode 7, especially the
new code coverage feature
that makes it really great
for measuring how much
of your applications code
is actually getting used
by your tests.
And we, of course, showed
you two great new ways
to extend Xcode Server
and integrate it better
with your team with triggers
and the Xcode Server API.
So for more information,
we have a --
there's a Continuous Integration
Guide on the developer library,
and of course, you can
come post any questions
to the developer forums.
There's a few related sessions.
Both of them have
already happened,
some more recently than others.
UI Testing in Xcode was
yesterday, but I encourage you
to go look at that video.
We touched on UI
testing but we didn't get
to demonstrate how
it works in Server.
It is pretty automatic, but
the UI testing feature is great
and I encourage you
to try it out.
If you want to know more
about getting started
with Xcode Server, last
year we demonstrated setting
up your server from scratch
and getting your bots set
up initially in the
Continuous Integration
with Xcode 6 session.
Thank you, everyone.
Have a great rest of your WWDC.
[Applause]