[Applause]
>> MIKE SWINGLER: Good morning.
Welcome to Advanced Debugging
and the Address Sanitizer.
I'm Mike and [break in video]
So how are we all doing?
Good? Ready?
Excited? All right.
Let's get going.
[Applause]
So I will start off and
cover some neat new features
that we added to Xcode and
also show you some old tips
and some new tricks that
you might not know about.
We will begin with
the view debugger
and see how you can get
even more insight --
even more insight
into your app's UI
and its user interface elements,
and how they behave at runtime.
We are going to debug an
AutoLayout Constraints problem,
which, at least for me, I
could always use a little help
understanding exactly what
AutoLayout is doing at runtime.
Next, we will dive into
debugging your code
with Advanced Breakpoints.
I will show you how you can set
custom actions and conditions
to quickly diagnose exceptions,
and conditionally print
values all without cluttering
up your code with
NSLogs or prints.
And after that, my colleague
Anna is going to come up
and show us the newest,
most exciting debugging
feature we've added
to Xcodes' debugging toolbox,
the Address Sanitizer.
She will do a deep dive into
how it works, and what kinds
of bugs it captures, and
how you can start using it
to start scrubbing
your code today.
So for these first two topics,
I thought I would just start off
and jump right over to the
demo machine, and show you.
So here we have an
application called Jogr.
It's a fitness application that
allows you to time your runs,
track the routes that you take,
and tag photos along the way.
We have used Jogr as a demo
app for a few years now
and this year we've added
some new features using Swift,
and converted some of the
classes from Objective-C.
It's very much a
hybrid application.
It also now uses size
classes in its storyboard,
and has fully adopted
AutoLayout.
So, since we changed and added
all this new code this year,
it's a pretty good bet that
we've added a few bugs.
So let's find them.
I'm going to start off just
by clicking on the timer here,
and well, the first problem
that's pretty obvious is
that our ring around our
timer is getting clipped.
This was not how it was
in the original artwork
that I had provided.
So this might have
something to do with the fact
that I'm running Jogr on
an iPhone 5 screen size.
As I was developing
this on the iPhone 6,
I probably did not fully test,
to see that the layout
was fully adaptable
down to smaller screen sizes.
To help get a little insight
into what's going on here,
I will click on the Debug
View Hierarchy button
down here in the Debug bar.
Right now, a snapshot is
getting taken of all of my views
and loaded into Xcode along with
a bunch of runtime information
about how those views interact.
As I click and drag
around the canvas,
you can see how I can
twist the scene to show all
of the different views,
and how they are layered
on top of each other.
I can even click on a
specific view to select it,
and we can see all sorts of
details about it over here
in the object inspector.
Now, there's a lot of
stuff going on here,
and with this navigation bar and
the background and all of that,
and I really just want
to focus on the one thing
that you care about,
which is the content
that I put in the center.
So you can do that just by
double-clicking on the view.
Just in case you missed that,
I will show you how to unfocus,
which is just double-clicking
on the canvas
and here we can go again, and
we can just focus on this one.
You will also notice that over
here, in the Debug Navigator,
all of the hierarchy above the
UI stack view has been elided
away, since we are currently
focused on the UI stack view.
If I click on the image that
is getting clipped here,
I can inspect its
balance and constraints
with the size inspector here.
The size inspector doesn't
just show me the x, y,
and Rect coordinates of this,
it also shows me the constraints
that are affecting
this view at runtime.
The constraints that are not
actually in play right now,
that are affecting the size, or
the bounds, or the x and the y,
are shown down here in gray.
So this is actually
a little odd.
I see that the self height
constraint of 249 points,
which is the actual
content size of this image,
is not actually in
play at runtime.
If I look up to the constraint
that says the superview should
be the same size as the image,
we see that it is in play.
It's like something else
is constraining the size
of superview.
So let's walk up the view
hierarchy and see what's going
on with that superview.
So here, we see that
there is a three-fourths
or a .75 relationship
to this other view,
and I know that that
other view is the one
that contains my start
button down below.
We can see all the
same constraints
over in the debug
navigator as well,
and we can open them
up like this.
We see that we have the same
three-fourths constraint
on the view that
contains the button,
and everything here
looks normal.
The top and the bottom
relationships are sensical,
top is higher than
bottom, bottom is connected
to the superviews
bottom, and nothing else.
So why don't we walk up the
view hierarchy one more level.
And we can see here that there
is something a little bit odd.
We have a center
y-constraint that is trying
to keep the entire stack
view centered vertically
in its container, but we also
have this self-top connected
to the superview
top by 50 points.
And that's kind of odd.
So I don't think that 50-point
constraint should actually
be there.
I think it probably was added
when I was initially switching
this view over to size classes,
and I told IB to just add
all the missing constraints,
and then later I set up
the vertical centering,
and I probably forgot
to remove it.
Let's change this over
here on our storyboard
and see if that's the issue.
So I can select the stack
view and there it is.
That's our 50-point constraint.
I will just delete that.
And rerun.
And great!
Now our circle goes
all the way around.
Nothing is clipped, and this
view is fully adaptable.
So let's try running the timer.
Okay. Looks like I got a crash.
I'm going to switch the
Debug Navigator here
to view the crashing thread,
and that's not really
all that helpful.
It has crashed in main.
If I pull up here on the
console, I can see that, well,
this was some sort of exception
that was thrown, but this is not
as helpful to me right
now, because I want
to actually stop the program
and be able to debug it
at the moment that the
exception is thrown.
In order to do that, I can go
to the Breakpoint Navigator
and click down here on the plus
to add an exception breakpoint,
and I'm going to configure
this breakpoint to stop
on just Objective-C exceptions.
Like that.
And we can just re-run
the application.
And hopefully we'll just
catch the problem right
at the moment that it occurred.
So this is great, but if I look
at my console now, I
don't see anything.
There's no message to describe
exactly what the exception is.
So I'm going to use a trick
that I learned from my friends
on the LLVM team,
I'm going to navigate
to the Ob-C Exception
Throw function,
inside the Ob-C runtime.
I will print the first
argument of that function,
which is actually the
exception object itself.
I do that by saying
print object, arg1,
and this is the actual
exception message itself.
So this is so helpful
that I'm going
to actually modify our
exception breakpoint
to just do this all the time,
for any exception that we hit.
I can add an action
here and I'm going
to just type the
exact same thing
that I typed into the console.
Print object arg1.
Now if I rerun the
application, run the timer,
now I'm still stopped
at the exact moment
that the exception was thrown.
I actually have the exception
message itself in the console,
and so here now when
I look at the line
that this exception
is being thrown from,
I can see that I'm constructing
a range, and the range is
out of bounds, and I bet it's
probably because we are starting
at index one instead
of index zero,
and going for the full
length of the string
when we are setting
the font attribute.
So let's rerun this
again and see, alright,
so it looks like our timer
works correctly here.
So, now we've successfully
found two bugs.
Let's go for a third.
So I'm now going to try
taking a look at a route
that I ran this morning,
before I came here.
And, that looks about right,
but if we go back again, well,
that really doesn't look right
at all, I didn't start off
at Mosconi, and run
down the Embarcadero,
and jump in the water,
that's kind of silly.
Let's try that again, And,
alright, now I just hit a crash,
so, I don't know, this seems
like a, definitely a problem
with our data model here.
So I want to figure
out what we are doing
when we are making
the overlay of points
that we put on to the map.
So here, I'm going
to go to the class
that we know makes the
route path overlay.
And this is where we actually
take a bunch of data points,
and pull them out of a
dictionary, and create
and construct a poly line that
represents the route that I ran.
So here I'm going to set a
breakpoint and see what sort
of data values we get.
I'm going to open up the
Debug Console and look
at the variables view, and
down here, we can see the point
that I'm interested in.
It has these values.
I will just kind of
step forward and, well,
this is interesting,
but kind of tedious.
All the values kind
of look similar.
What I will do here
to make this faster,
and just to see all
the values together,
is I will edit this breakpoint.
I will print the point Struct
that I'm actually inspecting
here in the variables view.
And then I will say,
automatically continue
after evaluating action.
Actually, this is
not a condition.
This is an action.
There we go.
And let's just continue
running this.
And we can see that all of our
points look relatively the same,
but there's still that
one that's teleporting off
into the middle of nowhere.
But all the values still
look, you know, reasonable.
I'm not exactly sure
what the problem is here.
We might have to get some
more help from someone else.
So, let's switch
back to the sides.
So just to recap what we saw,
first we started off by digging
into a constraint problem
on the timer view of Jogr.
I showed you how you can now
double-click on a view to focus
on a specific component.
We inspected some of the
constraints and found
that just one of them needed
to be removed when we ran
into another screen size.
Next, we hit an exception
running the timer,
and used the exception
breakpoint to stop
at the exact moment
of the crash,
and also print the
exception message.
And finally, we were able to add
a print and continue breakpoint
that added logging, all
without cluttering up our code
with NSLogs or print statements.
Now to help solve the next
mystery of why we are getting
such odd results from the
run that I did this morning,
I would like to introduce Anna.
[Applause]
>> ANNA ZAKS: Thank you, Mike.
Hello. Let's go back
to that route
that Mike showed
last in his demo.
As we were testing this demo
app, you saw all of these routes
and more, including
the correct one.
We were really hoping
Mike would not run
into the correct one again
and again while on stage,
because it would be not so
good for our presentation.
This unpredictable
behavior is often caused
by memory corruptions, for
example, memory allocated
for one object might be
overwritten by another object.
Or maybe you are using memory
that does not belong to you due
to some miscalculation.
I'm sure a lot of you have
seen something similar
to this before, as well.
A random crash happening
somewhere in our code.
Maybe you see this every single
time you test a certain aspect
of your app or maybe you only
see this on Friday evenings
when you are really
ready to go home!
[Laughter]
The worst case scenario is
when your users see these
instabilities or random crashes,
and you can't even
produce them locally.
Memory corruptions are
known to be notoriously hard
to consistently reproduce
and finding the root cause
of the misbehavior is
often a difficult task.
So what can be done?
Best way to minimize your
exposure to memory errors,
is to avoid memory
manipulations altogether.
For example, using language
occurrences such as Swift
and automated reference counting
will take you a long way.
Even though the memory
corruptions are still
technically possible there,
writing code that causes them,
will be much less likely.
On the other hand,
if you have code
that manipulates memory
directly, by calling malloc,
or by doing [unintelligible]
arithmetic,
or you simply have code
that interoperates with C
and C++ APIs, you
are in the risk group
that needs the most help.
Address Sanitizer is an LLVM
tool for C-based languages,
that serves the same
purpose as Guard Malloc,
as it finds memory errors at
runtime, however, it has a lot
of benefits over
the other tools.
It has much less
runtime overhead
and it also produces
comprehensive,
detailed diagnostics that
are integrated directly
into the Xcode UI.
What's also very important is
that it is the only such tool
that works on iOS devices.
Here's a list of common errors
that Address Sanitizer
can catch for you.
For example, it's very good
at catching buffer overflows,
which is a very common error
to make, that is notorious
for its relation to
security exploits.
As you can see it finds some
of the tools that are --
some of the errors that
are found by Valgrind
and Guard Malloc, however
it also finds new categories
of bugs, that the other
tools do not focus on.
Let's go back to the demo
and see how you can turn
this on in your project.
So I will start right at the
place where Mike left off
and let's see if the Address
Sanitizer will help us diagnose
this routes issue.
In order to turn
Address Sanitizer [on],
you go to Edit Scheme.
Go to the Diagnostics tab.
And check Enable
Address Sanitizer.
Unlike the other
memory management tools,
Address Sanitizer
requires re-compilation.
So after this check box is
checked, Xcode will know
to rebuild your application with
Address Sanitizer turned on,
and it will launch
it in a special mode
that will allow Address
Sanitizer to poke
at your process even
more at runtime.
Let's go ahead, rebuild
and re-run this app.
And see what happens when we go
to the route, to see the route.
Now, what you see here is
Address Sanitizer has spotted an
issue, and its diagnostics
are integrated directly
into the Xcode Debugger UI.
What happens is very similar
to what will occur on a crash,
however, unlike the
case with a Sec fold,
you get much better diagnostics.
Here, it tells us that the
heap buffer overflow has been
detected, and you also
see the stack trace,
at which this memory
fault has occurred.
As you can see, we are calling
it Poly Line With Points
and common method of Map Kit.
We are testing at the buffer,
and the number of points,
which is calculated by taking
the length of the buffer
and dividing it by the
size of each point.
That looks okay.
As your application
is being executed
under Address Sanitizer, it
collects important information
about the heap objects
in your process.
For example, allocation,
heap allocation,
and deallocation events.
And when it finds this memory
fault, it uses heuristics
to relate the faulty address
to a valid object in your heap.
And that information
is presented here
under the memory item.
So here it tells us that the
faulty address is one byte
after 2,240-byte heap
region, and it also tells us
where that heap region
has been allocated.
Even though this is
not a live thread,
but a historical snapshot
of the process execution
when that allocation event
occurred, we can look at streams
as if it was a live thread,
and here it takes us right
to the point where the
memory has been allocated.
Okay. So let's see, the size
of the buffer is calculated
by taking the size of each point
and multiplying it by number
of points and we
use MK Map Point to,
as our points representation.
It's a Struct with two doubles.
So what is the problem here?
Let's go back to the Use site.
Well, the type you pass the
size of here, is different.
We pass MK Map Point star.
But we know that we have just
allocated a buffer of Structs,
not a buffer of pointers.
And since the size of each
pointer is smaller than the size
of our struct, that
contained two doubles,
the count we get here will
be larger than the number
of elements that
our buffer contains.
So that would explain
why we get all
of those extra points
on the map.
To fix this problem, we just
need to remove the star.
And as you see, this is
like a very common mistake
that people could make and it
would be very hard to find this
by just looking at this code.
Now, in this case, this
information alone is sufficient
to diagnose and fix the problem.
However, you can -- if you
feel like you want to poke
at this report even more,
you can go to the Memory View
and see which memory is
considered to be valid,
and which memory is
considered to be invalid,
from Address Sanitizer's
perspective.
To go to the Memory View, you
can click on the address here,
and here you can see all the
greyed-out stuff is invalid
memory, and all the black memory
is considered to be valid.
Now let's go back
and re-run our app,
and see if removing the
asterisk did, fix that problem.
Now, I'm going to go back
to the Routes view, and aha,
here is the path that
Mike ran this morning,
and the morning after
the Bash, too.
I'm impressed.
So let's go back and
switch to the slides.
So as you had seen, turning on
Address Sanitizer is very easy.
You go to Scheme Editor,
open the Diagnostics tab,
and check the Enable
Address Sanitizer checkbox,
then you just build
and run your project.
And also as you have seen in
the demo app, the overhead
of using Address Sanitizer
was not even noticeable.
This low runtime overhead allows
you to use Address Sanitizer,
not only when you are debugging
some memory corruption problem,
but also while performing
UI-driven testing,
where you manually test
different aspects of your app.
Taking it one step
further we recommend
that you use Address Sanitizer
in your continuous integration.
Since it's a runtime bug-finding
tool, it will only catch bugs
in the code that
has been executed.
So you should provide
it as much coverage
as possible for best results.
To enable Address Sanitizer
in your tasks in Xcode
or in Xcode Server go to
Edit Scheme, select Task,
and then again go to
the Diagnostics tab,
and check the Enable
Address Sanitizer checkbox,
build and test your app.
You can also enable
it on command line,
by passing an extra
argument to Xcode Build.
We recommend that you
use Address Sanitizer
in Debug builds, where the
compiler optimizations are
turned off.
However, it is also supported
with the Fast optimization level
that corresponds to
01 compiler flag.
One thing to keep in mind is
that when you are deciding
between those two
optimization levels,
is that your debugging
experience will not be as smooth
in case you have any compiling
optimizations turned on.
So now we will go to the most
exciting part of this talk.
I will tell you the
cool technology
that powers this tool.
So traditionally, Xcode compiles
your source code using the clang
compiler, which produces
an executable binary.
In order to use Address
Sanitizer,
Xcode passes a special
flag to clang.
It produces an instrumented
binary
that contains more
memory checks.
And at runtime, this binary
links with asan runtime dylib,
that contains even more checks,
and that dylib is required
by the instrumentation.
But how does these
memory checks work?
Address Sanitizer checks all
allocations in your process.
If this is your process memory,
Address Sanitizer maintains
so-called shadow memory,
that tracks each byte
in your real memory,
and it has information
of whether
that byte is address-accessible
or not.
Bytes on invalid memory are
called red zones or as we say,
memory there is poisoned.
When you compile your program
with Address Sanitizer,
it instruments every
memory access
and prefixes it with a check.
If the memory is poisoned,
the Address Sanitizer
will track the program
and generate a diagnostics
report.
Otherwise, it will
allow you to continue.
Let's take a closer look.
Assume p is a pointer,
then IsPoisoned function
checks the relevant byte
in the shadow memory.
In this case, the memory is
valid, so the program is allowed
to write to that
memory location.
However, if it does not
point to valid memory,
the condition will be true,
and the program will
trap right there,
where the invalid memory
access was about to happen.
This is how Address
Sanitizer produces reports,
and reports this
problem to the user.
Now, the lookups into the shadow
memory need to be very fast.
To achieve this, we maintain a
lookup table where every 8 bytes
of your memory are tracked
by one byte in the shadow.
This is a very large
lookup table.
So we don't actually allocate
it, instead, we reserve it
when the process launches,
and use it as needed.
With that, we can
look up the address
by simply taking the value
of the original pointer,
dividing it by 8, and
adding a constant offset,
which is the location of
the shadow in the memory.
Even if the byte of the
computed address is nonzero,
we know that the
memory is poisoned.
Now, let's talk a little
bit about the heap.
To catch overflows and
other bugs in heap,
Address Sanitizer provides
its custom allocator
that replaces the default
Malloc implementation.
The default allocator
can organize objects
in various ways.
For example, it can lay out
objects one after the other,
which is great for optimizing
a memory consumption.
However, this is not so
good for catching bugs
because an overflow on
one object will land
on another object,
and therefore,
it will be indistinguishable
from a valid memory access.
So to fix this problem,
ASan's allocator lays
out objects further
apart from each other,
and all the unused memory in
between those objects is marked
as poisoned in the shadow.
When an object is
deallocated, we mark the object
as poisoned in the shadow.
To summarize, the custom Malloc
implementation inserts poisoned
red zones around the
valid allocations,
to catch heap underflows
and overflows.
It delays the user-freed memory
to make Address Sanitizer more
effective at catching user-free
and double-free errors.
And it also collects Sect
traces for allocations
and deallocations, that allow it
to provide those comprehensive,
detailed diagnostics that
we have seen in our demo,
and that could be the difference
between understanding
the problem immediately,
or spending a lot of time
debugging it and, you know,
figuring out what happens.
Now, let's talk about the stack.
So similarly, to heap
memory, red zones are put
in between individual
stack variables.
So, suppose we have an
array, and an integer
as our local variables,
then when compiling
under Address Sanitizer,
additional red zones
are inserted
in between those variables,
so we can detect any
overflows on stack variables.
Stack red zones are poisoned
when you enter the function
at runtime, and they
are unpoisoned
when you are exiting
the function at runtime.
Dealing with global variables
is very similar, again,
during compilation, the global
variables are instrumented,
and additional red zones
are inserted around them.
Now, both stack and global
compiler instrumentation is a
really useful feature
of Address Sanitizer.
This is what allows
it to find those bugs
that other tools cannot catch.
Here is yet another
type of a unique bug
that Address Sanitizer finds,
that is of special interest
to those of you who are
Avid C++ developers.
Here we have a C++
container vector,
and even though all
memory to v.begin,
to v.begin plus capacity
has been allocated,
accessing memory past
v.end is an error.
Leap C++ has been instrumented
to provide more information
to Address Sanitizer so
that it can find errors
such as this one.
As we had seen, all the
checks that we have talked
about required compiler
instrumentation.
However, we know that some
errors could occur even --
could be triggered even in the
code has not been recompiled,
for example when we are
calling memcpy function.
Address Sanitizer uses a
technique called BYOD function
interposition to replace dozens
of standard library functions
with its own versions
at runtime.
Since this is a running
technique,
those checks will
trigger even on code
that has not been recompiled.
Here's an example
of a memcpy wrapper.
As you expect, it first
checks if the source
and the destination buffers
are valid, before forwarding
on towards the original
memcpy implementation.
All of this additional
checks mean
that there will be
a runtime overhead
and you might be
wondering what it is.
The specifics heavily depend
on your individual program.
Address Sanitizer typically
causes CPUs slowdown
of about 2x, however we have
seen it go as high as 5x
in some edge cases, and the
memory overhead is from 2 to 3x.
One thing that I
want to note here is
that this overhead is much
smaller than what you would get
from other tools that
find similar issues.
And compiling the
compiler instrumentation
with the runtime
techniques is the key
that makes Address Sanitizer
so effective and scalable.
For example, we run and test
Safari under Address Sanitizer.
And that's a large app.
And this was Address
Sanitizer, new in Xcode 7.
Thank you.
[Applause]
Let's switch the focus a little
bit, and take a closer look
at other memory management tools
that are also available to you
on our platform, what they do
and when you should use them.
So let's start off with
Guard Malloc which finds some
of the same issues
as Address Sanitizer.
And the main advantage
of using Guard Malloc is
that it doesn't require
recompilation.
On the other hand, it has
other limitations as well.
Guard Malloc does not
work on iOS devices,
and it also doesn't
find all of the issues
that Address Sanitizer finds.
For example, since it uses guard
pages, it will not catch all
of by-one buffer overflows,
which is a common
mistake to make.
These are the tradeoffs
to consider when choosing
which of the two tools to use.
And also at your disposal
is NSZombie, which is good
for catching Objective-C
object over-releases.
It works by replacing
deallocated objects
with zombie objects
that trap when messaged.
The basic functionality
can be enabled
from the same Diagnostics
tab in Xcode.
However, if you want
to gain full power
of this feature do use
Zombies Instrument.
Malloc Scribble will help
in investigating
uninitialized memory issues.
It makes those errors
much more predictable,
by filling the allocated
and deallocated memory
with preset constants.
And finally, the leaks
Instrument will help you find
retained cycles, and
abandoned memory that leads
to higher memory consumption.
So to summarize, we have seen
three different techniques
that will help you get a deeper
understanding of your program.
First, use the View
Debugger to find
and fix constrained
problems in your layout.
Second, set up breakpoint
actions
to automatically evaluate and
print any LLVD expressions,
and use the exception breakpoint
to stop debugging your
program right at the place
where an exception
occurs, and finally, third,
use Address Sanitizer to
scrub your applications clean
of those elusive
memory corruption bugs.
Here are some resources that
you can use to learn more
about what we have talked
about today, and the sessions
from earlier this week covered
LLDB continuous integration
and testing.
You can watch them even
once the conference is over.
Thank you very much, and
enjoy the rest of your day.
[Applause]