>> CAROL TENG: Hello.
And welcome.
Many of you developers out there
pour all of your time, effort,
blood, sweat, and tears
into building some
of the most amazing,
entertaining, and
beautiful apps.
The most successful developers,
however, don't just focus
on building great apps.
They also recognize
the importance
of building a great
business around their apps.
And that's what we are here
to talk to you about today.
My name is Carol Teng.
I will be joined by my
colleague, Shashank Phadke,
and we are from the iAd team.
Today we are here to
introduce you to iAd,
Apple's digital advertising
platform.
Whether you are a
large development house
or a small indie developer, iAd
has a wide range of solutions
to help you grow your business.
And some of the challenges that
all businesses face are how
to generate revenue and how to
attract and retain customers.
iAd has solutions for both.
To help generate
revenue, integrating iAd
into your app is simple.
And you can do this
with minimal code.
We will show you how,
later in the presentation.
Acquiring customers,
on the other hand,
can be especially daunting
for an app developer.
As you heard yesterday,
there are over 1.5 million
apps in the App Store.
And an average of 119
apps on a user's device.
That is a lot of competition
vying for users' attention.
So how do you help
your app get noticed?
For this, iAd has solutions
to help you efficiently promote
your app in the iOS ecosystem
to generate awareness for your
apps and acquire customers.
Promoting your app involves
three main concepts.
First, identifying and
segmenting your users
so you know who the
different audiences are
that you are trying to reach.
Engaging those users with
relevant and targeted messaging
in your app promotion campaigns,
and then measuring
the effectiveness
of those campaigns, so you
can continuously optimize
and improve the outcomes.
We will demonstrate how to
use tools and best practices
that enable you to
do both: monetize
and promote throughout your
app development lifecycle.
Let's get started.
Imagine that I'm
an app developer.
I have a few apps
in the App Store.
And I'm about to launch my
next great app, LiteRight.
LiteRight is a new camera app
with some super special filters
that aren't available
anywhere else.
It is going to be a free
app which gives users access
to a subset of those filters,
and in-app purchases allow users
to gain access to even
more incredible filters.
This is my app development
timeline,
which may look similar
to your own.
Starting with the design phase,
then I'll be developing the app,
launching it in the App Store,
and growing my user base.
I'm currently in the
design phase of LiteRight,
but I'm already thinking
about the business model
and how I'm going
to monetize my app.
Since LiteRight will be
a free app, I've decided
to make it ad-supported so I
can start generating revenue
right away.
And I've selected iAd as my
preferred advertising partner
to monetize my app because iAd
takes care of the whole process
of finding great advertisers,
serving the ads, reporting on
and billing for the
ads that run in my app.
And for that, iAd
shares 70 percent
of the revenue generated
directly with me.
And iAd isn't an
exclusive network.
So I can work with
other ad networks
and mediation partners
if I choose.
But because I'm trying to
maximize my revenue and I care
about premium, high quality ads,
I'm going to make
iAd my first call.
Because I've spent a lot of
time building a beautiful app,
the ads in my app should
be equally beautiful.
To achieve that,
iAd works with some
of the top creative agencies
to deliver rich, immersive,
high production value
ads from some
of the world's most
recognized brands.
In addition, every ad is
reviewed and certified
by the iAd team so I can be
sure that the ads appearing
in my app comply with
Apple's creative guidelines.
And I can block any unwanted ads
using key words and iTunes URLs.
And all of this contributes
to a great user experience.
LiteRight is going to be
a globally available app
which means my users will
be everywhere and so is iAd,
with the ability to reach iOS
users in over 100 countries.
And speaking of my users, iAd's
solution is privacy conscious,
with built-in privacy controls.
That means my users'
data is highly secure
and is never shared
with third-parties,
which my users will appreciate.
It complies with
limit ad tracking,
and is automatically
managed by iAd,
due to a deep integration
with iOS.
And because iAd is built
into the iOS framework,
integrating it into my
app is quick and simple.
There are no additional
SDKs and no static libraries
or third-party headers
to clutter up my project.
I can be up and running
with minimal code.
Documentation and
sample code are available
to help me along the way.
And here are all the ad
formats that iAd offers.
I can integrate one or more
of these ad formats depending
on what best complements my
app content and experience.
A banner, which typically
appears at the bottom
of the app, a medium rectangle
or M-rec which is good in-line
for content-heavy apps.
Pre-roll video that
are best for apps
that primarily deliver video.
And interstitial, for apps that
have good, logical transitions,
such as in games where
users are leveling up.
And coming soon, iAd will
support interstitial video,
another way to help further
increase monetization
for my app.
Now let's look at
how we integrate iAd
into my app, LiteRight.
For LiteRight, I'm going
to include banner ads
on the photo gallery screen,
and an interstitial every third
time a user shares a photo.
For the banner, I need to link
to the iAd framework and import,
include the iAd library
as part of my project.
Then I'll need to configure
the view controller,
such that wherever I
want a banner to appear,
I'll set 'can display
banner ads' to true.
And a good place to do this is
in the 'view did load' callback.
iAd will take care
of managing the view
such that the banner
animates in on screen
and collapses the frame
of my content accordingly.
And when I'm done, here is
what that might look like.
Unlike banners there's a
little more setup required
to prepare my app
for interstitials.
In my app delegate,
in the 'application
did finish launching
with options' callback, I need
to let the iAd server know
that my app is going
to be requesting an interstitial
via the 'prepare interstitial
ads' call.
And in the view controller,
just prior to the interstitial,
I can configure the presentation
so that the interstitial
will appear just before the
next screen.
A good place to do this is in
the 'prepare for segue' method.
iAd makes this simple.
All I need to do is set the
interstitial presentation policy
to automatic.
And this lets iAd manage the
presentation of interstitial ads
in the view controller.
And when I'm done I can see
what that will look like.
I have just shown you
how to integrate a banner
and interstitial,
but integrating the other ad
formats is just as simple,
and iAd has tools to let me test
my integration so I can ensure
that I've implemented everything
correctly before I launch.
For some of you at this stage,
there may still be more
development work left
for your app.
But since I've taken the
time to integrate iAd early
into my development cycle,
I don't have to worry
about coming back
and doing it later.
And I can be generating
revenue as soon as I launch.
So now we've launched LiteRight.
It's live in the App Store.
Users are downloading
and using the app.
And ads are running in it based
on the integrations
I just showed you.
And here are examples of a
banner and an interstitial.
And I can see how much revenue
I'm generating from the ads
in my app by checking
the reporting portals
in iTunes Connect, or using
the new publisher reporting API
that is coming soon.
Because I've made the investment
to integrate iAd early
on in my dev cycle, it
is already paying off.
Now let's look at how to
make other smart investments
that will grow my
app install base.
So I'm earning the
steady stream of revenue
by showing ads in my app.
And some of you may choose
not to monetize your apps
in this way, which is okay.
All of you, however, probably
care about acquiring users
and driving downloads
and usage of your app.
And for that you
will need to invest
in actively promoting your app
which is what I plan
to do with LiteRight.
Part of my growth strategy is
to take some of the revenue
that I've earned from showing
ads in my app and reinvest it
in marketing efforts to
promote LiteRight in order
to expand my user base.
As more people discover,
download, and use my app,
that's more people engaging
with the ads in my app,
which further increases
monetization.
And this creates a
continuous cycle.
So I can monetize
or I can promote,
but experience has shown
that I'm the most
successful when I do both.
We just talked about how
to use iAd to monetize.
Now let's talk about how
to use iAd to promote
and drive growth for my app.
My plan to promote
LiteRight is two pronged.
First, I need to acquire
new users because with more
than 1.5 million apps in the
App Store I need some way
to make my app stand
out and be discovered.
For that I'm going to actively
promote LiteRight and generate
that awareness for my app.
iAd has tools to help
me promote my app
without any additional code.
We'll show you how later
in the presentation.
And what I've learned
from my experience
with the other apps is
that I can't just focus
on acquiring new users.
I also need to engage
existing users
who have already downloaded
because one in four apps
that are downloaded
are never used.
And only 32 percent of users
who download an app continue
to use it after a week.
To effectively reengage
users who have downloaded,
I need to understand what
kind of users they are
so I can tailor my
marketing messaging
and target my ad
spend accordingly.
And for that I'll need
to segment my users based
on their behavior in my app.
iAd lets me create several
hundred audience segments,
but to start I'll group my
users into two custom segments.
Dormant users, people
who have downloaded
but are no longer active.
For them I plan to
promote a special offer.
And a starter pack
purchaser segment.
These are users who have
purchased the filter starter
pack in my app.
For them I plan to promote
our platinum filter package.
To create a custom
audience segment,
let's look at how we integrate
the audience segmentation code
into my app as part of
the next update to my app.
And I'll use the starter pack
purchaser segment as my example.
First, I'll check to see
if users have purchased one
of my starter filters, which
means I want to add a them
to the starter pack
purchasers audience segment.
Then I need to get a
reference to the shared client.
And next I'll need to tell
iAd which segment to add users
to by keeping track of the users
who have purchased my
starter filter pack.
I can do this by calling the
'add client to segments' method,
which takes two arguments.
The first is an array of
segment IDs which I got
from the iAd WorkBench tool.
If I attempt to send
some random segment IDs,
those will be ignored.
So I do have to get
these from iAd WorkBench.
And we'll show you where
later during the demo.
Second I'm going to set
'replace existing' to false.
Since I don't want
these users removed
from any other existing
segments they may already be in.
Now that I've done the
appropriate prep work
to segment my users,
I'm ready to execute
on my promotion plan
for LiteRight.
And for that I'll
use iAd WorkBench,
iAd's self-service
campaign management tool.
It gives me full control
to create, manage,
and optimize my app
promotion campaigns
and gives access
to full reporting.
Here you can see I've already
created a few campaigns
to execute on my promotional
plan to acquire new users
and to re-engage dormant users.
Next we'll use iAd WorkBench
to retarget my starter pack
purchaser audience segment
to promote my platinum
filter package.
For this campaign we are going
to drive users from the tap
of an ad directly into
the page in my app
where they can make
that in-app purchase.
And I'll hand it over to
Shashank for that demo.
[Applause]
Thank you.
>> SHASHANK PHADKE:
Thanks, Carol.
Good morning, everybody.
My name is Shashank Phadke,
and I'm with the iAd team.
Today I'm going to show you two
awesome things in iAd WorkBench.
First I'm going to show
you where you can view
and manage your audience
segments.
And number two, I am going
to show you how easy it is
to create a retargeting
campaign using one
of those audience segments.
So let's get started.
When I log into iAd
WorkBench I see my dashboard.
This is where you see all your
campaigns across all your apps.
To view your audience segments,
you go to the 'my audiences'
page using the dropdown
on the right side of the page.
Here on the 'my audiences' page,
you see all the audience
segments
that you have defined
across your apps.
For every audience
segment you create,
iAd WorkBench assigns
you a unique segment ID.
Like for example,
for my LiteRight
starter pack purchases,
this is the Segment ID
iAd WorkBench gave me.
This is the ID you use in
your code to instrument
and start adding
users to that segment.
Because of that instrumentation
I can see that there are
about 10,000 plus users already
in my starter pack
purchases segment.
Now, of course this number
will keep on updating as more
and more users download
my starter pack.
Now let's see how we
can use this segment
to create a retargeting campaign
for my new platinum filter pack.
To do that, I go back to
the dashboard and click
on the 'create campaign'
button to start the campaign.
I get to choose if I want to
promote an app or a product.
In this case I'm
promoting my app.
So I select "app."
As you can see, all my
apps are already listed.
I choose LiteRight
for this campaign.
Then I get to choose if I want
to promote and run this ad
on the app network
or on iTunes Radio.
I choose app network and I also
see that my ad will be running
in more than 100 countries
where I already support it.
Next I choose my bid type.
CPC, which is cost
per click, or CPM,
which is cost per
thousand impressions.
For this campaign, since I want
to pay only when the user clicks
on my banner, I will choose CPC.
Let's name this campaign.
LiteRight platinum campaign.
Next I see a list of
lines in the campaign.
I don't have any.
So let me show you what
it takes to create a line.
Click on the 'create
line' button.
First I choose which country
I want to run this ad.
I choose U.S. And now for my
platinum filter pack I want
to specifically target the users
who have already
downloaded my starter pack.
In this case I will select my
retargeting option to be 'yes.'
As you can see, all my audience
segments are listed over here.
This was the same view which we
saw in the 'my audiences' page.
For this campaign
I want to reach
out to this 10,000
plus LiteRight starter
pack purchases.
So I will select that.
In addition to the
audience segment,
I can choose other
targeting dimensions.
Like, for example, if
I want my ad to run
on specific devices,
iPhone or iPad.
Or I could choose different
U.S. or user geographies,
or I can have a dimension
of app channels,
which is the iTunes
category of the apps,
I want the ad to run on.
Or I could schedule my ad
to run on a particular time
of the day or days of the week.
After selecting all the
targeting dimensions I can see
that I can reach up to 10,000
plus users which is more
than the minimum 6,000 required
for a retargeting campaign.
So I'm good.
Next I choose my ad type.
It is going to be a banner.
And I'm going to choose
a destination type
of ad deep link.
I'll tell you about this
ad deep link destination
on the next screen.
I choose my flight
dates, let it be running
from tomorrow for a month.
And then for the campaign
I define my budget.
I would like to spend,
say, $3,000.
And then I put in my CPC bid.
Say, 50 cents.
Now, iAd is an auction-based
marketplace.
So I know for sure I
won't be paying any more
than the 50 cents.
In fact, I could be paying less.
Let's name the line.
Once I have defined the line on
the next screen, I see a list
of all the lines I have
defined for this campaign.
You can define more
lines if you want,
but for now let's
leave it at one line.
Click on "next" to
start creating your ad.
Now, to define an ad you are
going to define your pre-tap
and post-tap experience.
For my ad, I want it to be
a banner before tapping;
I want my ad to run on all
devices, iPhones, iPads,
so I will choose universal.
I choose my language.
And for the creative, I can
use a standard set of templates
that iAd WorkBench provides
me with various color schemes.
Or if I want I can upload
images from my desktop.
For now, let's quickly
use a standard template.
I can give it a title, a message
for my new platinum pack,
and a call to action text.
As you can see, I get to see
the preview of how this is going
to look on the devices.
In fact, I can get a preview
of how it is going to look
across all different devices.
Now I want to choose what the
post-tap experience I want
for the user.
I am going to choose
ad deep link.
Because in this case
for my platinum pack,
every time the user clicks
on the banner, I want my app
to open up on the device
and take the user directly
into the page where
they can do the purchase
of my platinum filter
pack, in-app purchase.
In order to configure that, I
need to put in a deep link URL.
I put in my custom scheme
and for filters, where I want
to go directly to the page where
I can do an in-app purchase
of the platinum filter pack.
Now, most of the time
my app will be installed
on the device of the user.
But for some reason if
the app is not installed
and after the user clicks on the
banner, I can take them directly
to the iTunes App Store
page to re-download the app.
Or if I want to take
them to another website
of my choosing, I
could do that, too.
For now I want to take
them to the download page.
I will name the destination.
LiteRight deep link.
I associate the line which
I created to this ad.
And name the ad.
Click "next."
On the next screen, you
get to see all the ads
that you have created
for this campaign.
We just created this ad.
Again, you could create
more ads if you want to.
But for now, let's
keep it at one.
Click "next" to see the
summary of all the campaign set
up you have done so far.
I can see the line I created.
I can see the ads which I
associated with the line.
I can also enter my
payment information.
Since iAd WorkBench, when
I signed up for that,
already has my credit card,
I'm going to use just that.
That's it.
At this point of time, I go
and submit this campaign.
Once you submit the campaign,
all the ads that
you have created go
through a certification process.
And once they are all approved,
and your line start
date is reached,
your campaign will start running
and your ads will start
serving on the devices.
Now, let me show you after
you created a campaign,
how do you monitor the
performance of your campaign?
I recently ran a similar
campaign which just finished.
So let me click on the analytics
section of the campaign card
to go to the analytics, to
the analytics dashboard page.
Here you can see for the
campaign, various metrics.
The total spent, the
total impressions,
the total conversions,
all those things.
I can also slice and dice
this data by filtering
by a particular date range.
Or I can view the data
at the campaign level
or at the line level,
even at the ad level
or the device type level.
In the graph which you see I can
plot a particular metric, like,
for example, the spend per day
across my campaign time period.
Or I can also overlay
with other metrics.
For example, impressions
over time.
Or taps over time.
If I prefer to do all the
slicing and dicing offline,
I can always download this data
using the download icon here.
All this UI functionality
and analytics reporting I can
also use the iAd's advertising
API if I prefer so.
There are so many other things
you can do with iAd WorkBench,
but for now I will
hand it back to Carol.
Carol?
[Applause]
>> CAROL TENG: Thanks, Shashank.
As you can see from that demo
of iAd WorkBench I have
full control to set up
and run campaigns
to promote my app
and in the reporting screens I
can see how well my campaigns
are doing.
Not only can I do this
inside of iAd WorkBench,
but I can also use
iAd's attribution API
to measure the effectiveness
and track app downloads
that originated from
iAd campaigns.
It is a method of the AD
client class called 'look
up ad conversion details,'
which returns two dates.
The first is the app download
date, which is the date
that the user downloaded
the app.
The second is the
last click date,
and this would be the last
date that the user clicked
on the ad prior to the
purchase of the app.
If both of these dates
are there and true,
that means this app download
is directly attributable
to the user interacting
with and clicking on an iAd
that is promoting my app.
So that's it.
Over this imaginary
journey of developing
and launching the LiteRight
app, I hope you've seen how
to apply the best
practices of some
of the most successful
app developers.
Even as early as the design
phase, they are already thinking
about the business model
and how they are going
to monetize their app.
And with just a few lines of
code, you saw how easy it was
to integrate iAd into your app
and start generating revenue
even as early as launch.
Then we talked about the best
practices for growing your app
by investing wisely to
promote to your users,
how to instrument your app to
identify and segment your users
so you can better understand
the various audiences
that you are trying to address.
How to target them
with relevant messaging
and engaging ad experiences,
so your campaigns will be
more effective and efficient
at driving downloads
and in-app purchases.
And how to continuously monitor
and measure campaign
effectiveness using iAd
WorkBench and the
attribution API.
These are all the reasons
that iAd is a great toolset
for every app developer.
It is easy to leverage
iAd wherever you are
in your app development process
to impact the future success
of your app and just
as important,
the future success
of your business.
And one more thing.
For those of you who are
publishers of content
for the new news app that
was announced yesterday,
you will be able to monetize and
promote your content using iAd.
Go to the news publisher page
on the Apple developer
site for more information.
And for more information
about iAd, you can refer
to the iAd Developer Guide
and iAd Developer Forums,
or contact our Technology
Evangelist Team.
There's also a related iTunes
Connect session tomorrow.
Thank you, and enjoy the
rest of the conference.
[Applause]