&gt;&gt; Welcome to session 506.
My name is Tim Monroe,
and I am a member
of the AVFoundation engineering
Team, and I want to talk
to you today about editing
movies in AVFoundation.
The takeaway message
is very simple.
AVFoundation provides
new classes
for editing QuickTime
movie files.
Oh, come on.
You can do better than that.
Let's hear some applause.
[Applause]
Thank you.
Now, I am excited about
this capability because,
as you'll see in a little
bit, this provides the tools
that I need to manage a personal
project that I have been working
on for about the last ten
years, and in some sense,
it brings to a culmination a
project that I have been doing
for about the last 35 years.
So I've got a lot of
skin in this game,
and I hope you'll enjoy
the presentation today.
So what does it mean to say we
can edit QuickTime movie files.
Well, we can open
QuickTime movie files
and perform range-based
editing on movies and tracks.
So you select a section,
a segment of a movie,
and copy it into
some other movie.
We can add and remove tracks.
We can set tracks
associations between tracks --
so say to mark one track at
a chapter track of another.
We can add or modify
track and movie metadata.
And we can create movie
files and what I am going
to call URL sample
reference movie files.
So how are we going
to do this today?
First thing I am going to do
is situate these new classes
in respect to the existing
classes we have in AVFoundation.
Then I am going to do sort of
an API crawl where I go through
and touch on the high points
of the new methods we've
added to these classes.
And finally, I am going
to go back and talk
about this personal
project that I've mentioned
and show you very clearly how
these new capabilities allow me
to do interesting things
with this large amount
of data that I've collected.
So let's talk about the
AVFoundation editing classes.
If you've done any
work with AVFoundation
in the editing space, you
know that we have two classes
that you work with, the
operative abstraction is
that of a composition, and so
you can have AVCompositions
and at the mutable level,
AVMutableCompositions.
Now, compositions are
really cool stuff.
You can make some really
exciting presentations.
There's just one
pesky little drawback
to AVMutableComposition,
which is there's no
standard file format
into which you can
serialize your composition.
So it makes it hard
to interchange your
snazzy composition
with other applications.
Well, when we move to
AVMovie and AVMutableMovie,
that problem goes away
because this is tied
to the QuickTime
movie file format.
We can now open these, edit
them, and write them back.
At the track level, we
have a similar setup.
As you know, a composition is
composed of composition tracks,
and at the mutable level,
we have AVMutableComposition
tracks.
In El Capitan, we are adding two
new classes at the track level,
AVMovieTrack and
AVMutableMovieTrack.
So we have, really, five
new classes that you have
to worry about, movie and
mutable movie, movie track
and mutable movie track,
and then this fifth class
called AVMediaDataStorage.
That's a very simple class,
and its whole job in life is
to indicate where you want new
sample data that you are writing
into a file to end up.
So an AVMovie represents the
data in an audiovisual file
that conforms to the
QuickTime movie file format.
Now, if you are familiar
with QuickTime movies,
you know that there are also a
number of related file formats
that were devised based on the
QuickTime movie file format,
and these are collectively
called ISO base media
file formats.
And AVMovie and mutable movie
can handle these just as well
as they can QuickTime
movie files.
Now, what's the key
feature about these files?
From my point of
view, it's this,
that the file format
enforces a strict separation
between sample data and the data
that organizes that sample data
into tracks and movies.
So here's a basic diagram
of a QuickTime movie file.
It starts with what's
called a file type box,
and this is a very simple little
bit of data that indicates
which of the file formats
in this family this
file conforms to.
There's also a movie box
which, as I just said,
is the organizing information
about all that sample data,
which is found in its own box.
Now, the order of most
of this is arbitrary.
The file type box
has to come first,
but the other boxes can come
in pretty much any order.
So we could have the movie
box at the end of the file,
it could be situated between
a couple of sample data boxes,
there can even be parts of
the file that are unused.
Maybe they used to contain
data, but they don't anymore.
Now, what's in this movie box?
Well, there are three types of
information that we are going
to be concerned with here today.
First is what I like to
call global settings.
This is information that without
which you wouldn't
really have a movie,
things like how many
tracks are in the movie,
what's the duration
of the movie,
when was this file created,
and what's the preferred rate
that you would like
this played back at.
There's also in a movie box
some metadata, which is sort
of optional data that isn't
strictly speaking necessary
for the playback of the
media, but is useful to have.
And this would be stuff
like a copyright statement,
an indication of who the
author, what the title is,
and maybe even some
custom metadata that you
or some other app has
written into this movie box.
The last thing that
you will find
in a movie box are track
boxes, and these are pieces
of information that define
the tracks in the movie.
So they contain the track type,
they point to the sample data
that's needed for the track.
They also contain
track metadata.
And again, you can write
custom track metadata
in there if you'd like.
And there's also information
about track association,
so how this track relates to
other tracks in the movie.
So the key feature here is that
the sample data location --
so the sample data itself is
not contained in the track box.
The track box contains
references
to the sample data,
sort of like this.
Now, it's possible for the
sample data that a track refers
to exist in another
file altogether,
so you can have external
sample references.
It's even possible for the
sample references to refer only
to external sample data.
Now, when we have this
situation, the little movie box
and its file type box is called
a sample reference movie file.
So there's no actual
data in that box;
it just points to
data elsewhere.
Now, it turns out that this
is an incredibly powerful tool
to have available when you
are working with media files.
Why is that?
Because I can edit that small
little bit of information
and never have to touch that
huge amount of media data.
However, as you can imagine,
there's a certain
fragility involved here.
Why? Because I'm referring
to data, and if the data
that I am referring
to happens to move
or gets deleted,
I am out of luck.
I can't play my presentation
anymore.
Now, it's possible to reduce
that fragility in
a couple of ways.
Primarily by using relative URLs
when I make these sample
references, and we'll see how
to do that in a little bit.
But at the end of the
day, you are going to want
to have what's called
a self-contained movie.
If you want to give it to
a friend to view or post it
for delivery on the Web.
And when you need to do that,
you can just run
your mutable movie
through an AVAssetExportSession
to get a nice self-contained
file.
Okay. So let's look at
the movie editing API
that we are introducing.
At the immutable level -- so
AVMovie is an immutable subclass
of AVAsset -- we can actually do
some interesting things already.
We can inspect the movie.
We can get what's
called the movie header.
And we can write this movie
header into a new file.
By movie header, I just
mean the file type box
and the movie box together,
none of the sample data.
So how do we initialize
an AVMovie?
If you have initialized an
AVRL, you know how to do it.
You give us a URL, and we
give you back an AVMovie.
You can also, if you
have a movie header, say,
on the paste board,
you can access that
and create a movie
from a block of data.
We are not actually going
to talk about this anymore
in this talk, but if you look
at our sample code package
called AVMovieEditor,
you will see very nicely
how you can put stuff
and take stuff off
of the paste board.
So here is how easy it is
to create a sample
reference movie file.
We'll open a URL as an AVMovie.
Sorry. Then we call the right --
an indication of the type
of file we want to create,
and then some options.
Now, in this case, the option
that we've specified
is truncate destination
to movie header only.
Essentially, this means if
there's any data already
at that output URL, it's
going to get blown away
and what's going to end up in
that file is simply
the movie header.
Now, it's possible to
pass in a different option
and not blow away any data
that might be in that file,
so that would be the add movie
header to destination option.
So let's move to
the mutable subclass
of AVMovie, AVMutableMovie.
This provides editing
methods that aus
to perform range-based movie
editing, add and remove tracks,
add or modify movie metadata.
So how do we initialize
an AVMutableMovie?
Pretty much the same way
we initialize an AVMovie.
We will pass it a URL,
but in this case we need
to be able toened had ale
any errors that might occur.
It's also possible to create
an AVMutableMovie from scratch.
So this line of code gives us
back an empty AVMutableMovie
that we are going to want to
add tracks to and then some data
to the tracks and so forth.
These are the segment
editing methods available
on AVMutableMovie.
If you have worked with
AVMutable composition,
this is familiar because
they are, in fact,
identical with one exception,
which is the insert time range
method takes an additional
parameter that indicates whether
you want to copy the sample data
into the target or just
copy sample references.
Now, if you copy sample data
into the target mutable movie,
you need to tell it where
to write that sample data.
It does nothing by default.
It's not going to
write it into the file
that the movie box is
located in, for instance.
So you have to explicitly
specify
where you want any new
sample data that's written
into this movie to be put.
And you do that by specifying
the default media data storage
property of the mutable movie.
And this is where this
AVMediaDataStorage class comes
into play.
Again, it just simply
wraps a URL at this point.
There are methods for
creating and removing tracks,
and you see to create a track,
we have to say what
type of track we want.
Do we want a video track,
do we want an audio
track, and so forth.
And if we like, if we have an
existing track that we want
to model this new one on,
we can pass it in as an --
as a parameter and say take
the relevant properties
from that existing
track and use those.
So here's a simple
little case study.
To update an existing movie
file, we could open it
up from a URL, do some edits
using the methods we've just
seen, and then we can use the
right movie header to URL method
to write the movie header
back into that same file.
This is what's known
as in-place editing.
So here we haven't
moved any sample data.
All we've done is
tweak the movie box
and put it back into
the same file.
So let's talk about
the track editing API.
This allows us to
modify tracks that are
in a QuickTime movie file,
and we have range-based
track editing,
just like we saw
at the movie level.
We can also set associations
between tracks, and we can add
or modify track metadata.
So here are the segment
editing methods,
and they should look familiar
because we've just seen them.
At the movie level.
The only difference being that
instead of insert time range
of asset, we have insert
time range of track.
And again, when we do insert
time range, we have to specify,
do you want to copy the sample
data, or do you just want
to put in sample references.
And if you copy the sample
data, the track has to know
where that sample
data is going to go,
and we do that by setting the
media data storage property
of that track using exactly
the same class we used
at the movie level.
So here is another case study.
Suppose there's a
little bit of a clip
that I want to silence out.
Maybe there's some unfortunate
language in that clip.
I could do it it quite simply
by finding the first audio track
in the movie; define a time
range, which is the range I want
to silence; remove
that time range;
and then insert an empty
time range at that same spot.
The net effect of this code
is to have an empty segment
where there used to be some
offensive language, say.
Working with track
associations is very simple.
You can add a track association
or remove a track association.
We will see this in use later.
And I said I would tell you
how to use relative URLs
when you copy sample
data into your track,
and you do it like this.
You open. For each track,
we will set sample
reference base URL property
to some common parent of the
movie that contains the movie --
file that contains the
movie box and the files
that contain all the media data.
All right.
So let's move on to
this personal project
that I talk about, and I
want to call it A Study
in Scarlet (and Gray)
apologies to Conan Doyle.
Let's jump back in time to 1980.
What are we talking?
35 years ago.
At that time, I was a
graduate student across the bay
at Berkeley, and I needed a
way to blow off some energy,
so I went out and bought a pair
of skates, and I discovered
that Berkeley is a great
place to be a skater
because it's got these
really nice hills.
And I really enjoyed that.
So I kept finding higher
and higher hills to climb up
and then go flying down.
So here in 1984, you
can see me at the top
of Claremont avenue in Oakland.
In the distance, you can see
San Francisco, just this side
of the bay, we have Emeryville,
and we have this wonderful,
almost looks like a
ski run in front of me.
I am not quite sure what
the hand up is doing.
Maybe it's the sort
of we who are
about to die salute you
thing, and I didn't die.
It's okay.
[Laughter] Well, what I
did in order to keep track
of where I was, I went out
and I bought a street map,
and I got myself a
yellow highlighter,
and I started marking off on my
map exactly where I had been,
which hills were
particularly good.
Well, if you are like me,
that's a really bad thing
to start doing because
you're going to want to end
up coloring in the entire map.
And so about 2000 -- sorry.
About 1985, I came
up with a project
that I called Tim's Radical
Inline Skate Tour of Oakland,
or TRISTO, and the
goal was really simple,
to skate every street
in Oakland,
the entire length of it.
This continued from
1985 until about 2005,
so ten years ago, and I made it.
Okay?
[Applause]
Thank you.
Oakland has about 800 miles of
roadways that you would have
to skate in order
to accomplish this.
Now, when I was done in
2005, I had no location data.
GPS hadn't been invented
when I started,
and it certainly
wasn't available.
Actually, I did have location
data because if you open
up my map, you will see that
it is right side up all yellow,
not just -- but Alameda,
Piedmont,
Emeryville, the whole
nine yards.
I also had no video.
If you remember back
to that time, I mean,
the camera you would be
carrying in 1985 would be clunky
and fragile, and you just
wouldn't want to have it
with you when you are
out there skating.
So when I finished
this, I really --
this is a wacko project,
I admit that,
and I made absolutely no effort
to tell anybody about this.
Unfortunately, the San Francisco
chronicle learned of this feat,
I guess, and wrote a nice
little newspaper article,
one of these human
interest stories.
The Oakland City
Council learned about it,
they passed a resolution
praising the extraordinary
physical accomplishment --
that's their words, not mine.
A couple of filmmakers
in Oakland heard about it
and spent literally years off
and on making a nice little
documentary about this project,
which came out about a year ago
and has been making the rounds
of independent theaters
in the Bay area.
Just completely wacko.
So about a couple of years
after I finished this project,
I started spending some time on
the east coast, in particular
in the area of Boston,
Massachusetts,
and even more particular,
in Cambridge.
And I thought, all right, let's
take this thing on the road.
I spent a few years skating
Cambridge and Somerville,
and then finally the idea
for TRISTO Boston was born.
Same idea.
Skate every street in
the city of Boston.
So this began about 2011.
I looked at a map, and I
figured it would take me
about five years
to complete this.
Well, we had a couple
mild winters in there.
It's about the same
size as Oakland.
And I was able to complete this
in about two and a half years,
so in May 2013, I
finished TRISTO Boston.
Now, this time I was prepared
because as I was skating,
I had one of those sports
action cameras up on the top
of my helmet, and I had
a GPS app for my iPhone.
And so when I ended up,
I had 490 MPEG-4 files
straight off the camera covering
about 200 different
skates for a total
of about a terabyte
and a half of data.
I also had GPS data in
the form of GPX files --
that's sort of an XML
version of location data --
we will see one later --
for about 150 megabytes
worth of data.
So just to get an idea of
what these movies look like,
let's just look at one.
So these are movies
straight off the camera.
The only thing I have
done is rename them
so that it's got the date
and title making it
easy for me to find.
So we will open these
up in QuickTime Player.
There's the second one, so
that continues at the end
of the first one, so we will
select the first movie here.
We can see it's a
bright, sunny day.
It's late November.
It's a weekday.
And let's just roll this.
We see it's the fall because
there's leaves on the ground.
If we had the audio,
we would hear
that it's actually
quite windy on this day.
And there's something
strange here, though.
There's nobody on the street.
There's no pedestrians.
Let's jump ahead a
little bit again.
No pedestrians.
There's some cars.
Here I am at Longwood
Medical District.
This is a heavily
trafficked area.
Nobody there.
Here's a commercial district.
Nobody. It's like a ghost town.
So what's going on?
Well, we'll solve
that problem later.
So what I've got,
basically, is a hay stack
and a bunch of needles.
I've got 500 hours of video.
Even if 99% of it is junk,
that's still five full hours
of interesting video
that I'd like to find.
Part of the problem, though,
is I don't even know
what the needles look
like because I don't
know what's important
in these 500 hours of video.
Well, I do know some things
that I'd really love to look at,
and here is sort of a
montage of some of these.
Snow, really?
I mean, come on.
Like, I didn't see that pothole?
[Laughter]
Now, that one's my favorite,
because as you can see,
I go down, I kind of roll over,
I get back and keep on skating.
You know, if it wasn't
as -- thank you.
[Applause]
Now, I actually had to
pay somebody to weed --
to look through about
1/50 of all of my video
to get these six clips.
So in theory, there's 300
of these wonderful falls
somewhere in that hay stack.
So at about, you know,
five seconds per fall,
we are talking 25
minutes of this stuff,
which would be really
fun to watch.
[Laughter]
So here's what I want to
do with all this data.
I've got a terabyte and a
half of video data that I want
to somehow do something with.
I want to find those needles.
So the first step is going to
be to combine the various files
that came off the
camera for one skate
into a sample reference movie
file so that I can just open it
and edit it and not have to
worry about the camera files.
The second thing I want to
do is add indexing metadata
as movie metadata.
So I want to go in and
mark in the file, okay,
this is where I start to fall,
and this is the end of the fall.
Or this is where
dogs are chasing me,
and this is where
they finally figured
out they are not
going to get me.
Or this is where I am talking
to a law enforcement officer,
and that just keeps going.
So I'd like to index all
this stuff so that it's easy
to search and find all these
needles, as I call them.
I want to add GPS data.
I have all that location data
I haven't done anything with.
I want to add it to the
file, and I am going to do
that as what's called
a timed metadata track.
And the key is I want to do all
of this without modifying any
of the original camera files,
and by minimizing any data
copying that I need to do.
Okay. How are we
going to do that?
Well, AVMovie and AVMutableMovie
give us the answer.
The solution to the first
issue is very simple.
I am going to take those
camera files, and I am going
to create a sample reference
movie file that points
to the data in those
two original files.
Very straightforward,
standard use
of sample reference movie files.
The solution for the second
step is just to add a little bit
of extra custom metadata
to my movie box.
The third step is to add
some actual media data
into my new sample
reference movie file.
And that media data, even though
it's called timed metadata,
it's stored as media data or
sample data, and it just goes
into a new track in the file.
So that's the way I want
to approach this issue.
So the first step is
actually quite simple.
We'll open the first
movie as a mutable movie,
and we'll open the second
and any subsequent
movies as just URL assets.
We'll define the range in the
asset that we want to insert,
and that's just the
entire asset duration.
We will actually insert it into
the mutable movie at the end
of the mutable movie, and
notice we say don't copy the
sample data.
I just want to end up
with sample references.
Finally, all we have to do
is write a new movie header
out to a new file, and we have
then created a sample reference
movie file that points
to the data
in the two original
camera files.
So let's look at some demos
of how I solve the
second and third one.
Normally this slide would just
read demos, but I am a sucker
for a good palindrome, and
I just couldn't waste it.
Alvin is a sort of acronym
for AVFoundation-based
linear indexer.
Its job is to do the
indexing I talked about,
but also get the location
data into my file.
This is what the UI looks like.
I've got a movie view on the
left, I've got a map view
on the right, and down below you
can see I've got some display
areas where I am going to
be displaying information
that I glean about this skate.
So let's go ahead and
open up a movie file.
And this is the sample reference
movie file that I just created.
That opens up there.
I am going to load a GPX file.
I will go out and select
the appropriate GPS file.
Now, when I open this file,
some of the data's
going to be filled in.
It's going to figure
out how long this was.
Okay? So let's -- I've got it
so I can expand my map view
to make it clear where we are.
So I went out and made a big
circuit around Brookline.
This situates you.
There is Logan Airport.
Here is Boston proper.
There's Cambridge.
Now let's just zoom back in.
Oh, I said I was going
to show you a GPX file.
So this is what a
GPX file looks like.
It's just XML formatted,
longitudes, latitudes,
elevations, time stamps.
That's it, nothing
more in there.
So let's go here and
run a Web service.
I am going to go out and find
out from a government Web
server what the weather was
like on this day, and I
discover it was quite windy,
it was 17 mile an hour average,
or for those who speak metric,
28.4, and it was 39
degrees Fahrenheit or,
interesting factoid,
3.9 centigrade.
Thanksgiving day, that's why
there's nobody on the street.
You see, it figured out
this this was a holiday.
It's also the second
night of Hanukkah.
Okay? So just these Web
Services have allowed me
to deduce why there's
nobody on the street.
Now I am running another
Web Service called reverse
geocoding, where I am sending
each longitude and latitude
out to a server at
Apple, and it's going
to hand me back a
state, city, street,
and sometimes even
a street number.
Basically, it's going
to give me information
about the streets that I was on.
So we will wait here while all
these street pins fall down.
Then we can select one of them
to find out what street that is,
so that's Commonwealth Avenue.
Or here's Washington
Street in Brookline.
Now, I added a search bar
so I could type in, say,
Commonwealth Avenue, and it will
highlight it when it finds it.
So if I put this
data into my file,
now I have complete
searchability on street names.
I can go in and find all
those little clips where I am
on a particular street.
So let's hide those, and
the last thing we need
to do is synchronize our
video with our location data,
and I tried various
automatic ways to do this,
but I discovered the only really
good way to do it was to go
to a frame in the video where
I knew where I was on the map,
and then I am going to come
over onto the map and click it
and say synchronize the video
to this location right here.
Now, when I do this,
if I come back
and start playing the video,
you will see the pin moves
along with the video.
See, these are now synchronized.
And I can even go
the other direction.
I can go to someplace on
the map, and I can click it
and say make the movie
go there, and now I am
on Commonwealth Avenue,
and I know this is a
particularly fun downhill slope,
and we will just let
this ride for a second.
And this is really why we do
this, right, for these kind
of downhill with no cars and
what could possibly go wrong?
[Laughter]
Okay. So that's Alvin.
You can see that Alvin
has solved the second
and third problems for me.
It's added custom metadata to
my sample reference movie file.
And it basically
does it like this.
It gets the existing
metadata by calling the --
looking at the metadata
property.
We'll create a new
metadata item,
we'll fill in its
properties accordingly.
For instance, the average wind
speed value is the value I got
from the government server
telling me what the weather was
on that day.
And I just create some
identifier here that I can look
for later, and once I've
written this into the file
with the right movie header to
URL, my movie is all updated.
Now let's look at step three,
which is to add the location
data as a time metadata track.
You already know how to do this.
If you were here last year
and heard the talk Harnessing
Metadata in Audiovisual Media,
they showed a couple things.
First how to get location
data from a capture session,
and how to right-time
metadata into a movie.
Well, we've got our
location data.
It's in our GPX file.
So we don't need that
capture session stuff.
We can just focus on
taking the source code
in that second sample
code package
and putting it into Alvin.
Now, once we've done
that, what we end up with
on disk is a timed file that has
a single metadata track in it,
and all we have to do is copy
that track into a new track
in our movie, and we will do
it by opening the GPS asset.
We'll then add a new track
to our movie using whatever
media type happens to be
in that track, and we will copy
the settings from that track.
Finally, we insert that range
into this new track, and again,
if we write this header
into our file, we are done.
Now, the last thing we need
to do -- this is optional --
is create a track association
between the timed media track
and whatever track it is
metadata for, and in this case,
we have chosen the video track.
If you leave this step out, the
timed video track is assumed
to apply to the file as
a whole, and we are fine
as far as that's concerned.
If you are working
with AVMutableMovie,
there are a couple of
things to keep in mind.
As you know, an AVMovie or an
AVMutableMovie is an AVAsset
because it's a subclass.
So anything that you can do
with an AVAsset you can
do with a mutable movie.
For instance, you could
play it using AVPlayerItem,
you could grab an image from it
using an AVAssetImageGenerator.
You could export it using
an AVAssetExportSession.
Now, if you do any of these
operations on a mutable movie,
we highly recommend
that you make a copy
of that mutable movie because if
you're changing the movie while
you are exporting it,
bad things will happen.
So just make a copy
of it, do your export,
and everything works fine.
The second best practice is
that if you are opening an asset
that you want to insert
into an AVMutableMovie,
you should set this flag, AV URL
asset prefer precise duration
and timing key, to true.
Now, we haven't done this
in any of the code snippets
that you've seen so far because
when you open a QuickTime movie,
this flag is already
set to true.
But if you were to open
an MP3 file, for instance,
and wanted to insert that
into a mutable movie,
you would want to set this flag.
So let's summarize.
We've added new classes
to support editing
on QuickTime movie files.
This gives us, as
I hope you've seen,
a really nice, simplified
workflow.
We are able to work on
reference movies and not
on the original movies
themselves.
So if you are handling
large amounts
of data, this is for you.
If you want to see how
this works in practice,
download AVMovieEditor
and take a look at that.
For more information, go
to the standard places.
And if you have questions
about this, we'll be in the lab
on Thursday and Friday.
If you want to look at the --
how to work with
compositions, jump back to 2010.
And finally, if you want
to see in great detail how
to do the timed metadata
track generation,
go to last year's session,
Harnessing Metadata
in Audiovisual media.
Thank you very much.
[Applause]