[Applause]
>> MEGAN GARDNER:
Hey, everybody.
Welcome, and thank you
for coming to our session.
My name is Megan Gardner, I'm a
software engineer on the games
and graphics team and later
we will have my colleague,
Edwin Iskandar up.
We're going to be talking
to you about going social
with ReplayKit and Game Center.
So we have a few things
on the agenda today.
First, what's new
in Game Center.
We have two new things
basically guest players as well
as our new unified
server environment.
And then Edwin will get up and
talk to you about ReplayKit
which is a great new way to
add a new social experience
to your games and for
your users to be able
to share those experiences
with others.
So what's new in Game Center?
Well, what is Game Center?
Hopefully you know what it is,
especially if you
are in this session.
It's been around for a while,
but just in case you don't,
Game Center is our API and app
that allows you as developers
to add a social experience
to your games.
This allows our users to be able
to make friends with each other,
for you as developers to be
able to set up leaderboards
for those users to be
able to post scores to,
that they can then compare
against their friends as well
as others, for you to be
able to define achievements
that your users can achieve
and we also support everything
that you would need to be
able to write a realtime
or turn-based multiplayer
game without having
to set up your own servers.
And we also support challenges
which add a multiplayer element
to your single player game.
So, what's new?
First up, we have guest players.
Currently in Game Center
we have two main places
that you'll run into players.
First is your GKLocalPlayer.
You only have one of these
per device and it has
to be an authenticated
Game Center user.
You'll also run into GKPlayer
as friends of that GKLocalPlayer
but more commonly as
participants in any sort
of multiplayer match
whether or not
that is real time or turn-based.
However with these players,
you can only have one
player per device.
Well, not anymore.
Now we have guest players.
So what are guest players?
They actually are
GKPlayer instances.
So you can use them just like
you would any other GKPlayer.
They do not require
authentication,
they will be created by you
vending us an identifier
and then we will give
you back a GKPlayer.
They are first-class
participants
in any multiplayer game so
you can fill up the rest
of the slots in your game
with those guest players.
You do need to have at least
one authenticated GKPlayer
but everything else can
be those guest players.
What can you use
guest players for?
They are great for
pass and play.
Say you want to be able
to have an iPad game
that you have one
player logged into
and everybody else wants
to be able to play.
You can fill up the
rest of those slots
with these guest
players and be able
to have a completely
local game on that iPad
that your users will
be able to play
and you can treat the game logic
in that turn-base game exactly
as you would any other game.
You can pass messages,
you can pass the turn,
you can send exchanges
just as you would
in any other turn-based game.
It's also a really great way to
be able to plug in AI players,
which will allow you to be able
to have the same game logic
as you would otherwise
but also be able
to have your users be able to
play against different levels
of AI so they can learn how
to up their game faster.
So with guest players, as I
said before, you are going
to be defining the identifier,
and that identifier needs
to be unique across
each game session.
So whatever method
you end up using,
make sure that you are not going
to be having any collisions
on this identifier.
If you have one guest
player, on one device
and another guest player on
another device, just make sure
that those aren't
going to collide,
otherwise your game logic is
probably going to have problems.
These guest players can't
earn scores or achievements,
which makes sense, there's
nothing on the server
to post them to, but
you need to know that.
Sessions with guest players are
only compatible with sessions
with players that are
also running iOS 9.
Now, this does not lock
your game to iOS 9.
This only locks those individual
sessions with guest players
to other users that
are running iOS 9.
We try to make this a
little bit easier for you,
we won't be automatching anyone
that won't be able to join
that game and if one of your
users does extend an invitation
to multiplayer game to someone
who wouldn't be able to join,
we will be auto declining
that on the server side
on their behalf so you
shouldn't run into any issues
but it is something you
need to be aware of.
Again, this is not
locking your game.
Everything specified
in the compatibility
matrix will still work,
anyone who is running on
an older version of iOS
with your game will still work.
It's just those individual
gameplay sessions.
That's guest players.
We really hope that this is
going to allow you to create new
and interesting dynamic ways to
add to your multiplayer games
and we are really excited to see
what you're going to do with it.
Next up, we have the Game
Center Sandbox environment.
So Sandbox, we created to have
a separate environment for you
to be able to test out
Game Center functionality
without being on production.
But we had a completely
duplicate server,
you had to have different
accounts
and all the exact same
data in two places.
And this was really great.
But we feel that Sandbox
has really done its purpose,
and now we are going to unify
Sandbox with production.
So you will still
have two sets of data
but it will all be
running on the same server.
And this gives us a lot of
really good benefits, one,
this really simplifies
your accounts.
You no longer have to have
a separate Sandbox account
that you're going to have to
be worried about maintaining,
making friends with or dealing
with in any way like that.
This is really compatible
with TestFlight
so you can send your game out
on TestFlight for your testers
to be able to test with
and not have to worry
about them setting up Sandbox.
Multiplayer will now
work against any version
that you have published on that
server and this is automatic,
you don't have to do
anything to set this up,
we will be flipping
the switch on our side.
There are a few things that
you do need to be aware of.
First, any new game
that you will be working
on will actually show up in
your games list in Game Center.
So as you can see here,
me and demo-liscious are
working on GK tester.
And if you were demo-liscious'
friend, then you clicked
on her profile in the Game
Center app, if you clicked
on her games list, you would be
able to scroll through and see
that she was working
on that game.
If there's a game
you really don't want
to let anyone know about,
we do suggest that you set
up a separate account, however,
that shouldn't be too
much of a problem.
Any scores that you post,
while running your
game will be posting
to the same leaderboards.
And iOS 8 users will still
actually need to flip
that Sandbox switch in settings
because we will be
automatically errorring
out if they are not
thinking that they are going
into that Sandbox environment.
Well, Sandbox doesn't exist
so they won't actually be
in Sandbox but they will see
some of that same UI treatment.
But fortunately, everyone on
iOS 8 can upgrade to iOS 9,
so we just suggest that
you do that instead.
So let's go over what this
is exactly going to mean
for each one of these sections.
So leaderboards.
All of your versions
will be posting
to the same leaderboards.
However, if you have
an update to your game,
in which you've added
new leaderboards,
those leaderboards will only be
viewable to you or your testers
who are running that version,
that updated version
of your game.
No one else will be able
to see those leaderboards,
but everything else
you will be posting
to those same production
leaderboards.
Fortunately, everything is
iTunes Connect and that is going
to allow you to clear the
leaderboards before you publish
them or to call any scores
that you or your testers end
up posting either
erroneously or in a way
that you don't really
want to mess
up the integrity of
your leaderboards.
Those are easily clearable
through iTunes Connect
using your current tools.
For multiplayer, this is
a really huge benefit.
This is going to allow you to
be able to test your updates
to your multiplayer games
against games that are already
out there in the
wild in production.
Because there's no barrier
between the preproduction server
and the production server.
They are the same server.
So you will be able to
easily test and make sure
that any updates
that you are making
to your multiplayer
games are going to work
with whatever is
already out there.
For iTunes Connect, you will
be maintaining two completely
separate sets of metadata
that we will be maintaining
on the server.
You will have your currently
released version of your data,
as well as the unreleased
version of your data.
So which set of data that
you get, you or your users
or your testers is going to
depend on the CFBundleVersion
of the app that you have
installed on that device.
So if the CFBundleVersion
on your device is greater
than the release bundle
version that you would get
from the App Store, you will
be vended the unreleased data.
If the CFBundleVersion that you
have on your device is less than
or equal to the release bundle
version that you would download
from the App Store, you will be
vended the currently released
set of data.
If there isn't one
on the App Store,
then you will just be
getting the unreleased data.
It's the only data that exists.
So let's go over this again.
If you or one of your testers
is running a beta version
of your game, then that
game will be viewable
by your Game Center friends
in the Game Center app.
You will be able to play
against any other beta version,
that's the only versions
out there.
You'll be posting to
the beta leaderboards,
again those are the only
leaderboards that exist.
If you or one of your users
is running a released version
of your game, this is
kind of your normal case,
you will be able to see
the game in Game Center,
on your Game Center's
friends list.
You will be able to play,
if it's a multiplayer game,
against any version specified
in the compatibility matrix
and iTunes Connect,
including versions
that your game would not
necessarily know about because
that compatibility matrix
is stored on the server
and the server will
know that you can match
against those unreleased games.
You will be posting to
released leaderboards just
like you would expect.
If you or one of your testers
is running an updated version
of your game that has
not been pubbished
yet that game will still
be viewable in Game Center
in your Game Center friends list
and you will be able to play
against any specified
version, whether
or not it is the older version
of your game or the new version
of your game that you're
testing, anything specified
on the compatibility matrix, you
will be able to play against.
Then you will be posting
to release leaderboards
if the leaderboard already
exists or you will be posting
to an unreleased leaderboard
if that is a new leaderboard
for that game and those games --
those leaderboards will only
be viewable by those people
who have that version of
your game on their system.
So that's what's new.
First was guest players
which we really hope is going
to expand the multiplayer
opportunities that you have
for your game, as well as our
new unified server environment
which is really simple, it's
automatic, there's nothing
that you need to
do to set this up.
It's going to work so much
better with TestFlight,
which we feel will give you
guys a better way to be able
to get full functionality
testing on your game.
And I think that
this is really going
to just make your guys'
life a lot easier.
Now I will bring up Edwin
and he will tell you
about the new framework
replay kit.
[Applause]
>> EDWIN ISKANDAR: All right.
Thank you, Megan.
Good afternoon, I'm
Edwin Iskandar.
I'm a software engineer on the
graphics and games team here
at Apple and I'm here to
talk to you about ReplayKit.
So some truly memorable moments
happen during gaming, right,
like when you finally
get those three stars
in that seemingly
impossible level.
Or when you finally
beat that last boss
without losing a
single life point.
Wouldn't it be awesome
if you could capture
and share those moments?
So that's where ReplayKit
comes in.
ReplayKit records
the audio and visuals
of your running application.
It also allows you to use
this to add voice commentary
and so they can make their
recordings more personal or just
to provide additional context.
It allows your users
to play back,
scrub and trim their recordings
and finally share
their recordings
to their favorite
social networks
and video destination sites.
ReplayKit produces
high-quality HD recordings
that will look great on TV's,
websites and mobile devices.
And it does this
extremely efficiently
with a low-performance
impact while also minimizing
power usage.
ReplayKit includes
privacy safeguards
that help protect our users and
we'll talk a little bit more
about these in the next slide.
And it's available
today in the iOS 9 beta.
And later in the fall, to
customers when iOS 9 ships.
It's available in all
A7 and A8-based devices.
Like all of Apple's frameworks
ReplayKit takes the users
privacy very seriously.
So before ReplayKit
can start recording,
it requires that the
user give it permission,
and it does this via
user consent prompt.
ReplayKit also supports
parental controls
so if you have a device
that's often used by a child,
you can disable ReplayKit
systemwide via settings.
All recordings made via
ReplayKit will exclude
system UI.
That means that any personal
notifications that come through,
while recording, will
be excluded as well
as any keyboard entry
that happens in game.
And finally, applications
don't have direct access
to the movie files.
These are only accessible
to the user via ReplayKit's
preview UI and share sheet.
All right, so let's take a
look at how ReplayKit works
by taking a look at
its architecture.
So your application links
to the ReplayKit framework
and it uses these two
classes, RPScreenRecorder
which handles the
recording tasks
and RPPreviewViewController
which is responsible
for the preview UI
and share sheet.
So RPScreenRecorder communicates
with the replay demon
which is a separate process
from your application.
The replay demon communicates
with lower level video
and audio services which in turn
communicate with the hardware
to capture the visuals and
audio of your application,
as well as the audio data
from the device microphone.
During capture, the replay
demon will encode this data
in realtime and write
it to a movie file.
It will write this movie file
to a location only accessible
to ReplayKits internal services.
How does the user actually
interact with that movie then?
Well, when you tell
RPScreenRecorder
to stop recording it vends back
an RPPreViewViewController.
And you can simply present it,
and RPPreviewViewController
hosts the preview
and share extension which
does have access to the movie
and your users can
interact with that
to preview and share the movie.
As you can see, it's a pretty
complicated system with a lot
of moving parts but thankfully
for developers it really just
boils down to these two classes.
RPScreenRecorder and
RPPreviewViewController.
Pretty simple.
All right, so let's take a
deeper look into these classes.
So first up, is
RPScreenRecorder.
Again, it's responsible
for starting, stopping
and discarding the recording.
It can also be used to check
for the ability to record
and it can also be used
to enable the microphone
for commentary.
RPScreenRecorder has a
delegate that you can set
that should conform
to the RPScreenRecorder
delegate protocol.
And this delegate can be
used to check for changes
in availability, and also how a
case is if recording stops due
to an error, for example.
For the second class,
RPPreviewViewController,
again it's responsible for
previewing the recording,
editing and trimming and
fially sharing the movie.
RPPreviewViewController also
has a delegate that you can set
that should conform
to the
RPPreviewViewControllerDelegate
protocol.
That can be used to simply
dismiss the view controller
when the user is done
previewing and sharing.
That's literally it.
There are actually only two
classes and two protocols.
It's a really compact framework
and as you will see adoption
is incredibly simple.
So let's take a look
at this API in action
and I think the best way to
do that is to use an example.
So the example we are
going to use is a game
that the sample code team
created called DemoBots.
You have probably seen
this in other sessions.
Just in case you haven't,
the premise of DemoBots is
that you have this circuit
board where these task bots live
and the task bots
are responsible
for keeping the circuit
board running
but unfortunately all
the bots are buggy.
It's your job to debug them.
So each level in DemoBots
takes two to three minutes,
so it's short gameplay sessions
and you can download the source
at developer.Apple.com.
You should definitely
check it out.
It showcases a lot of Apple's
new gaming technologies.
It's a really great sample.
One of the reasons
why we chose DemoBots
to showcase ReplayKit is it has
this great scene flow that's
common to iOS games.
Once you launch DemoBots
you're treated to a main menu.
From the main menu,
you can start a game
and it transitions
you to the game level.
The game level, if you succeed
at the game level or fail at it,
will transition to
a level end scene
and from the level end scene,
you can either replay the level
or go to the next level.
So now that we know what
the scene flow looks like,
let's see how ReplayKit fits in.
Since we know that DemoBots has
short game play sessions we will
opt for an automatic
recording strategy.
And what I mean by that is
that we want to tell ReplayKit
to start recording immediately
when the game level starts
and we want to tell
it to stop recording
when the game level ends.
We also want to allow
the user to preview
and share the recording
but we don't want
to do this immediately after
we stop recording, right?
We want to do this when all
the action has died down.
A perfect place to do that
is the level end scene.
All right.
Pretty straightforward.
So let's step through this.
So first up is the main menu.
Since we are using that
automatic recording strategy,
we also want to allow the
the user to disable this
if they don't want to
auto record each level
and to do this we have
implemented an auto record
button on the top right
there that the user can use
to toggle this behavior
on and off.
So let's say a user toggles
this on and then presses
on the new game button.
At this point, we
transition to the game level
where the actual gameplay
happens and we want
to tell ReplayKit
to start recording.
Let's take a look at what
that looks like in code.
First things first, we need an
instance of RPScreenRecorder.
So each application has a shared
instance of RPScreenRecorder
which can be accessed with the
class function; shared recorder.
Pretty straight forward.
To start recording, we
call a start recording
with microphone enabled
on that shared instance,
and here you can specify if you
want voice commentary on or off.
You also supply a handle block,
and that handle block is
supplied an optional NSError.
If you receive an error here,
you should handle
it appropriately.
In our case we're just
going to pause the game
and alert the user and
that the recording failed.
Once you start the recording
with microphone enables,
the user is presented with
this user consent prompt.
And the user at this
point has three options.
It can choose to record the
screen and the microphone
to enable voice commentary.
They can just record
the screen only.
Or they can don't
allow recording at all.
So this user consent prompt will
be displayed everytime you call
a start recording with
microphone enabled,
but once the user has accepted
it, it will not be shown again
for another eight minutes.
Let's say the user now wants
to enable voice commenary
and also record the screen.
So they press on the record
screen and microphone button.
Okay, at this point
ReplayKit starts recording,
the game starts and
the user is playing,
providing voice commentary
and whatnot.
And they debug all the task
bots at that particular level.
At that point, they beat the
level and we want to transition
to that level end scene.
Before we do that, we want to
tell ReplayKit to stop recording
to do that in code, we simply
call stop recording with handler
on that shared recorder
instance and then
that handle block its
applied an optional NSError
and optional preview
view controller.
Again, handle that
error appropriately.
And for the preview
view controller,
you have a couple of options.
You can either present it
immediately or you can hang
on to it for later use.
So we are going to hang on
to it because we don't want
to display it just yet.
ReplayKit has stopped
recording and now we transition
to that level end scene.
And here we want to
allow user to preview
and share their movie.
We have implemented the
play recording button
that you see in the top right.
The user taps on that.
We want to present
that preview UI.
To do that in code, we
simply call UIViewController,
as present view controller
animated and we patch
in that preview view controller
that we held the
reference to previously.
That brings up replay
kit's preview UI
where the user can
scrub through, trim,
and finally share
their recordings.
Using ReplayKit's share UI.
So the share UI is implemented
with UI share preview controller
so you can even write your
own custom sharing extensions
in your app, which
is pretty cool.
So say the user wants to now
share this video to Facebook.
They tap on the Facebook button
and the Facebook modal shows up,
the video is already attached,
they can write a custom message
and then simply press post and
it will show up on their feed.
It's that simple for the user
to use and also really fun.
All right.
So now the video is posted
to the users Facebook feed,
and they are done sharing
and previewing, now they want
to cancel and dismiss
this preview UI.
So remember, we presented
the preview UI.
So we are also responsible
for dismissing it.
So to handle dismissal,
we simply set preview
view controllers delegate
and that delegate should conform
to RPPreviewViewController
delegate protocol
and should implement
preview controller did finish
with get supplied, a
preview view controller
and you simply call dismiss
view controller animated
on that preview view controller.
And that's basically it.
Just a couple lines of code,
we have a basic implementation
of ReplayKit in DemoBots,
it's really that simple.
So just to recap, we went over
how to get a shared instance
of the recorder, how to stop
and start the recorder and how
to present and dismiss
that preview UI.
All right.
Now that we have
the basics down,
let's go into some more advanced
topics to really fine tune
that ReplayKit implementation.
So first up is verifying
availability.
So ReplayKit may become
available or may be unavailable
for a number of reasons.
ReplayKit uses the same
technologies as AirPlay and TV
out to capture its
video content.
So unfortunately, it cannot be
used simultaneously with either
of those two services.
And as I mentioned before,
ReplayKit is supported
on A7 and A8 based devices.
Any older devices, ReplayKit
will not be available.
To check for availability,
you simply query the available
property and RPScreenRecorder.
And what do you do if
it's not available?
Well, you simply
discard any recording UI
in your game or app.
Since availability can
change in realtime,
you can also implement
RPScreenRecorder delegate screen
recorder to change the
availability to listen
for changes in availability.
Quick example, remember
the auto record toggle
that we had in DemoBots?
If ReplayKits not even available
on the device, we don't want
to show that toggle, right?
We query that available property
in RPScreenRecorder and use
that to drive the visibility
of the recording toggle button.
Simple. All right, next up
is discarding the recording.
So ReplayKit automatically
discards the previous recording
when a new recording starts.
So currently there can
only be one recording
at a time per application.
But there are cases
where you know
that the user no longer will
have access to the preview UI.
So you probably want
to discard it earlier.
So in our example with DemoBots,
if the user transitions
from the level end scene,
you know they're not going
to be able to preview
the video anymore
so you should probably
discard it.
To do that in code, in
our particular example,
and I will transition to
the next level scene --
next method, we simply call
discard recording with handler
and once that returns, we
transition to the next level.
Next up is recording indicators.
So when ReplayKit is
recording, you probably want
to notify the user that
recording is happening and also
if voice commentary
is on or off.
So to implement this, you can
simply query the recording
and the microphone enable
properties in RPScreenRecorder
and use the values of those
to toggle the visibility
of your recording indicators.
Again, pretty straightforward.
So next up is excluding UI.
So there's certain elements in
a game that are really useful
for users, but pretty
uninteresting
to spectators, right?
We just talked about
one of those.
Recording indicators.
They are great for the user
to know, but for a spectator,
they are pretty useless.
They know that the recording
is on and voice commentary is
on because they are
watching the video, right?
So you probably want
to exclude those.
A couple more examples
of virtual controls
and pause and menu buttons.
These may clutter
up the recordings
and not be necessary
for spectators.
How do you exclude UI
from the ReplayKit?
So ReplayKit only records your
applications main UI window.
If you want to exclude any UI,
you simply create a new instance
of UI window and place any
elements you want hidden
in that new instance.
That's excluding UI.
Next up is choosing
when to record.
So if you remember in DemoBots,
we know that DemoBots has short
game play sessions lasting only
two or three minutes.
So we went for an
automatic recording strategy
where we automatically
record each game level.
But some games are
different, right?
For example, in RPG, there's
longer gameplay sessions,
it might have more spread
out interesting events,
but it really doesn't make sense
to record the entire session.
Instead you should give the
user the ability to start
and stop recording at will.
To do this, you simply build
your own recording controls
that allow users to do that.
Again, all games are different.
So you should just
choose what is appropriate
for your particular game type.
All right, so that actually
concludes the fine tuning
session as well.
So we went over how to
verify availability,
how to discard the recording,
how to show the indicator,
how to exclude any UI, and also
choosing the best recording
strategy for your game.
Now, we would like
to show you a demo.
So a couple of weeks ago,
we invited Spacetime Studios
over to Cupertino to check out
ReplayKit and try to adopt it
into the upcoming game,
Call of Champions.
So I'd like to welcome
up on stage Cinco Barnes
from Spacetime Studios to
share his experiences with us.
Please welcome Cinco.
[Applause]
>> CINCO BARNES: Thanks, Edwin.
I'm Cinco Barnes.
I founded Spacetime Studios
with my partners back in 2005.
Our purpose was to make
hard core PC games but all
of that went out of the
window in 2009 with iOS
and the first iPad and our
release of Pocket Legends.
Since then we have been
dedicated to the iOS platform
for gaming and it's
been fantastic.
Today I get to talk to you
about Call of Champions
as a case for ReplayKit.
I definitely want to talk to you
about how it affects
the game itself
but the big message is how this
builds community, specifically
for us as a community
of gamers, active gamers
into something like this.
I want to give you a
little bit of history
on who we are in some context.
Spacetime Studios has always
endeavored to take core games,
distill them and adapt them into
our mobile gaming lifestyle.
It's the way that we
found our voice in trying
to provide things that are
both immediately accessible
and things that are
strategically rich.
And our next product here
is Call of Champions.
Call of Champions is
a mobile battle arena.
It's a three-on-three team game,
its got a neat Rugby-inspired
lane mechanic,
it's got shooter style
power ups in the middle.
The main thing is it's squeezed
into a five-minute segment
like a mixed martial arts fight.
We worked really hard to load
those five minutes with all
of the different choices and
all the different strategies
that we know that our
audience loves to play.
But we also know that the
audience that's attracted
to these kinds of games
doesn't just enjoy playing them.
They love to watch them.
They love to watch live games.
One of the things that we did
also was include a spectator
mode for watching just that,
live games anywhere
around the world.
And on its own this
satisfies our side of it.
But then we also know how
people would love to record
and share this as part
of the energy of creating
that community of gamers and
that's where ReplayKit comes in.
Here's an example of a replay
that I'm sharing with you.
As a designer of
a game like this,
I've got some top
level programmers
that are beating the heck
out of me and my partners
and I really want to show
off the features that we have
in spectator and
replays allows me to do
that here in this context.
There's tons of cool stuff
going on inside of this
but the addition of my
commentary and the presentation
of this in a shared environment
is really what ReplayKit is
all about.
I mean, we see how this works
really well for a game like Call
of Champions, but it's our
position that it would work
for anyone who is actively
trying to foster a community
in today's media-rich market.
That's an excellent
shot right there.
A skill shot, by the way
and a professional gamer,
killing my partner by
setting him on fire.
And capturing these moments
and being able to share them
from the tail end of a
game that was important
to me is exactly the
spirit of all of this.
So when I think about ReplayKit,
I see it as a crazy powerful
means to address this community
and to embrace the fact
that we are all playing,
we are all sharing and being
able to bring this stuff
to a game like Call of Champions
was really easy for us.
The implementation took us,
well we have one guy, Rick,
and he did it in a day.
So no excuses.
It's spectacular!
That's what I have
to say about it.
Thank you very much
for your time.
Edwin, I'm taking
it back to you.
[Applause]
>> EDWIN ISKANDAR:
Thank you, Cinco.
That was awesome.
So unfortunately that
concludes our session,
what's new in social gaming.
Just to recap, Megan talked
to us about the changes made
at Game Center, like adding
guest players which allow
for new player configuration
and Game Center multiplayer.
She also talked about how
we streamline development,
and testing of Game Center games
by unifying the server
environments and removing
that Game Center Sandbox.
And we introduced ReplayKit,
a whole new way to add social
into your games and it allows
you to record audio and visuals
in your running application
and it does it efficiently
and it has privacy
safeguards for the users.
As you have seen, it's an
incredibly compact framework
and has incredibly
simple adoption.
For more information, go to
developer.Apple.com and refer
to the documentation or
contact Alan Schaffer our game
technologies evangelist.
I urge you to download the iOS
9 data, check out ReplayKit,
get it into your games,
bring them to the labs
and show us what you've got.
That's it for me.
Thank you so much for attending.
I hope you enjoy the rest
of your WWDC experience.
Thank you.
[Applause]