[ Applause ]
>> DAN OMACHI: Good morning,
welcome to the second part
of our What's New in
Metal presentation.
My name is Dan Omachi.
I'm an engineer in Apple's
GPU software frameworks team.
Today my colleague Anna
Tikhonova and I will talk
about technologies
that build upon Metal,
helping you deliver great
rendering experiences
on both iOS and OS X.
So this is the second
of three sessions
at this years WWDC
talking about Metal.
In the first session, Rob
Duraf talked about developments
in Metal that have
happened in the past year.
He also described some
of the new features
in Metal we just released.
He also described how app
thinning is a great match
for your Metal applications.
In this session, I will be
up here first to talk to you
about MetalKit, convenience
APIs allowing you bring
up Metal applications
much more quickly.
Then Anna will come up to talk
about Metal performance
shaders framework,
which offers great shaders
for common data parallel
operations available
on iOS devices with
an A8 processor.
And tomorrow, you
will get a chance
to catch the Metal Performance
Optimization Techniques session,
where they will introduce
the Metal System Trace Tool
and provide you with
some best practices
for shipping an efficient
Metal application.
So let's get started
with Metal kit.
Utility functionality
for your Metal apps.
So because Metal is a low
level API, there are a number
of things you need to do
to get up and running.
MetalKit hopes to help with this
by providing efficient
implementation
for commonly used scenarios.
This requires less effort
on your part to get up
and rendering and we offer
increased performance
and stability over the
standard boilerplate code
that you might implement
yourself.
There is less maintenance
for you as the burden
of that maintenance has
been shifted from you to us.
So MetalKit consists of
three main components.
First is the MetalKit view.
A unified view class
between iOS and OS X
for rendering your Metal scenes.
Second is the texture loader
which creates texture objects
from image files on disk.
And finally, Metal kit's model
I/O integration which loads
and manages mesh data
from Metal rendering.
MetalKit view is
the simplest way
to get Metal rendering
on screen.
It's a unified class
on both iOS and OS X.
It offers pretty much
the same interface
on both Operating Systems,
but naturally it's a subclass
of UI view for iOS and a
subclass of NS view on OS X.
Its main job is to manage
displayable render targets
for you, and it creates
render path descriptors
for these render
targets automatically.
Now, it's super flexible
in terms of the ways
that it can execute
your draw code.
You can use a timer-based mode
where it will execute your
draw code at a regular interval
in synchronization
with a display,
or you can use an
event-based mode
which will trigger your
draw code whenever a touch
or UI event has occurred, so
you can respond to that event.
Finally, you can explicitly
drive your draw code,
perhaps in an open loop
on a secondary thread
at your own frame rate.
So there are two approaches
to using the MetalKit view.
The simplest approach is
to implement a delegate
to handle your draw
and resize operations.
In this case, you would
implement the draw
in view method to handle your
per-frame updates including
encoding any rendering commands.
You would also implement
the view will layout
with size method to handle
size changes to your view.
This is where you might
update your projection matrix
or change any texture sizes
to better fit your
displayable area.
Now, if you have any other
pieces of the view that you need
to override, you can
subclass the MetalKit view.
And in this case on iOS,
you would override
the draw Rect method
to handle your per-frame updates
and the layout subviews
method to handle resizes.
Likewise on OS X
you would handle,
you would override these
two methods, the draw Rect
and set frame size method.
So here is an example of
setting up a view controller
that also serves as the
delegate to our view.
In the view did load method,
after we received a reference
to the view, we will assign
ourself as the delegate,
and particularly important on OS
X is that we will need to choose
and set a Metal device.
Once we are done with
that, we can configure some
of the view's properties
including choosing our own
custom pixel formats
for the color
and depth and stencil buffers.
We can use multisampling
by increasing the sample count
property to a value above 1,
or we can set our
custom clear color.
Now, here is a very basic
usage of the MetalKit view
in the implementation
of the per frame update.
In our drawing view method,
we call the views render,
I'm sorry, current
render past descriptor.
Now, the first time you access
this property each frame,
the view will call
into core animation
and get a drawable back,
which you can encode
your rendering commands
and render to.
So we will render our
final render pass,
which will show up
in this drawable.
And then we will present the
drawable, which is stored
in the view's current
drawable property
and we will commit
our command buffer.
Now, because of its importance
in structuring your per-frame
updates, let me take a minute
to talk about managing
these drawables.
So there are a limited
pool of drawables
in this system all
managed by core animation.
There are only a few of them
mostly because of their size,
they take up some space.
Now, these drawables
are concurrently used
through many stages of
the display pipeline.
Here is roughly how it works.
First, your application
encodes commands
to be rendered onto
the drawable.
It sends that drawable
down to the GPU
as your application encodes
commands for the next frame
and the GPU renders to that
drawable, and core animation
at this stage may do compositing
with other layers
into that drawable.
And finally, the display
can take the drawable
and slap it up onto the screen.
Now, the display can't
replace it with anything
until another drawable
is available.
So if any of these previous
stages are taking a lot of time,
it just has to sit
there for awhile.
Additionally, the display can't
recycle that drawable back
up to your frame until it
has something available.
So let's take a look at
your application frame
with respect to these drawables.
First, you call the MetalKit
views current render past
descriptor which
reserves a drawable.
Then you will encode rendering
commands that you want
into that drawable, and
finally you will present
and commit the drawable
which will release it
back to core animation.
Now, this is fine if all we
are doing is rendering a single
render pass, however,
it's likely we will
do other operations
such as some app logic, encoding
in offscreen render pass
where we don't actually
need the drawable,
or running some compute
kernels for physics or whatnot.
In this case we are
essentially hogging the drawable
from our future self because
in a subsequent frame,
we will call this current
render pass descriptor
and it will sit there
waiting for a drawable
to become available,
which may not be the case
because we are doing these other
operations and reserving it
for much longer than we need to.
So to solve this problem,
let's put these operations
before our access
to the current render
pass descriptor.
Now, let me just note that
this isn't a problem specific
to the MetalKit view.
You need to be aware of this
issue if you roll your own view
in access core animation
directly.
So this is information that's
quite useful in any case.
Now, here is a more
complete example
of our per-frame
rendering update.
First, as I described we want to
update our app's render state,
encode any offscreen passes,
do anything where we
don't need the drawable.
And then we can continue
as we did previously,
get the current render pass
descriptor, encode our commands
for that final pass, and present
and commit our command buffer.
The key point is that
these two stages should be
as close together as possible.
It's a critical section where
we are holding onto a resource
and we don't want to hold onto
it any longer than we need to.
That's it for the view.
Let's move on to
the texture loader.
It's textural loading
made simple.
You give a reference and
you get back a fully formed
Metal Texture.
Not only is it simple, it's
fast and fully featured.
It asynchronously decodes files
and creates textures
on a separate thread.
It has support for many common
image file formats including
JPG, TIF and PNG and
also supports the PVR
and KTX texture file formats.
What's interesting about these
formats is that they store data
in a raw form that can be
uploaded to your Metal Texture
without any conversion.
Additionally, you can encode
data for MIT maps for any
of the other types of
textures including 3D textures,
cube maps, and texture arrays.
Its usage is really simple.
First, we create a
texture loader object
by supplying a device.
Then, once we have that
texture loader object,
we can create many
textures with it.
First, we will give a URL
location of our image file,
and we can supply a number of
options including how we want
to treat the sRGB information
in the file or whether
or not we want to allocate
memory for MIT maps
when we create this texture,
and finally we will supply
a completion handler block.
Now, this block will
get executed as soon
as the texture loader has
finished loading the texture
and created it.
It will pass the texture
handler back to you
which you can stash away
for later and render
with when you need to.
That's very simple,
the texture loader.
Let's move on to model I/O.
So model I/0 is a new
framework introduced
with iOS 9 and OS X El Capitan.
And one of its key features is
that it can load many
model file formats for you.
You can create your own
importers and exporters
for proprietary formats
if you need to.
Some of the cooler
features here are
that you can do offline
baking operations.
You can create static
ambient occlusion maps,
light map generations, it
also includes the Voxelization
of your meshes.
It provides you a way to
focus on your rendering code
and write your shaders.
You don't have to deal
with creating some parchers
to get some stuff off disk.
You have to deal less
with serialization,
you just load a model
file with Model I/O,
put it into some form
you can render it with,
and start writing your shaders.
So what does MetalKit
provide in this context?
It's utilities to efficiently
use model I/O with Metal.
It offers optimized
loading of model I/O meshes
into Metal buffers, the
encapsulation of mesh data
within MetalKit objects, and
there are a number of functions
to prepare mesh data
for Metal pipelines.
Let me walk you through the
process of loading a model file
with model I/O and getting it
rendering on screen with Metal.
And here are the
steps we will take.
So first, we will create a
Metal render state pipeline
that we'll use to create our
mesh, to render our mesh.
Then we will actually
load the model file
by initializing the
model I/O asset.
And with that asset, we
will create MetalKit mesh
and sub mesh objects.
Finally, we will render
those objects with Metal.
So let's focus on creating a
Metal Render State Pipeline
and we will pay particular
attention
to creating a vertex descriptor
that will describe the layout
of vertices that we'll
need our mesh to be
in to feed our pipeline.
Here is the bare bones
of a vertex shader.
It uses the stage in
qualifier which basically says
that our per vertex
inputs, the layout for them,
will be described
outside of the shader
in our objective-C code
using a vertex descriptor.
It uses this vertex
input structure
which is defined up here.
And the key part of this vertex
input structure are these
attributes, the indices here
which we will use to connect
up outside inside of
our Objective-C code.
Note that these floating-point
vector types define how the data
looks within the shader, not
actually how the data looks
as it's being fed
into the shader
from our Objective-C code.
For that, we need to
create a vertex descriptor.
Now, I'm going to put this
vertex input structure
up here just for reference,
but let me just remind you
that it does not define
the layout of the data
as it's being fed
into the shader.
We are actually creating
the Metal Vertex Descriptor
that is down below.
And for that, what we will
do is for attribute zero,
the position will define as
using three floating points,
three floating point values.
For attribute one, the color
will specify that it's going
to be composed of four
unsigned characters,
not the four floats above,
four unsigned characters
and it will have an offset
of 12 bytes immediately
following the position data.
Now, for the texture coordinates
in attribute 2, we will define
that it uses two half floats.
And that it immediately follows
the position and color data
with an offset of 16 bytes.
And finally, we will
specify that the size
of each vertex is 20 bytes
by setting the stride
to 20 for that buffer.
Now, this defines the
layout of each vertex
within our array of vertices.
So now that we have got our
Metal Vertex Descriptor,
we can assign it to our
render state pipeline,
and with that render --
excuse me, with the
render pipeline descriptor,
we can create a Metal
Render State Pipeline.
So let's move on to
actually loading our asset
and using model I/O
for that task.
And we will actually use the
vertex descriptor we just
created in the previous step,
along with a MetalKit
mesh buffer object,
a mesh buffer allocator object.
I will describe a
little bit more
about its importance
as we continue.
So the model I/O
vertex descriptor
and Metal Vertex
Descriptor are very similar,
but while the model I/O vertex
descriptor describes the layouts
of vertex attributes
within a mesh,
the Metal Vertex Descriptor
describes the layout
of vertex attributes
as their input
to a render state pipeline.
Now, they are intentionally
designed to look similar
as they contain attribute
and buffer layout objects,
and the reason for this is
it simplifies the translation
of one object to another.
Now, each attribute in a model
I/O vertex descriptor has an
identifying string base name.
Model I/O assigns a default
name if one does not exist
in the model file or that
model file does not support
these names.
These names include position,
normal, texture, coordinate,
color, et cetera, and
model I/0 defines these
with the string based
MDLVertex attribute constants.
There are a number of files
including the Alembic file
format where you can
customize those names.
Be aware if you are changing
the names you will need
to access these attributes
with those customized names.
So we recommend that you create
a custom model I/O vertex
descriptor, because by default
model I/O loads vertices
as high-precision
yet memory-hungry
floating-point types.
This is one of the
advantages of using model I/0.
You can actually load a model
format and have the vertex data
in any form that you would like
and use model I/0 to massage
that data into a format
you can actually use.
In this case, we want
to feed the pipelines
with the smallest type
that meets your precision
requirements.
This would improve your
vertex bandwidth efficiency;
as you are feeding each
vertex to the pipeline,
you don't really want
a bloated vertex.
So here is the layout
we defined previously
when creating our Metal
Vertex Descriptor.
Now, we will create our
model I/O vertex descriptor
by calling this MTK model
I/O vertex format from Metal
and we will supply our
Metal Vertex Descriptor.
This builds the majority of this
model I/O vertex descriptor,
yet we still need to tag
each attribute with a name,
so model I/O knows what
we are talking about.
So for attribute
0, we will tag it
with the vertex attribute
position name.
And similarly for attribute
1 and 2, we will tag them
with a color and texture
coordinate attributes.
The other thing we will do here
is we will create a MetalKit
mesh buffer allocator and we
will supply a Metal device.
Now, what this object does
is it allows model I/0
to load vertex data directly
into GPU backed memory.
Now, you don't have to use a
MetalKit mesh buffer allocator,
but what that will do is it
will allocate system memory
for these vertex and index
buffers inside of the mesh.
And when you want to actually
render it, we will need to copy
from that system memory down
into the GPU backed memory.
So for efficiency, it's
really desirable to use one
of these mesh buffer allocators,
and here is how you use it.
Now, we are going to
load our asset file.
We will supply the URL location,
the model I/0 vertex descriptor
which will tell model I/0
how to lay out each vertex
and we will also supply
this mesh buffer allocator
so that model I/0 can
load this data directly
into GPU backed memory.
So now that we have
got our asset,
let's actually create
some MetalKit mesh
and some mesh objects.
So here's an example of an asset
that might be created
by model I/0.
Inside of an asset, we
might have camera objects,
light objects, and
particularly important
to us right now are
the mesh objects.
Now, MetalKit is
primarily concerned
with these mesh objects.
It doesn't really deal
directly with the light
and camera objects because that
sort of data is very specific
to your custom shaders
and your engines.
You can actually
introspect into this object
or go look inside this object
and grab out that camera
and light information to
plug it into your shaders,
but MetalKit isn't directly
involved in that process.
So what we can do is pass
in this asset directly
to this mesh, meshes
from asset class function
which will create an
array of MetalKit meshes.
Let's take a look at what's
inside this mesh object.
So first are these
vertex buffers
which includes the
position attributes,
the normal attributes,
textural attributes, et cetera.
In our example, we
only needed one array
because we interleaved
all of our data.
However, you can define the
layout to use multiple arrays,
and therefore you would have
multiple vertex buffers.
You could define that
attribute 0 would be inside
of a single array, so you would
have an array of positions
in one array, an array of
texture coordinates in the next,
another array with
colors, and so on.
The mesh also includes
a vertex descriptor
which defines this layout
and it's the same object
we just created and passed
in when we initialized
our asset.
And finally, the mesh contains
a number of sub mesh objects.
Now, the key part of each
sub mesh object is this index
buffer, which references
vertices inside the
vertex buffer.
Additionally, there are a number
of properties which you can use
to make a draw call with Metal.
So now that we have
got our Metal kit mesh
and sub mesh objects, let's
go ahead and render them.
So first we will iterate
through each vertex buffer.
Now, we may have a sparse
array, so we need to make sure
that there is actually
something in each buffer,
but once we are sure of
that, we can continue on
and set the vertex buffer
in our render encoder.
Now, the vertex buffer
actually has two properties,
the buffer itself, and an
offset within the buffer
where your vertex data resides.
We also need to supply a buffer
index telling the pipeline
exactly where the data is.
Now, we will actually
render our mesh.
We will iterate through
every sub mesh,
and make our draw
index primitives call.
Note here that the sub mesh
has all of the parameters
for this draw index parameter.
So today we posted this
MetalKit essentials sample
on the WWDC 2015 site.
I encourage you to download it.
It describes a number of
the techniques I described.
It uses model I/0 to load this
little airplane object that's
stuffed in an OBJ file and
creates a MetalKit mesh
and renders it on screen.
So you can get an idea of
exactly how this is all done.
So I encourage you
to check that out.
So that's it for me,
my name is Dan Omachi,
I will be at the Metal Lab
tomorrow if you have questions
about topics I have discussed.
I would like to welcome my
colleague, Anna Tikhonova
on stage to talk about the Metal
performance shaders frameworks.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> ANNA TIKHONOVA: Good morning.
Thank you, Dan, for the
introduction, my name is Anna
and I will be talking to you
about Metal performance shaders.
Let's get started.
So first of all, what is it?
It's a framework of optimized
high performance data parallel
algorithms for the GPU in Metal.
When and why would you use it?
If you are writing
C code and you want
to add a common sorting
algorithm
to your CPU application, you are
very unlikely to implement one
from scratch unless it
was out of self-interest.
You are a lot more likely to
use the implementation provided
to you by the library because
it's already been debugged
and optimized for you.
Likewise, if you wanted to add
an image processing operation
to your CPU application,
on our platform,
you would use the
accelerate framework
because it uses vImage.
It's a powerful,
high-performance tuned image
processing framework for --
that utilizes the CPU's
vector processing.
These are just a few examples.
The point is that there is
a rich environment available
for your CPU applications.
On the GPU the story
is a bit different,
you simply have fewer
options but we would
like to change the story.
Our goal is to enrich your
Metal programming environment.
We have selected a
collection of common filters
that we see often used in
graphic processing pipelines
in your image processing
applications and games.
These algorithms are
optimized for iOS and available
in iOS 9 for the A8 processor.
The Metal performance shaders
framework has two goals,
performance and ease of use.
It's designed to
integrate easily
into your Metal applications.
It operates on Metal
resources directly.
They are the input
and the output.
We are not only giving
you collection
of these high performance
optimized awesome kernels --
we are giving you that, but
we are also taking care of all
of the host code necessary
to launch these kernels.
We take care of the
decision-making process of how
to split up the work for
parallel computation.
The work you have to do to take
advantage of this framework
in your applications
usually amounts
to only a few lines of code.
It's as simple as calling
a library function.
So now that I have introduced
the framework to you,
let's take a look at the
available operations.
Here is a full list and let's
start from the beginning.
I will cover just a
few of these actually
and I will show you examples.
So first, the framework
supports the histogram filter
and the histogram equalization
and specification filters.
The equalization and
specification filters,
they allow you to
change the distribution
of color intensities
in your image.
The equalization filter
is a special case.
It changes the distribution
from the current
distribution to the uniform one.
And the specification
filter enables you
to set any distribution
of your choice.
You specify the histogram that
will be used in the filter.
This is an example of
the equalization filter.
It increases the global
contrast in the image.
Here it brings out the rainbow
in the sky quite beautifully.
One thing I'd like to mention
about these filters is they
are not an end in themselves.
They can be used as
an intermediate step
in a more complex algorithm.
The histogram filter can be
used as an intermediate step
in implementing tune mapping,
which is a technique commonly
used by graphics developers
to approximate the appearance
of high dynamic range.
So moving on, we also
support Lancos resampling.
It's a high-quality resampling
algorithm that can used
to downscale, upscale,
squeeze, and stretch images.
In this example, I
stretched the image vertically
and squeezed it horizontally
while preserving all
of the image content.
You also support the
thresholding filter.
It can be used to
find image edges
if chained with a Sobel filter.
Let's take a look at an example.
This is the output of
the thresholding filter,
and now it's fed into the Sobel
filter to give you image edges.
And finally we support
a whole range
of convolution kernels
including general convolution,
where you can specify your
own convolution matrix.
And we also support
Gaussian blur,
box tent, and Sobel filters.
My final example will
be of a Gaussian blur.
You should all be
very familiar with it;
we like to use it in our UI.
What if you wanted to
use a Gaussian blur
in your own application,
the Metal performance shaders
framework makes it very easy.
How easy, you ask?
I'm building some
anticipation here.
It's just two lines of code.
You first have to create a blur
filter object, and then you have
to encode the filter
to the command buffer.
And that's it [applause].
Thank you, guys.
And one thing I just wanted to
point out again and just note is
that this API takes your common
Metal resources as input.
Your device, your command
buffer, your textures.
These are the Metal resources
that you already create
in your application.
And now that I have shown
you these two lines of code,
let's take a look
at where they plug
in into your current
Metal work flow.
So this is a graphical
representation
of your command buffer.
It contains all of the
commands you are going
to be submitting to the device.
You do your work as
you usually would.
You render your scene
by issuing draw calls
and you do your post processing
effect by dispatching kernels.
Now you have decided that one
of your post processing effects
is going to be a blur filter.
So this is exactly
where it goes.
And don't forget that you still
have to submit your commands
to the device as
you normally would.
Nothing changes here.
And now, if you would like
to look at the sample code
for the example I was
just going through,
you could do so right now.
You can go to
developer.Apple.com
and download the example called
Metal performance shaders
hello world.
I've mentioned before that
the Metal performance shaders
framework has two goals,
performance and ease of use.
I just showed you how
easy it is to use.
Let's take a quick
look behind the scenes
at what's giving you
this performance.
For every one of these filters
including the Gaussian blur
filter, we had to choose
the right algorithm.
The right here means correct
and it has to be the fastest.
The fastest for a particular
combination of input data,
input parameters,
and device GPU.
What do I mean by this?
There are multiple ways to
implement Gaussian blur.
There are constant
cost, log 2, linear,
and brute force algorithms.
All of these approaches
have different start
up costs and overheads.
One approach may work really
well for a small kernel radius
but perform very poorly
on a large kernel radius.
The point is we had to implement
each one of these approaches
and find out experimentally
which one is going
to be the fastest for a
particular combination
of input problem, input
parameters, and device GPU.
And after this process, all
of the kernels had to be tuned
for such parameters
as your kernel radius,
your pixel format,
your underlying hardware
architecture's memory hierarchy,
and such parameters as
number of pixels per thread
and thread group dimensions.
This is what determines how to
split up your work in parallel.
And finally, I would
like to mention
that the framework also performs
CPU optimizations for you.
It optimizes program
loading speed.
It also reuses intermediate
textures,
and finally it does some compute
encoder optimization for you.
Specifically, it can defect
if you are using multiple
computing coders in a row and if
so it will coalesce them.
And after we have done all
of these steps for you,
that's cool, but what would
this actually look like in terms
of code, for example, for an
optimized Gaussian blur shader
that I just showed you?
Well, are you ready for it?
Here is the code.
So now all of you know how
to implement your own
optimized Gaussian blur, right?
I bet you didn't
know you were going
to learn this in this session.
Basically all joking aside,
this is 49 Metal kernels,
2,000 lines of kernel code
and 821 different Metal
Gaussian blur implementations
where each implementation
is some combination
of these 49 Metal kernels, so it
looks like a lot of work we did
and now you don't have to.
Now, let's take a look
at the Metal performance
shaders framework in action.
So first, I will
demonstrate the performance
of a simple textbook separable
Gaussian blur implementation
that took only minutes
to write in Metal.
This is probably something you
would start with if you had
to implement your own blur
and you didn't have Metal
performance shaders available
to you.
So now we are happily running
at 60 frames per second
but we are not actually
doing any work yet.
The sigma value is 0.
Let's change the sigma value
to 6 and we are down to
about 8 frames per second.
Dare we go any further?
Let's try a sigma of 20.
Okay. And we are down
to 3 frames per second
so that's not going to work.
Let's switch to the
Metal performance
shaders implementation.
So now we are back to
60 frames per second,
not doing any work, sigma of 6.
Still 60 frames per second.
Sigma of 20.
And, of course, we had to go
further and really blur it,
still at 60 frames per second.
So this looks like a winner.
[ Applause ]
Okay.
So your screen refresh
rate is 60 hertz.
This means that we are running
at 60 frames we are second,
so the performance of this
optimized Gaussian blur shader
you have seen in the demo is
capped at 60 frames per second.
This means that you have 16.6
milliseconds to draw your frame,
and this also includes
any compositing work
that your system
might need to do.
This chart shows you
the execution time
of this optimized Gaussian blur
filter for different values
of sigma and as you can see,
the execution time is a lot less
than 16.6 milliseconds.
So this means that you
still have some extra time
to do additional GPU work,
and still hit the desired
60 frames per second.
And now there are just a
few more details I would
like to cover.
Sometimes you will need to
work on very large images
and you will need to tile them.
And sometimes you
will just need to work
on a portion of your image.
So there is a mechanism
for that.
It's called source offset
and destination clip Rect.
Clip rect has an
origin and size.
It determines the region
of the destination texture,
which is going to be
updated by a filter.
The source offset
only has an origin.
The size is implicit, it's
determined by the clip rect,
and it is just an offset
from the upper left corner
of your source texture.
They work together to
give you the final image.
In the Metal performance
shaders framework your source
and destination can be
one in the same texture.
In this case, the clip rect
and source offset work
exactly the same way.
When the source and destination
are the same texture,
we call it an in
place operation.
Use it to save memory.
How could you do you
actually encode one
of these filters in place?
You have to use the encode to
command buffer method that takes
in place texture and a fall
by back copy allocator.
One thing to keep in mind
here, it's not always possible
for the shaders to run in place.
It depends on your filter,
on the filter parameters
and properties.
If you want this operation
to always succeed,
use a copy allocator.
It will be called automatically,
only in the situation where the
in place operation
is not possible.
And we will create a new
destination texture for you
so that the operation
can proceed
out of place if necessary.
And here is an example of a
simple fall back copy allocator.
This one simply creates
a new destination texture
with the same pixel
format and dimensions
as the source texture,
very simple.
So now I have shown you
an example before of an
in place operation where
you only modified a portion
of your destination texture
and everything outside
of the clip rect
remained unchanged.
You can also do this
in the copy allocator.
Just initialize your destination
texture with the contexts
of your source texture.
And I would also like
to mention that all
of the usual Metal
resources such as your device
and your command buffer
are available to you
in the copy allocator.
Now that I have covered
these details,
let's jump into the summary.
I would like to say please use
the Metal support frameworks,
MetalKit and Metal performance
shaders, they are robust,
they are optimized, and as I
have shown you, they're easy
to integrate into your
Metal applications.
They will allow for faster bring
up time of your applications.
Now, you can spend the time
on making application
unique instead
of implementing common tasks.
And, of course, as an added
benefit, there is less code
for you to write and maintain.
And come to our labs,
give us feedback.
Let us know how to get
started or give us questions.
Let us know if there are new
utilities or shaders you would
like to see added to
the support frameworks.
You can always find
more information online.
We have documentation videos
available, and take advantage
of the Apple Developer
Forums and technical support.
For general inquiries,
contact our gaming technologies
evangelist Allan Schaffer.
You can watch the past sessions
online, but if you would
like to learn new Metal
performance optimization
techniques, come to
our talk tomorrow
at 11:00 a.m. Thank you.
[ Applause ]