>> DANVIN RUANGCHAN: All
right, good morning, everyone,
and welcome to session 701.
My name is Danvin, and I'm
really excited to be here today
to talk to you guys
about Wallet,
the app formerly
known as Passbook.
All right.
With a new name, we
also have a new logo!
And you may have seen our
icon if you installed iOS 9,
this is now our new icon, but
beauty is more than skin deep.
We have been working on a
lot of features for Wallet
over the past few years.
We will talk about a
few of those today.
So let's take a look at
our agenda and take a look
at what we will be
talking about today.
First we're going to take a
glance at what we've been up to
and then a quick history lesson
and review all of
Wallet's features.
We will talk about
what is a Pass.
We will talk about PassKit,
our framework inside iOS
and we're going to talk about
Apple Pay and then there's more!
So stick around.
We have a lot of content
to talk about today.
So what have we been up to?
Well, Apple Pay is
what we have been up to
and Apple Pay was
introduced last fall,
and the responses
have been great!
Consumers have loved
its ease of use.
And merchants have loved
its higher conversion rates.
And now with Apple Pay we have
now enabled contactless payments
on our phones, our watches.
We even released an API
so you can take Apple Pay
inside your apps as well.
But to understand the
essence of Wallet,
to understand what we are about,
we need to take a look back.
Take a look back and
see how we got here.
Does this ring a bell?
Does this look familiar
to anyone.
Does anyone have a wallet
that looks like this?
I'm sure someone out there
who has a wallet
that looks like this.
This is a real problem.
We stick our gift cards in here,
our debit cards and credit cards
and our coupons and
then when we try
to find something,
we can't find it.
The overstuffed wallet
is a real problem.
And we are trying to solve
that problem with Wallet.
We do so with passes.
We have beautiful
passes inside Wallet.
We have passes for coupons, for
event tickets for store cards,
and even for boarding
passes as well.
But all the things that
these passes have in common,
is that they all allow us to
take action in the real world.
And now, with Apple Pay,
we have your credit cards
and debit cards inside
Wallet as well.
But we went beyond that.
We want to solve the problem
where we can't find the thing
at the right place at the
right time so we built
in relevancy inside
our passes as well.
And they look like this.
If you come to the airport,
your boarding pass is right
there waiting for you.
All I do is swipe
on the lock screen
and my boarding pass
is ready to use.
It's so great!
It's that great surprise in the
light factor that this brings.
But let's take a
look at these passes.
In essence, these passes
contain information.
On the top left-hand corner
you will see there's a logo.
It clearly states the entity
that this pass belongs to.
In this particular
case we are looking
at a United boarding pass.
So their logo is
predominantly up there
in the top left-hand corner.
We put our important
information in our header field.
In this case, our gate
information is present there.
Our users will know exactly
what gate they need to go to,
when boarding time arrives.
We put our important information
down in our primary fields.
And this particular case, we
have a flight that takes off
from Newark and arrives
in Stockholm.
We also have auxiliary and
secondary fields and this is
where we put our nice go to
know pieces of information,
things like the seat number.
And, of course, we
have our bar code.
And this is that link.
It's the message that connects
the users to your system,
to be able to take action in the
real world, and in this case,
this boarding pass will allow
the user to board a flight.
And we can flip this
to the back.
We call this the
back of the pass.
And you'll notice right away
on the very top you can
associate an app with this pass,
and appropriately we have the
United Airlines app associated
with this pass.
There are two options
for users here as well.
To be able to automatically
update this pass,
that's very important
we're going touch
on that a little bit later in
our presentation to be able
to update these passes to
keep information up to date.
We can also turn on and
off relevancy on and off
on the back of the pass as well.
That's the option there,
Suggest Pass on Lock Screen.
And along with that, on
the back of the pass,
with he have some other nice
to know pieces of information,
things like terms can go
open the back of the pass.
What makes a pass a pass?
Let's take a look at this
beautiful MLB event ticket.
The pass is made from
a pass.json file.
The contents and the layout
of this pass is defined
in that file.
And it just your standard JSON
file with keys and values.
In this case the keys and
values determine the content
and the styling and the
layout of this pass.
And this MLB pass also has
some really beautiful images.
We have a logo that's an image
on the top left-hand corner
and we have a strip image
that spans that pass.
It really makes that
pass come to life.
And when we package
all of these things
up together we get what
is called a PKPass file.
And the file hierarchy
looks something like this.
Your PKPass file will
contain the pass.json
and those images we talked
about and there are a couple
of other files in there
I want to point out.
First of all, there are
localized strings in here.
Yes, passes can be localized,
I will encourage
you guys to do so.
You'll also notice
on the bottom,
the manifest file
and a signature file.
Our passes are cryptographically
signed
so that their authenticity
can be verified
and that the users know that the
pass came from a known entity.
This is great.
So now with a PK pass file
and this is now just
a generic pass file.
How do we make this unique?
How do we make this your pass?
Well we use three
different values to be able
to determine the
uniqueness of your pass.
The first one is
the teamIdentifier
and this is just a 10 character
string that you can find
in the developer portal and
we use this to entitle apps
to gain access via
PassKit, our framework.
The second value we use
is a passTypeIdentifier.
And now this defines the class
or the category of passes
that this particular pass is.
You register for this in the
developer portal as well.
We also use this value
to group passes together.
And lastly, we have
the pass serialNumber.
And now, this is unique
for every single pass.
And it's completely chosen
by you, and opaque to us.
Now, when we combine this
value, the serialNumber
with a passTypeIdentifier,
we get our guaranteed global
uniqueness for your pass.
Along with all of these
values, the pass.json is also
where you declare
your pass' relevancy.
Let's take a look
at relevancy now.
Relevancy can be determined
by three different categories.
You can use date.
You can use location.
And you can use beacons.
And it's the combination
of these categories
that make these passes
really, really powerful.
So let's take a look at
how we implement relevancy
on our pass.json.
We have a few keys.
First of all, we're going
to take a look at
the locations key.
That takes an array
of dictionaries
and that dictionary will contain
in it a latitude, a longitude
and an optional relevantText.
This relevant text will
then appear when your users
in that locate or
near that location.
So it's good to declare
those to be able to clarify
to your user exactly why
that's shown to the user.
And then we have
the relevantDate,
and that's just your standard
W3C format, relevantDate,
and then we have our beacons.
The beacons key is an array.
Inside that array
are dictionaries,
the proximityUUID will
uniquely identify your beacon.
Again, we have that relevantText
and the optional name
field here as well.
Again, it's when you combine all
of these relevancy
categories together is
when you make your passes
really, really powerful.
And it's a great surprise
in the live feature
for your users as well.
Passes are only interesting to
the user when the information
on them is up to date.
So how do we keep our
passes up to date?
Now, I'm going to give
a very high level glance
at how this works,
and I'm going to refer
to a WWDC talk we
gave back in 2012
that goes really
in-depth into this topic.
Let's take a look at this now.
So your server will implement
the Apple Push Service.
And we utilize the Apple Push
Service to start a pass' update.
We get pass down, a
passTypeIdentifier.
That's what we talked about
a couple of slides earlier.
With that passTypeIdentifier,
we then look at your pass.json
and look for the webService key.
That webService key will
contain a URL that we can hit
and ask for updated passes.
And then we get brand new
.pkpass files with updates
on them sent down to our devices
and we update the user's pass.
Now that's a very high level
view of how this works.
I would highly recommend going
back to that WWDC talk from 2012
and dig into how to implement
a web service for your passes.
Okay. This is great.
Now, let's take a look at how
we can programmatically get
to these passes.
We do have PassKit
after all inside iOS.
Let's see how we use it.
The main class that
we're going to be using
in PassKit is PKPassLibrary.
This is your link.
This is what you are
going to use to be able
to query your user's passes,
and access to it is
gated by entitlements.
We talked about that
a little bit earlier,
using your passTypeIdentifier.
Let's take a look at some of the
methods inside PKPassLibrary.
First we have a function
that asks,
is the PassLibrary
available on this device.
This is a very good
question to ask.
When we get a positive answer
back, you can then get passes.
When you call passes, you will
get back an array of PKPass.
And these are all the passes
that you are entitled to see.
You can also find a
particular, a specific pass
that you are looking
for by calling
passWithPassTypeIdentifier,
serialNumber, passing
it the identifier string
and the serial number string.
That will get you the exact
pass that you are looking for.
We also have another
one called passesOfType,
passing a PKPassType.
And you may wonder what are
all the different pass types?
Well here they are
there's Barcode,
there's Payment and there's Any.
So you may ask yourself, Danvin,
why would you want
to get passes?
Why do you want to see
your user's passes.
Well as a developer
you may want to know --
any of your passes that your
users already have on the system
so you don't duplicate
things again.
For payment passes, we're
going talk about earlier,
banks and other merchants
may want to be able
to activate payment passes
from your users' pass library.
We will get into that when we
get into the Apple Pay section.
Now we have our passes
together, they're beautiful,
they're relevant, they're up
to date, how do we get them
in the hands of our users.
Well the PKPass file is pretty
portable, so you can host them
on a website, you can
email them to your users,
you can even include
them inside your apps.
And I want to point one
neat little feature,
we give special treatment
to PKPass files inside
our iOS apps like Mail.
When we receive a PKPass file
in our email Mail will give
it some special treatment
with this action button and you
can see exactly what PKPass file
is in that email.
And if you host this on a
website or put this on an app,
we even have a banner for you,
you can include inside your
sites and on your apps.
But you may be telling
me, Danvin,
you know that says Passbook.
I know. I know this
says Passbook.
This is a good little
transition for me to talk about.
We are in the middle
of a transition.
We are moving from
Passbook to Wallet.
And for now, in the public, we
are still known as Passbook.
So be aware of that.
But please stay tuned as
we get closer and closer
to iOS 9's release, we will keep
you up to date on this topic.
I'm really glad we got
to talk about that.
But let's say we want to add
these passes programmatically,
how would you do that?
Well, PKPassLibrary does that.
We have a function in
there called addPasses.
That's right, multiple passes.
Why would you want to do this?
Well, consider a flight with
multiple segments and you want
to be able to ingest all
the passes all at once.
This is a great way to do that.
So addPasses
withCompletionHandler will alert
the user with a small
and very subtle dialog
to add these passes
into their library.
Please make sure before you call
this that you already denoted
to the user that they
are about to add a pass.
We do have one more way to add
passes into the pass library
and that's using
PKAddPassesViewController.
you may have seen this before if
you have added passes to Mail.
It looks something like
this, you tap on a pass,
they call
PKAddPassesViewController
and we get this nice beautiful
view controller fully rendered
out with an action up top
for the user to choose.
How does this work.
PKAddPassesViewerController
has a function
that checks can you add
passes to this device?
And then like before, you
can add a single pass,
or multiple passes.
So you knit one of these guys
and then you just show this
view controller and we take care
of rendering that pass for you.
Great. Now we can add passes.
We can keep them updated.
We can keep them relevant.
But how do we keep
these passes engaging?
All right.
We want our users
to keep coming back
and take a look at our passes.
So I have a few tips for you
to keep our passes engaging.
As I mentioned before
relevancy is a big deal.
Relevancy will give that
big surprise in the life,
kind of feel for the users.
You want to keep
our passes updated.
For example, this pass,
this boarding pass,
it's useless unless we have
the latest gate information.
Users want to come back and
keep looking at your passes.
Images are great.
For example, this MLB
pass that we looked
at has this strip image that
spans the entirety of the pass.
It really brings life
and also brings clarity
as to what this pass is
actually for and what it does.
This is called a strip image.
You notice that there's no
extra information there.
It's just for context.
It's beautiful!
And lastly, I want to
talk about formatting.
Formatting is tricky.
But we take care
of this for you.
And now we know we
have different devices
with different screen sizes.
And so what I recommend is you
take a look at our HI guidelines
on the website follow them
and we will do our very best
to make your passes look really
great on all of our devices.
Great. These passes have
been really, really useful.
They really let us take
action in the real world.
But they are not as slick
as what that experience
with Apple Pay is yet.
So how do we make that
experience a lot better?
Well, let's talk about
where we go from here.
Let me give you a scenario.
So the other day, I go
to my local neighborhood grocery
store, and I pick up my things
and I'm ready to check out.
Great, they take Apple Pay.
As I head to the terminal, the
clerk is ringing up my things
and I get my phone ready
to pay with Apple Pay.
All right.
They are done ringing up my
things and I bring my phone
to the terminal and...
do you have a loyalty
pass with us?
I think I do.
The clerk is really -- really
adamant about this loyalty card.
I think it's in that
big fat wallet of mine.
Oh, I can't find it right now.
I know it's on my phone number.
It's got to be registered
with my phone number.
I blurt my phone
number to the clerk.
Nope. It's not registered
with that phone number.
I'm frustrated and the
line is two or three deep.
I just blurt out my
mom's phone number
because I know my mom
has one of these things.
Great. That works!
And I now can Apple Pay
and I grab my things
and I'm out the door.
So a lot of bad things
happen there.
For me as a consumer,
I just want to pay.
I want to get my
things and be done.
For the merchant, they just
got the completely wrong
loyalty information.
They got my mom's loyalty
information, not mine.
So we want to make this better.
And that's why we are
introducing passes
that work with Apple Pay.
Passes that work with Apple
Pay transmit your loyalty
information, contactlessly along
with your Apple Pay transaction.
We use the Value Added
Services Protocol
and we have been working with
major terminal manufacturers
for the adoption of
this new protocol.
So now, my scenario
looks more like this.
I go to my friendly
neighborhood Walgreens.
They take Apple Pay, great,
I use the new iOS feature
and double tap on my home
button and I can prearm my card.
I can get my card ready before
I even head up to the terminal.
Great. My card is ready and I
head up to pay for my things.
When I put my phone
on the terminal,
my Walgreen's loyalty
information is transmitted
contactlessly, along with
my Apple Pay information,
all in one tap.
That's it!
I give a friendly
smile and a thank you
to the clerk and
I'm out the door.
That is great!
That makes the process
a lot more smooth.
So how do we do this?
How do we add this
feature into your passes?
We have a new key.
It's pass.json.
It's nfc. Nfc is a a
dictionary that takes a message.
Just kind of like a bar code,
this is the loyalty information
or anything that
links this user,
this identity to your system.
We have an optional
encryptionPublicKey.
And this guarantees
authenticity,
this is something
handshake yourself
between merchant
and your terminal.
So this is how you
implement passes that work
with Apple Pay on your passes.
And now if you are a
merchant or a terminal maker
and you are interested by
this, please come see us.
Our developer relations
team will be here this week
and you can contact them.
I will give you the contact
information after this talk.
And let them know
you are interested
and we will get you started with
passes that work with Apple Pay.
Speaking of Apple Pay,
Apple Pay has been great,
like I mentioned before.
We have now enabled contactless
payment on our phones,
on our watches, and even
we have enabled APIs
so you can take Apple
Pay inside your apps.
And Apple Pay is great because
there's a seamless payment
experience for your users.
And merchants are seeing
higher conversion rates
across the board so we
want to encourage our users
to add Apple Pay cards
into their devices.
How do we do that?
We are giving you a couple
of APIs to enable this.
There's two.
The first one will take your
users directly to our Wallet app
and start setup from there.
And a second one,
that allows you to set
up these cards from
within your app.
Let's take a look
at that first one.
It's in PKPassLibrary
and it's very simple.
We call openPaymentSetup.
And that will take your
user directly into Wallet,
and start the setup flow.
And now with our new
features in iOS 9,
your users can go really
easily back into your app
and we leave a little bread
crumb for them to tap on
and go back into your
app and do continue
to do whatever they were doing.
Hopefully shopping.
And if you are a bank or if you
are a merchant with a store card
or a private label card,
you want to have this
happen inside your own app,
we have an API for that as well.
It's actually a view controller,
it's
PKAddPaymentPassViewController.
And of course we need to check
whether this particular device
can add a payment pass or not.
When we find out it can, we set
one of these up, we can knit it
with a requestConfiguration
and we pass into it a delegate.
Now this delegate that you
implement inside your app,
will form together using
those pieces of information,
like the nonceSignature, will
form up a AddPaymentPassRequest.
We can really dig into
this for a long time.
I really don't have time
in this particular session
to dig into this.
So please refer to
your documentation
if you have any questions
about how to use this class.
And this class will be entitled.
So please let us know
as well if you want
to use this inside your app.
Another necessary step that
our users might need to take
when they are adding a payment
pass inside Apple Pay is a
payment pass verification
or second factor auth
as some people know it.
And along with the typical flow,
like using SMS or a phone call
or email, another option
we offer is using an app.
We see here Capital
One using their app
to verify their user's identity.
How do we do this?
Well, we give you guys a
couple of APIs to be able
to allow this inside
of your apps.
It's also in PKPassLibrary.
You check first, is
there a payment pass
activation available?
Remember when we
were pulling PKPasses
out of the user's library?
Well this is where it's useful.
You can pass into this call,
that PKPaymentPass and pass
into it some activation data
and you'll get a
completion back whether
that activation was
successful or not.
That's how you can implement
verification inside your apps.
So our phones have been
really, really popular
and there's awesome and really,
really great accessories
out there.
Some of them emit a field and
we want to be good players
with those accessories.
We are announcing with iOS 9,
a contactless interface
suppression API.
What this will do is temporarily
disable the user interface.
It's the sheet of
passes that you see
and this will require
a user's permission.
Let's take a look
at how we do this.
It's in that PKPassLibrary
again.
PKPassLibrary has a
new function called
requestAutomaticPassPresentation
SuppressionWithResponseHandler.
It's a mouthful!
And what you will get
back is a response result
of what the user
decides, whether
or not they will allow
suppression inside your app.
You also get back
a request token.
Then you can use that request
token for this next call
to endAutomaticPassPresentation.
Pass into it, that requestToken,
and the payment UI will
appear again inside your app.
You can also check whether
automaticPassPresentation
Suppression is already occurring
by using this function
right here.
As I mentioned before,
it is temporary.
So if your app is suspended,
the payment pass UI will
appear again for the user
or if it's been 24 hours
after your last requests,
you will need to re-request
your user's permission again.
These classes and these
calls are entitled.
So please let us know if
you would like to use them.
Along with Apple Pay, last fall
we also introduced Apple Watch.
And now I'm really happy to
announce that in watchOS 2,
we are bringing full PassKit
support to Apple Watch.
And this is really great because
now on Apple Watch, you can add,
you can remove, you can query
passes just like up doing
on our phones previously.
So full PassKit support
is coming to Apple Watch
and watchOS 2, there's
another thing I want to talk
about in regards to Apple Watch
and that's the screen size.
Working with a lot smaller real
estate space on Apple Watch,
and I want to point this out,
because passes are drawn
a little differently
on Apple Watch.
This is a pretty cool graphic.
This is what a pass rendered
on Apple Watch looks like.
As you can see this
is our MLB pass
from a couple of slides back.
And you will notice right away
it looks a little different.
That strip image
is no longer there.
And, in fact, we don't even
have a back of the pass.
So take a look and remember,
passes do look different
on different devices,
especially on Apple Watch.
So consider that when you
are designing your passes
and implementing them.
But, of course, if you
follow the HI guidelines,
we will promise and do our best
to make your passes look great
on every single one
of our devices.
So that's PassKit
and Apple Watch.
There's one more thing
I do want to talk about.
And that's 1D bar codes.
We have been getting a lot
of requests for 1D barcodes
and I'm really glad
to say that iOS 9,
we are bringing 1D
Barcode support to Wallet.
Yeah.
[ Applause ]
I'm glad you are glad.
So we have a new barcode format.
It's PKBarcodeFormatCode128.
You may ask what about my users
that are who are still on iOS 8
and below, are they
going to get this?
Well, no. That's why you
will have this fallback.
We still have that barcode key.
That barcode key is
very, very important
but we have here is
implementing that 2D barcode.
We have a new barcodes, plural,
key that is an array that takes
in a dictionary of barcodes.
So, as you can see, we have a
new barcodes array here that has
in the first dictionary,
a barcode with
PKBarcodeFormatCode128.
And that's the 1D barcode.
So please, please, as you
are implementing this,
do me a favor, please verify
your system supports 1D barcodes
and what I really mean
is optical scanners.
And please remember to
fall back to 2D barcodes
so that your users on iOS 8
and below have a
barcode on their passes.
All right.
I have done a lot of
talking this morning.
If I had to say that you
should remember something
from this session, it's
these things: We're solving
that overstuffed wallet problem.
We don't want that
wallet anymore.
We don't want to see
that wallet anymore.
We do that with passes.
Passes allow us to take
action in the real world.
They are really easy
to integrate
into your apps, into your flow.
And passes when they are
engaging really keep your users
interactive and interested
in your systems.
And I want to remind you
to integrate Apple
Pay into your apps.
Encourage your users to use
Apple Pay into their apps.
Remember you want that smooth
and seamless checkout flow
and we also want the
higher conversion rates
for our merchants.
I didn't even talk about
integrating Apple Pay
as a payment inside apps at all.
This session cannot
contain that awesomeness.
We have our own session
immediately following this one,
give by my colleagues Nick
and Rachel, and it's going
to be really, really amazing.
They will solve that
abandoned cart issue.
They're going to help integrate
Apple Pay into your apps.
Remember, please use
Wallet and use Apple Pay.
Go out there and redeem coupons.
Go out there and spend money!
I mentioned a lot of resources
during this talk and I want
to point a couple
of them out to you.
First, we have Passbook for
Developers specific site
on our developer website.
We also have one specific
to Apple Pay as well.
And I mentioned a couple of
talks from previous WWDCs.
Here's one from 2012,
it's called "Introducing
Passbook Part 1 & 2" that's
really going to go in
depth into designing passes
and updating passes as well.
And then "Integrating Passbook
Into Your Ecosystem"
which is WWDC 2013.
These are really great resources
for you guys to check out.
And of course we have
our developer forum
that you guys can
utilize as well.
And a really awesome evangelist
Paul can also help you guys
out here, here's
his email address.
So again, thank you for your
time, thank you for coming
and listening about
Wallet and Apple Pay.
I hope you go out there have
a really, really great week.
Thanks a lot.
[Applause]