[Applause]
>> OLIVIER BONNET: Good
afternoon and welcome
to Session 704 What's
New in CloudKit.
My name is Olivier.
I'm the Engineering Manager
for the iCloud Client teams.
So a year ago we introduced
CloudKits a brand new framework
for you as developers to
harness of the power of iCloud.
We built a number of
the iOS 8 new features
on top of CloudKits.
Most visibly iCloud Drive and
iCloud Photo Library were built
from the ground up on top of
CloudKit but Mail Drop, HomeKit,
Safari history syncing, and
call history syncing were also
using CloudKit.
So a year later,
what have we seen?
We have uploaded over
240 billion records.
We saved over 250 petabytes
of assets and that's coming
from over 300 million users.
So really, we couldn't
be happier
with how this has turned
out, with how reliable
and stable CloudKit
has been for us.
So this year, we're going to add
a couple more features to that.
Notes is now using
CloudKit on iOS,
and OS X to synchronize your
notes between your devices.
The new app we introduces
yesterday,
News is entirely built on
the CloudKit public database.
Even the WWDC app is now
using CloudKit this year.
And last but not
least iCloud Backup,
was ported in iOS
9 to use CloudKit.
So this is actually -- this
one is actually a bigger deal
than it seems because iCloud
Backup is our biggest service
in terms of number of users,
amount of data, and the number
of requests per seconds.
We've also heard some good
feedback from you as developers.
For instance, from Hipstamatic,
"With CloudKit, we were able
to focus on building our app,
and even squeeze
in a few extras."
So that is exactly
why we built CloudKit.
To enable you as developers to
focus on building great apps,
building awesome user
experience, without having
to set up a server, without
having to operate it,
without having to
be on call 24/7.
AgileBits is using CloudKit to
synchronize one password data.
They're happy with it.
Here's what they're saying:
"CloudKit is very fast,
efficient, and makes it easy to
detect and troubleshoot errors."
Again, that was one of our
design goals with CloudKit.
If there's an error in the
daemon, on the network,
or on the server side, we will
return that error to your app
and your app is in
charge of handling it,
retrying it, if it makes sense.
Last but not least, IconFactory:
"One of the best parts
about CloudKit is there's no
complicated sign-in process
or setup."
Again that was one of out goals.
Make it possible to enable
completely seamless user
experience, no account creation,
no password to enter
or remember.
In addition to this
good feedback,
we also heard some questions
from you as developers.
So last year, we
introduced CloudKit.
We said it was free with limits.
And so we get some questions
like, okay, what does it mean?
What if my app reached
the limits?
How much will I have
to pay Apple?
Second question we got
immediately last year is like,
okay, but what about the web?
What if I have a web app
and I wanted to be able
to access the same data as
my iOS and OS X CloudKit app.
To talk about both of those,
I would like to hand
it over to Eric.
Eric is the manager for
the iCloud Server team.
[Applause].
>> ERIC KRUGLER: Thank you.
Well, thank you, Olivier.
It's terrific to be here
this afternoon to talk to you
about what's new in CloudKit.
Let's start by answering
that first question.
What does it cost?
We are going to look at CloudKit
usage and pricing but to get
into that, we first need
to understand the
CloudKit architecture.
So when you use CloudKit,
all of your data is stored
in your CloudKit container.
This is the place where
all of your data resides
and you can store that
data, in two different ways.
One is as a private database
and two is as a public database.
Now a private database is
the user's private data.
This example would be
the iCloud Photo Library.
All the photos that you
take are stored in CloudKit
and accessible by the user
and managed by the user,
and because it's the
user's private data it comes
out of the user's storage
quota, not the developer's.
Now when we look at
the public database,
this is application's
public data.
A great example of this
is the new News app
that we just announced
yesterday,
where all of those news articles
are actually distributed
to all the news applications
via CloudKit public database
and because it's the
application's public data this
comes out of the
developer's storage quota.
So when we talk about pricing
and we talk about usage,
we are really talking about
public database usage.
So let's see what that means.
For our public database
offering,
we have a free offering.
We also have a fee structure if
you exceed those free limits.
And we also have usage data.
Let's look at the free offering.
So you have to store assets in
the cloud, and we track that
and we give you ten
gigabytes to start.
So if you have no users, you
are just starting development,
10 gigs.
Now as your user
population grows,
as your application becomes more
popular, we are going to grow
with you and we are going to
add an additional 250 megs
for every single user that is
using your application for free
and we will grow that up
to an astonishing 1
petabyte of storage.
Likewise, for the database side,
where you store your record
data, we will start you
with 100 megs and we will
grow that at 2.5 megs per user
and we will go up to
10 terabytes for free.
Now in addition to storage,
we also have data transfer.
So as you're uploading
and downloading your assets
you are consuming bandwidth
and we will start
you with 2 gigabytes
of data transfer per
month in and out.
And like the others we will grow
that as you have more users.
So we will add an extra 50
megs per user per month.
And we will allow you to
grow up to 200 terabytes
of data transfer per
month all for free.
Now for database, it's
a little different.
We actually measure it on
a request per second basis.
So we are going to start you
at 40 requests per second,
which is very large.
And just like the
others, we will grow
with the number of users.
And we will do that
in increments
of 10 requests per second
for each 100,000 users
up to 400 requests per second
for free, and what's important
to note about the
request per second is
that it's actually
a throttle limit.
So if for some reason your
application hits these limits,
we will actually send you
back a throttling error back
to your client to tell
you you've hit the limits.
And then we will talk
in a bit about how
to make sure that
doesn't happen.
All right.
Now, if you do go
over those limits,
there is a way to pay for more.
And that's our public
database fees.
Now, this is over and above
what we give you for free.
So it's the incremental delta
between what you get for free,
and what you are using.
So for assets, it's $0.03
per gigabyte per month,
for database, $3.00
per gig per month.
On the transfer side,
for transferring
assets $0.10 per gig
and on the database
request rates,
we'll add an extra 10
requests per second for $100,
and so you can increment that
number up to get to the level
that allows your
application to work smoothly
if you hit the free limits.
And, of course, push is free.
Okay? So now let's
take a look at a demo
of the CloudKit calculator.
This is on
developer.apple.com/cloudkit.
You can play around with
this if you haven't already.
I'm going to invite
Ramiro Calvo to help drive,
because apparently I can drive
and talk at the same time.
And he's going to help
us walk through this.
If you go to the calculator,
you notice that right now,
we have zero active users.
Okay? And the numbers that you
see beneath it tell you how much
storage we are getting
to you for free.
For start, this matches
what we just talked about.
There's 10 gigs of
asset storage,
100 megs of database storage, 2
gigs of data transfer per month,
and 40 requests per second.
Now let's say my
application starts taking off
and I have 100,000 users.
So we're going to
grow that to 100,000,
and you will notice we gave
you a lot more storage,
and if you look below
at the bottom there,
and Ramiro maybe you can scroll
up a little bit, you're going
to notice that the
cost is actually $0.
Ramiro is it possible to
scroll it up a little bit.
Thank you.
Okay? So we have $0 cost.
Now let's say we go up
to half a million users.
Okay? Now, once again we
have a lot of storage.
Now we are up to 125 terabytes.
We're still growing and the
cost to you is still zero.
Let's take it to
a million users.
Okay? So now we got a
lot of users in here.
We got a lot of storage.
We are up to 250
terabytes of data.
Lots of requests per second.
It's still free.
Let's take it to
4 million users.
Okay. So now we are at 4
million users and you are going
to see some very
large numbers here.
We are up to the petabyte
of storage, 10 terabytes
of database storage,
200 terabytes per month
of data transfer,
this is a lot of data,
and all of this still
costs you nothing.
Now if you recall from
the pricing slide,
at some point, we hit a limit.
And that limit looks
about right here.
You got about a petabyte
of storage.
That's what we said was
the max you can get to.
So, as we add more users then
there must be some costs.
Let's take it to
5 million users.
And the cost here is --
well, it's still free.
So what's going on here?
Well, if your application on
average uses less per user
that we give you, it
still costs you nothing.
And because it's an average,
that means that some users
may use more than the average,
and some may use less and
that's perfectly fine.
It still costs you nothing.
So we could take this all the
way up to 10 million here,
and demonstrate that it still
costs you nothing, all right?
If you just architect your
application correctly to stay
within the free limits
that we give you.
All right?
So that's how we calculate
things, use the calculator
if you would like
more information.
Thanks Ramiro.
[Applause]
All right.
The next question is how do
I know how much I'm using?
The CloudKit Dashboard
is the place
where we put this information.
The Dashboard is a web
application that you get
to at developer.apple.com.
It's a place that you get
to look at your container
and you get to do things like
manage your record types,
manage whether they are in
development or production,
and we have added some
new functionality.
So if you take a look
at what we've added,
there's a new section
called Usage.
And you can go there
and take a look
at how your application
container is performing.
If we drill in, we have a couple
of different ways
to look at the data.
We can look at it at a daily
level or a monthly level.
And if you look at the daily
information, the very top thing
on the graphs is
the number of users
and this is really important
because we calculate how
much free stuff we give you,
based on the numbers you have.
So you want to look
at that first.
Now, you'll also
notice on the right,
you have some dashed
lines over this
because what we are giving you
is two months worth of data,
the prior month and
the current month.
The current month,
depending on where you are at,
some of that is going
to be a forecast.
And we're going to
forecast that for you based
on the prior activity
of your container.
Now, below this,
is another graph,
which shows our requests
per second and day by day,
we show you what the peak
request per second we're seeing
on any given day is.
Now you can also select monthly
and if you choose monthly,
you're going to get a
12-month view month by month
of the activity of
your application,
and the current month
is typically going to be
in a forecast where
it shows a dashed line
and basically what we
expect it's going to be
for the current month.
Now, let's scroll down to look
at a couple of other graphs.
Here's database storage,
as well as asset storage.
And you'll notice
something different here.
You will see two lines.
There's a red line on top
and a yellow line just below.
The red line represents
the amount of free storage
that we are giving you.
And the yellow line represents
how much you are actually using.
So the game all of you
guys get to play is how
to keep the yellow line
beneath the red line, right?
The way that you can actually
see this information is
by clicking over here on
the section on the right
where the quota box is.
It's off by default.
You can just turn
it on if you like.
The reason it is off by
default is because we give you
so much free storage, if you
click that, the scale changes
and basically your usage looks
like a flat line relative
to the amount of free
storage that we give you.
So please go ahead
and try that out.
So the CloudKit Dashboard
provides two things.
It's a new section to
keep track of usage data
and also give you
the free limits.
And it's available now in beta
release at developer.apple.com.
So if you already
have a container,
you can go there today and
you can see the usage data
on the Dashboard.
All right.
The second question that
was asked is what about web?
Well, I'm pleased
to introduce you
to the new CloudKit
Web Services.
This is the way --
[Applause].
Yeah, all right!
This is the way that you
can take your amazing iOS
and OS X applications and you
can extend them to the web.
So how does this work?
Well, first lets talk
about the features.
You get a full CloudKit
API via JSON and HTTPS,
we also provide CloudKit
JS Library
which is absolutely the best way
to quickly create
web applications,
and we provide Web Sign in
with Apple ID is the way
that your users will
authenticate
when they use your web app.
Now, how does this work?
If you look today, you'll
see your application running
on iOS and OS X.
It interacts with
CloudKit the framework,
which behind the scenes talks
to our CloudKit servers.
What we have introduced
today is the ability for you
to create your own
web application,
running in a web browser and
talking over JSON and HTTPS,
to our CloudKit Web Services
which lets you then talk
to the same exact
CloudKit servers
that your native applications
are talking to on iOS and OS X.
Now, it's important to
understand about the JSON
and the HTTPS piece of this,
it's just a specification.
There's no code.
Effectively, it's up to
you as a developer to look
at that specification.
You get to construct your own
end points, hitting endpoints.
You get to create your URLs and
construct your JSONs that goes
in the bodies that go up in
a request, you get back JSON
in responses, you parse that,
you deal with asset uploads
and downloads, retry
logic and on and on.
But a much better way to do
this is using the CloudKit
JS framework.
CloudKit JS gives you a
JavaScript API that you can use
that shields you from all
the complexities of the HTTPS
and JSON protocol
that sits behind it.
And you can use either one,
but you are probably crazy
if you go the other route.
So please use CloudKit JS.
So what does this give you?
Well all right, it
gives you full public
and private database access.
It gives you all those
record applications.
It lets you upload
and download assets.
It lets you execute queries.
It even lets you do
subscriptions and notifications,
which means that I can actually
get an asynchronous event
into my web application,
just like you get pushes
to tell you something has
changed or to notify you
of some other event,
so you don't have
to have users hitting the
refresh button or pulling
from your web application.
It also has user
discoverability,
and it has the ability to answer
the question what's changed
since within custom zones
which gives you sync semantics.
In short, what this gives
you is full compatibility
and capability as what you get
on the native CloudKit
on iOS and OS X.
Now, CloudKit JS, as I mentioned
before is the absolute best way
to develop web applications.
It's a JavaScript API.
It matches the native
CloudKit API as much
as you can make JavaScript
match Objective-C,
but you know we did our
best, it's pretty close.
There's no intermediate servers.
So you can create your
JavaScript application
and you can talk directly
to the CloudKit, you know --
the CloudKit Web Service behind
the scenes and you don't have
to run your own servers
or anything in the middle
and it's how we built
the new Notes web app
that you saw demonstrated
the other day.
And what I would like to do is
have Ramiro Calvo join me again.
We're going to give you a demo
of the new Notes web app
based on CloudKit JS.
All right.
So we are going to
start at icloud.com.
This is our spring board.
There's a bunch of web
apps sitting here already.
You'll notice some familiar ones
we have Photos and iCloud Drive.
Those are two applications
that already exist
on top of CloudKit.
And with iOS 9, the new Notes
application is also built
on CloudKit.
And so we've created a new web
application that sits on top
of CloudKit, and
gives all of those --
that rich capability that you
saw demonstrated at the keynote.
So Ramiro will click in.
Here's the web app.
You're going to see some
great content in here.
You see images.
You can do videos.
There's check boxes.
All of these things are
available in the new Notes app
and they are just CloudKit
assets and records.
Okay? So what we are going to do
now is create a brand new node.
And since we are at the
developers conference,
we should probably
have a what to do
at the developers
conference while we are here.
So let's start out
with maybe one
of the more important
things, which is we need
to make sure we attend
all the after parties.
Let's get that one on the list.
Now after we get done with
attending the after parties,
we really need to go to
developer.apple.com/cloudkit
and take a look at all
the amazing documentation,
including this amazing
presentation,
where you are going to be
able to find information,
documentation and everything
about CloudKit itself as well
as the new CloudKit
Web Services.
Once we get through that,
we should really go off
and create our first
CloudKit web application.
And once we create that, well,
we should basically move on
and do our best to try
to hit those free limits
and that might actually
take a while.
So I don't think we
will check that one off.
But I have attended
at least one party.
So I think we can check
that first one off, Ramiro.
And complete this
web experience.
Now, let's go over to
iOS, which is an iPad,
running the new Notes
application.
We will open this up.
And you will see that same
kitchen remodel project
as we saw before.
And here's our new things to
do at WWDC that we just typed.
It showed up automatically.
It's the same data, right?
It's just that we have
a web interface to it,
where you can have your
native iOS interface to it.
Now, we will make a few
more changes in here.
I have already gone to
developer.apple.com.
Ramiro you have clearly
developed an amazing CloudKit
web app with the Notes app
and why don't we now go back
and take a look at the web
and see what happens,
you know, over there.
Now, if all things happen,
you will notice everything
got checked.
That was, again,
that notification
experience I talked about.
The notification, push
notification happened.
The web application
picked that up,
and automatically updated itself
and showed you the changes.
And that's the new Notes
web app that's available
on iOS 9 and icloud.com.
Thanks Ramiro.
[Applause]
>> ERIC KRUGLER: Now,
if your users are going
to use the application,
they have to sign in.
And so we are going to jump
right in to taking a look
at what that might look like
in your web application.
So, first, you need
some sort of a button
to ask the user to sign in.
This is your UI.
Now when the user clicks this,
a new browser window is going
to pop up and this
browser window is owned
and managed by Apple.
And this is because the ID
and password is only exchanged
between the user and Apple.
The developer never sees this.
And there's a few other
things that show up further
down on the login page.
So first, there's
"Keep me signed in."
So the user can opt in to
say I want to stay signed
in for up to two weeks.
There's a "Forgot
Apple ID or password?"
So if the user has
forgotten their ID,
we'll manage the whole
flow of helping them
to remember their
password or reset it.
And finally, if the user
is brand new to, you know,
the Apple ecosystem, they
don't have an Apple ID at all,
they can create an Apple
ID right here in the flow
and they will get
an Apple account
that they can then
use immediately
with your application.
So the CloudKit Web Service
offering includes iCloud
web-only accounts what I just
described, which offers 1 gig
of free storage for
private database usage.
And if that same user then
goes to iOS or OS X and sets
up their account there,
it automatically upgrades
to the 5 gig iCloud
account immediately.
Public database usage is the
same for iOS, OS X and web.
There's no difference,
so a request made
on the web is the
same as a request made
on your phone or on your Mac.
Storage is the same way.
So when you go to the storage
areas or the usage information
on the Dashboard,
there's no distinction.
It's all put together.
We do require a comparable
application for iOS or OS X.
The purpose of the Web Services
is to take your amazing iOS
and OS X applications and
extend them to the web.
And it's available now in beta
for development,
releasing with iOS 9.
And that's it for
CloudKit Web Services.
What I would like to do is
ask Olivier to come back
and close out the session.
Thank you very much.
[Applause].
>> OLIVIER BONNET: Thank
you very much, Eric.
So that's it.
We are very excited to see
what kind of application,
what kind of amazing
ideas you guys will build
on top of CloudKits.
As Eric mentioned, we have
new web page developer
at apple.com/cloudkit.
It aggregates all the data we
have and all the documentation,
the reference library, the
simple code we have on CloudKit,
both the new server, web APIs,
and the client framework.
In addition to the
usual technical support,
and forums, URLs.
If all of those fail, you
can email cloudkit@apple.com
for general inquiries.
We have two more
sessions this week.
The first one is tomorrow
and we will do a deep dive
on the CloudKit JS and
the Web Services API.
And then we have on Thursday
at 4:30, we have CloudKit Tips
and Tricks session, where
we'll do a best practices,
do's and don'ts and
as well a couple
of nice improvements we made
to the client's framework
in iOS 9, and OS X El Capitan.
We have a number of labs
during the rest of the week.
On Wednesday, Thursday,
and Friday at 9:00,
we'll have client engineers.
We will have server engineers.
I promise some of them
will even be awake at 9:00.
Please come and with your
questions, with your ideas.
We're happy to talk about
data mall, about what type
of apps you guys have in mind,
either using public
or private databases.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for your attention.
[Applause]