>> ABHINAV PATHAK: Hello.
Hello, everyone.
Good morning.
Hope you are having
a great WWDC so far.
I'm Abhinav Pathak, along with
my colleague, Pai-Han Huang,
we are going to talk about
debugging energy issues.
We are going to show you the
tools that we already have
and the new tools we built
this year specifically for iOS,
using which you can find energy
problems in your app and, two,
fix them so that your
customers really like your app.
Let's begin.
The red battery icon.
How much we all hate it
when it happens to us.
Customers also hate this.
Having a good battery
life is really important
to having an awesome
user experience.
Time and time again, it has
come up that battery life is one
of the most important
feature that people want.
At Apple, we take great strides
to ensure customers get a
good battery life experience.
However, the apps the
customer run have equal
or usually more say in
how the energy is drained
from their device.
To help our customers understand
which app is draining battery,
which app is heavy in terms of
energy, a couple of years ago
on OS X side, we had an activity
monitor monitor energy impact,
where you can see, for
each and every app,
what is the instantaneous
impact and what is the impact
for a period of time so
that users can get, hey,
what happened on their device?
On iOS 8, last year we
introduced battery usage UI,
a customer-facing UI, where they
can go and see in last 24 hours,
and last 7 days, what is the
proportion of energy breakdown
in different application
that is they have used.
An app coming at the top could
have very legitimate reasons,
hey, I love this app,
I use it all the time.
To help customers understand
what is the factor here,
this year we have included a
single toggle at the top of it
where they can toggle and
see how much usage there is,
how much screen time
the app got,
and how much it ran
in the background.
And then they can assess
hey, I used it more, or hey,
this app consumes
a lot of energy.
This talk is about if your
app is coming on the top
of this list, how you can get it
down while maintaining
the same utilization
or giving the same
utility to your user.
This talk is also about
people who usually come down,
how they can further come down
and get a good customer
experience.
To give a high-level overview,
we are going to quickly go
through energy fundamentals
and best practices.
We are going to summarize the
talk we had in the morning.
We are going to show you the
energy debugging workflow
and the tools we have
on how to debug energy.
We are going to have a demo
where we will fix energy
problems in a sample app
that we have built
specifically for this talk
and show you how easy
it is to go ahead
and fix energy problems, and
then we will close this talk.
Very simple.
Everybody knows this.
Energy 101.
Energy is equal to
power times time.
What we are seeing
here is a graph,
X-axis is time, Y-axis is power.
It's a waveform of
an application usage.
What happened?
Let's say a user launches an
app, a bunch of activities,
backgrounded the app, and
the app got suspended.
The single most important
point here is the entire area
under the graph is
the energy consumption
of this particular app.
Energy is dictated
by power and time,
and to illustrate
the point further,
if we take two rectangles here,
they are differing in terms
of how much power they
consume, differing in terms
of how much time they consume,
but they are equal energy wise.
Second concept, there's
something called fixed cost,
there's something
called dynamic cost.
A lot of hardware components
we have in our systems,
if you have to use them, we have
to first bring them into a state
where they can start
serving your requests.
These states are very high
energy consumption in terms
of -- compared to
-- the sleep states.
Once they are brought up, they
do the work that you asked it
to do, and then we keep them in
that state in anticipation of,
you know, further
work is going to come.
Once we see there's
no work coming up,
we quiet them down,
let them go to sleep.
Fixed cost can be
very, very expensive,
and we will see throughout
this talk how we will go
after this fixed cost
whenever it starts impacting
your application.
When it comes down to
reducing energy usage,
there are very simple three
rules that you need to follow.
First rule, do it never.
Does a customer really
need that work to be done?
If you don't do it, fixed
cost, dynamic cost, energy,
power time -- all the
things we have talked --
is a grand total of zero.
Awesome. If you need
to do it, do it less.
What is the least amount of work
to satisfy the customer's
request?
Next thing, do it
at a better time.
A customer is out in the
wild, taking photographs.
Do I need to upload it
to the server right now?
Have some tolerance, maybe
when a user is connected
to a power outlet.
Third, do it efficiently.
What is the best
efficient algorithm
or the best thing I can
do to serve this request?
We will see how these things
come back again and again
in different parts of the talk.
To jump in the energy debugging
workflow and tools we have,
let's look at how does an energy
debugging workflow look like?
It's very similar to normal
software engineering practices.
What you do: you
write code and build.
You run it on a very
simple debugger which tries
to show you what's the
high-level problems
in your code.
A lot of problems you
can easily identify,
fix, and you run it again.
Some of the problems, though,
are hard, so you go ahead
and say let me get a
focused debugger, you know?
Hey, I have a memory issue.
Let me get a focused tool only
on memory that can pinpoint
in my app exact line of the
code, where is the problem?
And once you are
done with all this,
you ship it to your customers
and your customers use it.
On OS X side, we have
Xcode, where we write
and build your application.
As part of general
debugger, within Xcode,
there are energy
debugging tools,
which we are going
to talk about.
These show primarily hints
of how your app is behaving.
As part of instruments,
we have focus tools.
Once you have identified, hey,
this part of the
system is a problem,
let me go ahead and fix this.
And customers, as we talked
about, they have energy impact,
and they can go ahead
and look at it.
Before we jump into the tools,
let's look at energy
debugging priorities on OS X.
The reason is the
tools are very focused
on energy debugging priority
because they point you
to exactly the location where
you need to fix your problem.
Priorities on OS X
are the CPU and GPU.
They have a very,
very high fixed cost.
To bring it to a state
where they can serve you
or your request in
the idle state,
it is ten times the power
consumption of as compared
to when they are
in the sleep state.
Once they are in the idle state,
if you use CPU for 1 percent,
that is 10 percent more on
top of idle power consumption.
And from then on,
it goes exponential.
10 percent CPU, two times idle;
100 percent CPU, 100 times idle.
Very simple rule here.
Do not wake the CPU up
if you do not need to.
Let the giant bear sleep.
Don't poke it.
The tool we have in Xcode,
I call it energy gauges,
it prints you an energy report
that looks something like this.
How do you get there?
You click -- once you are
running your application,
click on the debug
analysis part.
Once you click there, you
see a bunch of gauges.
Click on the energy
impact gauge.
You will see the report.
What do you see in the report?
So primarily, you'll see if you
are being a bad citizen of OS X,
basically, you have -- if
you are using high CPU.
If you are preventing your --
your application is in
background, user is not looking
at it, system will try to put
you in App Nap, which is a kind
of background suspend, and
you are preventing system
to do that.
You are not actively
serving any request,
but you are burning
a lot of energy.
Idle prevention.
You are not letting the CPU
to go to into idle state.
If it cannot go into idle, it
cannot go into sleep state.
Once gone into sleep state,
the CPU wake overhead says hey,
you are responsible
to bring this guy up.
Once you have figured
out high level
where the problem comes in,
what you can do is just
underneath the report,
you have first of
all the description
of the things we
just talked about,
but you have these buttons which
you can jump into instruments,
and these tools are
specifically designed for each
and every area, and they can,
you know, help you pinpoint,
hey, which line of code
is actually causing high
CPU utilization?
Which line of code is
causing the wake overhead?
You can go ahead
and debug your app.
When it comes to principles
of reducing energy on OS X,
we come back to our three simple
rules: do it never/do it less.
You want to coalesce
all the timers.
You don't want to wake up
the system again and again.
Minimize CPU wakes.
Do it at a better time.
Use the background
activity scheduler APIs,
where you can specify
a lot of parameters
and let the system choose
the right time for you.
Do it efficiently, set
the right work priorities,
QoS work priorities,
on your work queues.
Program a computer algorithm.
Moving on to iOS, CPU is still
a dominant energy consumption.
But given the fact that
these devices are different
than OS X devices, a few
other things come into play.
First of all, two of the
peripheries, location
and networking, can be
equally costly as CPU
if not more in some use cases.
Next, when an app runs
in the background,
your app consumes all
these three hardware
and it consumes a lot of energy.
You don't have the display
energy, but still all the rest
of components are huge in
terms of energy consumption.
So let's look at each
of these one by one.
Location energy usually
acts like this.
It's not very high in power.
The power is data mined by
which API you have called
and what is the precision
with which you are calling it.
The time component is big,
and that is how the
energy becomes really huge.
When it comes to fixing location
issues, again, same principles:
do it never, do continuous
location only
if you actually need it,
it has actually been
requested by the user.
And please stop once
you are done with it.
Once you get the location,
once your request is
satisfied, just stop it.
Next, do it efficiently.
What is the best
accuracy you need?
Do you need to know
exactly within three feet
where the user is standing on
earth or the city is good enough
in predicting weather for it?
What are you trying to do?
We have went ahead in the
location site and we said hey,
there are a set of use cases
where people want to have
and for each of the use
cases, we have designed APIs
that help serve better
the developers, you.
Try to read on these APIs
what actually you want
and we'll do the energy
management really nice for you.
When it comes to networking,
very similar principles:
do it never.
Cut down transfers.
Can you cache, can you compress?
Do you need the highest
quality media
on the smallest form factor?
Can you do it at a better time?
Can you consider tolerance?
When is it needed?
Can you mark it as
a discretionary?
The moment you mark
it discretionary,
the system takes over.
You can specify, hey,
in the next 6 hours
or the next 12 hours, I
need this to be uploaded
or downloaded, and
the system will figure
out what's the best time,
will do the activity for you,
and once it's done, it will tell
you hey, this activity is done.
Do it more efficiently.
Coalesce transfers.
Let's take a look at an example.
What do we mean by this?
Let's say you have a requirement
where you have to sync data
to a server, user is
using your app and have
to periodically sync as it's
being generated on the device.
Very simple solution.
As the data is getting generated
on the device, just
keep pushing it.
What happens here?
For every push, you bring the
data up, you send your 2 bytes,
10 bytes, 100 bytes, radio stays
on for a long time,
it goes to sleep.
Next push, the same is repeated.
The fixed cost is very
high in that point.
How do you fix it?
Very simple.
Coalesce all the transfers.
Let the user interact with
the device, build a state,
and once in a while send
the state to the cloud
so that you pay the cost only
once, the cost of fixed price.
Moving to background,
first thing,
background when your app is
running at the background,
it is draining energy
from the user.
Please don't do anything
in background
if you don't need to do it.
If you need to do it, call your
task completion handler as quick
as possible, and this task
completion handler is an
indication to the system
saying, hey, I am done.
Please suspend me.
Please let the device
go to sleep.
Do it efficiently.
There are a lot of background
APIs that you can, you know,
give your system a hand, you
know, please do the work for me
as you find the best time
and the best, you know,
period energy wise and the
system will do it for you.
To go back to the energy
debugging workflow on iOS,
what we have so far,
we have Xcode,
where you write and
build your code.
Customers have battery usage UI
where they can see how your
app is performing energy wise.
So far, we have had for a few
years a tool called Energy
Diagnostics in Instruments that
can give you a first-cut idea
of how your app is behaving.
Let's take a look at this tool.
How do you enable it?
You go to settings, developer,
go to the logging pane.
You turn on the energy
toggle here
and then you say,
hey, start recording.
Once you have started
recording, use your app
as your customer will.
Live on it for a
few hours, 12 hours,
24 hours, a few days or so.
And once you are done,
just click the button,
stop recording.
After this, connect your
device to a Mac and go
to the instrument, select
Energy Diagnostics, and say hey,
please import the log
data that you have.
Once you do that, you
will get a picture,
which is something like this.
You'll see Wi-Fi, Bluetooth,
and you'll see how long they
were on, when they were on,
when they were off, and so on.
You will see how many packets
were sent out of each interface,
what was the CPU activity.
At the top, you will see
an energy usage level,
which with is a number
out of 20.
If you are 20 out of 20,
believe me, it's a problem.
Very, very high energy
consumption.
You want to stay close to 1.
This tool is good if you
want to do long experiments.
But what it doesn't do is it
doesn't tell you why did the
hardware come up?
Did you request it?
Where did you request it?
It doesn't pinpoint, it's not
fine-grain to go to your code.
To fix this problem, this year
we are introducing energy gauges
on iOS and instruments,
a few instruments too,
which you can use to
pinpoint in your code
where the problem
is coming from.
To talk about all of
these, let's move to demo.
I call Pai-Han Huang, my
colleague, to talk all about it.
[ Applause ]
>> PAI-HAN HUANG: So, in
a demo, I will walk you
through the major features of
the new energy bugging tools,
demo the app, and show you
how we can use the new tools
to identify and improve the
energy efficiency of your app.
So as a developer, I like these
new tools because they are easy,
they are effective, so
at the end of the demo,
I hope you will join me in
including these new tools
as part of your project cycle.
There are two major
components in the demo.
One is the new tool set; the
other one is the demo app.
So let me start from introducing
you to the new tool set.
On the screen, what we are
seeing is the screenshot
of iOS energy gauge,
which is the entry point
to all the other new
energy debugging tools
for iOS this year.
So where is it?
It is actually inside
debug navigator of Xcode,
which you can find over here.
After you launch your
apps through Xcode,
you will be populated
automatically for you over here.
And when you click
it, it will bring you
to the right-hand
side of the screen.
And the iOS energy gauge can
visualize the energy impact
of your code, can visualize
the energy impact of your code,
both instantaneously and
in the average instance.
So the first is the
instantaneous energy impact
of your code, can be found
in the field meter,
which is over here.
There are three different
zones in this graph.
In the speedometer, the lowest
one, when the needle points
to a green zone, it
means the energy impact
of your code is actually
reasonable.
Congratulations.
You are a good citizen
of the iOS ecosystem.
But still, we suggest you to
take a look at these new tools
to see how you can make
your customers happier.
When the needle moves up,
it enters the yellow zone.
In the yellow zone, the energy
impact of your code is high,
so it's likely that if you
don't deal with it carefully,
your app will show up high
in the battery usage UI.
So please use the new
energy debugging tools
to see how you can improve the
energy efficiency of your code.
But if the needle keeps moving
up, you enter the red zone.
Red zone indicates
that the energy impact
of your code is very high.
It means that even with the
slight usage of your app,
users will significantly --
will experience significant
battery drop on your device.
So please use the new tools!
Please [laughter]!
Sorry, I apologize.
That's the evil in me
protesting to the people
who don't take battery
life seriously.
I promise you, I am a very nice
guy, so come to chat with me,
you know, in the last
session this afternoon.
Okay? Okay.
But speedometer can give you
an instantaneous energy impact
information overall of your app.
If you want to see more
breakdown, you should see here,
energy impact session.
So this graph will be
refreshed once every second.
If your app introduces any
workload to CPU, location,
or networking, you will
see a block showing
up on the top three rows in
the corresponding time slots.
And, as an earlier
talk it was mentioned,
your app can consume
significant power,
not just on the foreground,
but on the background as well.
So based on this observation,
we have the fourth
rule, background.
When your app stays in the
background and doesn't go away,
you will see the moving blocks
showing up on the fourth row.
On top of the graph, you will
see a series of color bars.
And they look like this.
Two colors.
Red color means that that is
overhead, energy used to bring
up the system resources like
the radio module to perform work
for your app, and it also
maps to an earlier talk,
the fixed cost of the hardware.
For the blue one, it represents
the energy which has been used
to service the workload
introduced by your app.
Besides instantaneous
information,
we also provide average
information.
For example, like this one, the
average overhead in percentile,
and this guy shows you
the average energy impact.
On the bottom, you will see
a series of explanations
about legend, CPU, location,
networking, and background.
And it also provides some tips
about how you can optimize them.
But please remember that
iOS energy gauge is designed
to show you quick the
high-level understanding
about your energy
impact of your code.
So if you want more detailed
information, more breakdown,
then check this button.
This button, after you click
it, it will trampoline you
to the corresponding instrument,
to give you breakdown energy
information for your app.
This is the iOS energy gauge.
Let me next briefly
introduce you to instruments.
Instruments, as many of
you already use them:
it looks very similar.
For example, the one you see
on the screen is the
location instrument.
How do we start?
We start from toggle this
button, record it, and stop it.
After you record it, you
will see the system activity
like this.
And you will see some reasons
about why you see
this kind of activity.
For example, here you will
see the location service
that is trying to
request for location.
And if you want more
information, more detail,
go here, extended detail.
Then you will bring up this
guy, which is the code stack.
So this is the introduction
to the instruments.
Next, let me briefly
talk about the demo app.
On the screen, you will see
a screenshot of our demo app,
which we call Energy Buddy.
So, as an iOS power
software engineer,
I am eager to know whether I
can improve my energy efficiency
everywhere, not just
on my phone,
but in my daily life as well.
Energy Buddy can suit
my needs pretty well.
I can use it to take a picture,
and it will extract
the usage information
from the picture I take for
energy meter, for example.
Then it will query the
location of my device,
get the weather information
based on my location,
correlate the weather
information with my usage,
showing up on the screen.
The structure is like this.
There is a centralized data
manager, and if I import a photo
from there, it will try
to get a reading from it.
And based on the location,
it will try to hit
a networking service
to get the weather information
based on my location.
And then data manager will
correlate this information,
showing up as a curve
on the screen.
So next, let's try
to give it a shot
and see how the new tools
can help us identify
and improve energy
efficiency of Energy Buddy.
So on the left-hand side of
the screen, you will see Xcode.
Right-hand side is the
screenshot of my testing device.
So let's start from
launching Energy Buddy
by opening the project files.
So what it's currently doing is,
after I hit the round button,
it will try to build a
binary file and transport it
into the device and
launch it for me.
So once it's launched,
we will see this.
It's here.
So let's go to debug
navigator over here.
Energy impact over
here...oh, there we go.
The first thing we want
to see is whether there's
any moving block over here
because currently I don't
do anything with the UI.
So it seems like
it's pretty clear
of those kind of moving blocks.
This is a good sign because
when the app is idle,
not too much should happen.
So this is good.
So let me try to import
a photo by clicking the
"Import Photo" button, select
a photo from my gallery.
It will try to extract
information,
and I will set the reading.
Okay. Oh, okay, I see lots
of activity coming up,
including CPU, networking,
and location.
But among them, I
immediately notice one thing.
That is location is always on.
Huh. It doesn't make sense.
Because Energy Buddy is not the
kind of app where you're trying
to track your exercise,
like running, right?
So why do I need to keep
monitoring the location
of my device?
It doesn't make sense.
So let's take a look to see what
the location instrument can tell
us and how we can
identify the line of code
to improve the situation.
So I will next click
the location instrument,
and I say restart.
Then you are trying to bring
up the instrument,
launch an app for me.
Okay. So let me redo
import photo again.
Set the reading.
There you go.
Okay. So on the screen,
you will see this.
This is the location activity.
It keeps going on and
on without stopping.
But where is it?
Where do we introduce this?
Take a look at this.
Go to extended detail and see.
Oh, okay, it's this part
-- request location.
That's how we request
for location service.
So let me stop this,
go back to Xcode,
and search for request location.
Okay. It's already here.
So what is the request
looking to do?
First of all, you
are trying to set
up the confirm view controller.
In this piece of code,
you are trying to set up,
create a location manager.
Then you are will call
start updating location.
So after this line, what will
happen is location service will
periodically push the
location update to us
through a callback,
which is over here.
So in the callback, let's take
a look -- what does it do?
First thing is you are
trying to see, okay,
if there is anything
updated here, if it's zero,
that's invalid, so we
just ignore it, return.
Then we will store it, we say,
whether location is
horizontal accuracy is actually
up to our standard,
up to our expectation.
If not, we return.
If so, then we are trying
to handle location inside
the confirm view controller.
And then you return.
And this callback routine will
be repeated again and again
and again, every time
when we receive a callback
from the location service.
Push doesn't look nice.
So what we should do?
The thing we should do
is we should stop it
when we have a value.
Like this line.
So we say when we get
a value updating --
location update,
we should stop it.
So let's take a look
and launch it again
and see what the energy
gauge can tell us.
What I expect to see is after
I receive the first time a
successful location update,
I should stop the location,
and location service should
not be on and on forever.
Let's wait for it
to be launched.
Hmmm.
Okay. Go to the iOS
energy gauge.
So let me try to
import a photo again.
Select a photo from a gallery.
Set a reading.
Okay. Location, one second,
two seconds, three seconds,
four seconds, and it's gone.
This is an immediate improvement
after just one line of code.
You can think about
the scenario over here.
So if the app has been
turned on for a long time,
imagine how much energy you
can save just by doing one line
of code, which is amazing.
So let's give more
try on Energy Buddy
to see what will happen next
time when we import another one.
Okay. I import another one.
And I see the location has
been up for four seconds,
but this time, I notice
the big thing here is
networking service.
This doesn't look nice.
The reason Energy Buddy wants
to hit the networking service
because it wants to get
the weather information.
But I just did a query
like two minutes ago,
so the weather shouldn't change
that much during the
past two minutes, right?
Even for an hour, I would say,
the weather may not
change that much.
So what is the purpose
if we want
to redo the networking although
we already have earlier request
that is two minutes ago?
So let's go directly to the code
and see how we can fix this.
So the place where
we actually request
for location is inside
the weather file.
And there's a function
called Fetch if Missing.
So let's take a look
what does it do.
In the first part, we were
trying to set some parameters
like date, URL based
on the query URL for --
based on the device location
and the current date --
and whether I have
done this kind
of query within today or not.
And you will store the source
ID for the location coordinate,
and you will set a constant
that is exactly the number
of seconds within the hour.
So the first if we are
try to go do is we say
if we have done the
query for today
and the data manager already
has the weather fetched
since the last time we queried,
that is like three minutes ago,
then we say we just return.
Next is if we don't do it today
and data manager already
has the weather fetched,
then we also return.
If none of these two
situations have been satisfied,
then we will try to set up a
task based on the location,
based on the date, and we will
try to download it over here.
So what's going wrong there?
The reason it's doing wrong
is actually inside this gauge
over here.
So I will add in another
situation like this,
to say if I have done this today
and the previous fetch is
actually within an hour,
then I will not do it again.
So let's launch it again and see
how we can see the improvement
inside energy gauge.
So what we expect
to see is this.
Because we've already done our
fetch, like five minutes ago,
we should not see any networking
every time when we are trying
to import a photo again
within the next hour.
Let's take a look whether
energy gauge will agree
with my theory here.
Okay. It's up.
So I am trying to
import a photo,
select a picture from a gallery.
Set the reading.
So I see the location.
It's been for four
seconds like before.
But magically, all the
networking is gone.
This is exactly what we expect.
So this is another good way
for the energy efficiency
of our Energy Buddy.
So besides the foreground,
Energy Buddy can also consume
significant battery even
on the background.
So let's take a look at what
the energy gauge can tell us
when Energy Buddy is
actually on the background.
We put Energy Buddy
in the background
by hitting the Home button.
So what we see is over here.
We see lots of, lots
of background activities
of Energy Buddy.
And that means that
whenever Energy Buddy is
on the background, the
device cannot go to sleep,
which will consume
significant power
because there is a fixed cost
to keep the device awake.
This doesn't make sense because
Energy Buddy doesn't need
to do anything on
the background.
So what's going wrong here?
Let us go to the callback
when we actually go
to the background.
Here is the code.
What does it do?
It does the following.
You are trying to set out
background task identifier,
and they will do one thing,
archive to data manager,
which will store all the
changes to data manager,
and they will say wait for
input, and we will code
in background task when
it is actually done.
Does it make sense?
No. Why not?
Because our app is always
on in the background, right?
So how come users
can actually interact
with Energy Buddies
through the UI?
So there has been no input at
all, and we are waiting for it.
This doesn't look nice.
So what we should do is
we shouldn't wait for it.
Instead, we should do
something like this.
After we archive the data to
data manager, we will call
in background task immediately
and invalidate the
background task identifier.
Again, let's launch
Energy Buddy again
and see what the energy
gauge can tell us.
What we expect is this.
After we just saw all the
changes in data manager,
it will directly
just quit itself
and release the control
to the assistant.
It will not stay
in the background all
the time like before.
Okay. Go to energy gauge.
Put the Energy Buddy
in the background.
So we are in the
background one second,
two seconds, and it's gone.
So this is another big win.
So keep in mind that, with
very simple fix like I just did
on the stage, you can see
significant improvements,
and Abhinav will introduce
you because we carry
on a couple hours or even a day
with significant
battery improvement.
So this concludes my demo, and
let me hand it back to Abhinav.
[ Applause ]
>> ABHINAV PATHAK:
Thank you, Pai-Han.
That was a great demo.
Back on the slides.
So let's conclude this talk.
Let's see what happened during
this demo, a quick summary.
We started with the Energy
Buddy, inefficient code.
We ran it as the user would use
it and let's see what happened.
Everything is lighted here.
Bad, bad, really bad,
the impact is very high,
and your app will come very
high in the battery UI.
How did we fix it?
We went to location, and we
said hey, location has started.
Then stop.
One line of change,
boom, location stops.
Let's see before and
after how does it look?
If you focus on location
timeline,
we see location is
on all the time.
Afterwards, location is on only
when it is actually required
whenever a photo is imported.
Let's go to networking.
What we did was we were getting
weather information all the time
whenever a new photo was
imported, and that is not good.
We wanted to cut
down the transfer,
and we put a very simple block.
Hey, if this is recently
called, don't do that.
We don't need the new
information again.
What impact did that
have on the energy gauge?
Two photos, again,
before and after.
And if you focus on
the networking part,
networking is highlighted
for a long time.
The red bars on the top are
highlighted all the time,
saying networking
hardware is up.
It's a huge amount of time
during the usage of the app.
At the bottom, we just
do networking once, boom,
after that, it's recently
called, it won't be done again.
What about the background
session?
When we went to background, we
stored our state into database
and said hey, let's
wait for the user input.
Not a good place to do.
User is in the going to do
any input at that point.
Very simple fix.
We say don't wait
for user input.
Just call the task
completion handler.
Tell the system hey,
I am done, suspend me,
let the system go to sleep.
How does energy gauge look
like before and after?
Let's focus on the
background line.
Background is up all
the time in the top.
At the bottom, the moment
we have done the archiving
to the database, the
background task is done.
We are suspended.
Awesome. Let's take a look at
overall code before and after.
Before, you see everything
lighted up.
If this is happening to
your app, this is a problem.
After is we are doing
the same utility,
we are giving the same utility
to the user, same experience,
but very, very little
amount of load
on the hardware in
terms of energy.
Probably the most important
slide, as we promised you
in the starting, if your
app is coming at the top,
please do the changes and you
will see your app actually going
at the bottom of the UI.
What we did, we took two
iPhone 6 fresh installs,
on one of them installed
inefficient code,
on the second installed the
code with all the fixes,
took both of them exact
same amount of work,
while running other applications
as well, same amount of load
in terms of all application,
in terms of Energy Buddy
and other applications.
What we found: the fixed code
consumed 50 percent less energy,
including display energy,
which is exactly the
same in both the apps.
Battery UI you see right
on the top, 28 percent.
And with optimized
code, it goes way down.
User is getting exactly
the same thing.
To summarize this talk, battery
life is really, really important
to have a good customer
experience.
Design your app with
three things in mind --
do it never/do it less,
do it more efficiently,
do it at a better time.
Be a very considerate
background application.
Please try out the
new debug tools.
We have our labs.
I will give details right now.
Check out the new
Energy Guide we have.
It contains all the
information we talked
about in this talk and more.
Bring your apps to
the Power Lab.
Some more information
about where you can
find the Energy Guides.
Technical support for this talk.
Finally, the related
sessions for these talks,
which are talking about
a few concepts we talked,
but in more detail.
Thank you, everyone, for coming.
[ Applause ]