[Applause]
>> ADAM DRISCOLL: So good
afternoon and welcome
to What's New In Core Location.
My name is Adam Driscoll,
and I'm an engineer
on the Core Location
frameworks team.
I'm glad to bring this
session to you today
because things are
getting more complicated.
As you know, we have Apple
Watch and iPhone now.
So we thought we would
focus on simplicity.
What can we do to simplify
the tasks for you guys,
and we think we have
good stuff for you today.
Some of you may be
completely new
to Core Location as a framework.
I thought I would start out
with an overview of what we do,
the full breadth of our API.
The users know, the people
who buy your apps know
about Core Location,
that they are in charge
of whether you can
use it or not.
You can't access their
location off the bet,
you have to ask permission
and we have the API
that lets you do that.
After that we have
the bread and butter,
which is location updates.
This is the portion of the
API you can use to get access
to where the user
is at that moment.
Starting in iOS 8 we introduced
the ability to do that indoors,
maybe in a large venue like
an airport or shopping mall.
Then we have APIs that
we collectively think
of as monitoring APIs.
These are APIs that allow you to
specify an interest in an event
that may happen and
then be launched even
if you are not running
in order to get that,
when that event does happen.
The first of these
is region monitoring.
This allows you to
specify a geographic region
or iBeacon based region and be
launched into the background
when the user enters
or exits that region.
We have visit monitoring, sort
of a complementary technology
that allows you to
specify that you would
like to be notified whenever
a user arrives or departs
from the place but
you don't have to know
in front what that place is.
It's reminders type things,
remind me to get milk when I get
to the store and
visiting monitoring is
for diary type things.
I want to know where I
went today and what I did.
We have we have other
APIs, location, geocoding,
I'm not going to
go into it today.
We have improved a number
of these regions of the API,
but I want to especially
call out indoor location.
Indoor location is
more accurate.
It's faster at detecting
floor changes.
Most importantly the
sample has been rewritten
to make it more straightforward,
use MapKit.
If you think that
that's relevant
for your users, check it out.
It's should be much
easier for you to use.
For the most part we will be
talking about the first two
of these points, authorization
and location updates.
Specifically, we've
got four parts today
and the first one is
background location.
This is the portion of our
API that you use to record
where the user has gone.
Maybe you have a run tracking
app and they want to have a map
of where they went, or a
navigational app and you want
to give them turn
by turn directions.
We have some new API for the
other cases of location use
where you just need to know
where they are right now.
You don't need to be able to
map but want to provide them
with the information about
where the nearest store is,
that kind of thing.
Then we're going to talk about
authorization, how that changed
in iOS 8 and how it applies
now in the Apple Watch era.
Finally we will dive into
detail on best practices
for Apple Watch, which
hopefully should be very useful
if you're getting started there.
Okay. Background
location updates.
Well, we decided
not to have any.
I was just kidding.
This is what the slide would
have looked like in iOS 2 or 3.
If you were a user then,
you remember having
to leave a phone on, unlocked,
in your pocket when you went
for a run if you wanted a map.
Starting in iOS 4 we
improved on this greatly,
with what we call
Background modes.
You still by default will be
running only in the foreground.
However now you can use this
handy capabilities tab in Xcode
that says that you
want to be kept alive
in the background
unsuspended in order
to receive location updates.
What it does, it sets a
value key in your info plist,
statically for the whole app.
The key is UI background modes.
What happens when
this has been done?
We will see a video in a second.
Before we do, let's just see,
let me list out what
to look for.
So it allows you when -- the
user is using your application
to start location updates.
Then let's say the
user gets bored.
Maybe they check out the mail
or their music, a little demo,
maybe they're going to stare
at the home screen for awhile,
but you will be able
to accessing location
during that time.
The user launches you
up and starts you again.
You can stop the session and
stop accessing their location
and thereby stop draining
their battery with the GPS.
So here is the video.
So user launches our app.
There's a button in the
middle there to indicate
that they would like us to
start recording, which we do.
The eye chart, notice that
the numbers are counting up,
what they get to.
The user is going to put
us in the background.
And you see at the top now there
is what we call the Blue Bar.
This indicates that our
sample app is still running.
It gives the user the ability
to tap on it to come back,
which is what they just did.
Notice that the numbers in
the eye chart got bigger,
not bigger in the
eye chart sense.
That indicates that we continue
to receive location updates.
That's just a count of
the ones we've received.
We continue to receive
them in the background.
The user asks us to stop,
we go back to square one.
App developers have
created a lot
of great experiences
off of this.
We are wondering if
there's something we can do
to improve it.
Is there room for
improvement here?
With the particular theme of
simplification, you'll notice
that once your application has
opted into this capability,
it has responsibility because
if you continue running
in the background, the user
may not know this is happening
and you could accidentally
use up either through a bug
or through a corner case in
your UI you could use up a lot
of battery without their intent.
We think of that as high stakes
and we want to lower those,
so that the consequence of a bug
or an unexpected
circumstance are lower.
Another thing that you have
to do right now that we would
like to improve is, you
have to be closely coupled
to the transitions that your app
goes through when it is entering
and exiting the foreground.
Once you opted in to begin
running and using user location
in the background, you have to
tell us you are not interested
to when you do go
to the background.
You only find out you are going
to the background
until after the fact.
That leads to this view that
we have in the video here
that you may have seen
in your app as well.
We modified the sample so
that it stops location updates
in the delegate callback
to indicate
that it went to the background.
The Blue Bar appears
briefly and then disappears.
That can be kind of
confusing to users.
You notice that the unifying
characteristic here is you
signed up for the
ability to check,
to access the user's location
in a continuous manner
in the background, but
that was done on a kind
of carte blanche basis for
your whole app forever.
In fact you only want to
do it at certain times,
only when the user is
actively using your app
in the background.
Starting in iOS 9 we have a new
API that helps you express that.
It's called allows
background location updates,
and it's a property you set
on your location manager.
If you have multiple location
managers, you have to set it
on each one when appropriate.
You can have it set differently
on different location managers.
What does it do?
Well, you set this
property to yes.
Then it kind of opts
you into this behavior
that you requested
in your info plist.
If you said you like the
capability in the background,
you set this to yes and
start the location updates,
you will be kept
running in the background
to receive those
location updates.
However if you set it
to no, you will not.
Okay. Crucial question then:
What is the default value?
How do we know when to set this?
The default value is no.
So I want to reiterate this.
The default value here is no.
If you have an application
that runs for purposes
of recording location
tracks in the background
or for navigational purposes,
you must make a change
when you adopt iOS 9.
You have to go into
the app and find
where the user is indicating
that they want you to do this,
really want you to record a
session in the background.
Set this property to yes on
the location manager there.
When they finish,
set it back to no.
Once you've done that, however,
you no longer have to worry
about transitions
to the foreground
and background in
an immediate case.
You don't have to rush to turn
off location updates when you go
to the background because you
are already configured either
to continue or not
continue as you go.
Okay. So must change
if you have an app
that uses background
location updates.
What is the compatibility story?
Will the apps in
the Store be broken?
No, we grandfathered in all the
apps in the Store, but you need
to make this change as soon
as you adopt iOS 9 SDK.
What if you want to
support users not
on the latest and greatest iOS?
Maybe they're still
running iOS 8.
You can do that in
the standard fashion,
set a minimum deployment target
on your app and check at runtime
with response to selector to see
if the location manager
you are running
against currently has
this property or not.
And that's what it looks
like in Objective-C,
the response to selector
in Swift.
We have a fancy new
pound available
in Swift in response to this.
If you are at runtime
with a location manager
that has knowledge of this
property, you can set it to yes.
Otherwise you can assume
it's already set to yes
and you don't have to set it.
Unfortunately, that means
you can't set it to no
for extra protection either.
Okay. Brief sidebar
because I know many of you
who are interested in
background location updates
of this kind also may
have audible cues.
Probably the go-to way to
communicate with the user
when they have their
phone in their arm band
or mounted on their dash.
Starting in iOS 9, the core
audio team introduced this new,
very long-named option.
What this can, you use
this option in order
to indicate you are
going to do spoken output
and the system can mix you with
other output that the user has,
so you are not garbled
but you do mix with music.
Check out What's
New In Core Audio.
It happened yesterday, if
this is appropriate for you.
Background location.
What about those times
when you don't need
to access the user's location
in a continuous fashion?
You are not building
a map for them.
You are trying to
provide them context
for where they are right now.
Starting in iOS 9 we've
introduced a new method
for that called request
location.
It basically automates the
process that you would have had
to do in the past to
accomplish this goal.
If you are experienced
with Core Location,
maybe you know the
drill already.
You start updating location.
You watch those locations
come into your delegate.
You'll notice that they come in
very quickly at first but not
with the best accuracy.
So you need to keep an
eye on the accuracy level.
Figure out when it's good
enough, when it is not going
to get better, pick the
right tradeoff on waiting
and getting converged
accuracy, and use that location,
and then you have to remember
to stop location
updates after that.
We are going to do that
automatically for you.
When you call request location,
we'll start automatically
getting location updates
but we will not give them
to your delegate callback.
We threshold them
internally according
to your desired accuracy
and then we will call
your delegate back once
with just the location you need.
It will apply our logic
to determine what
the best location is.
We'll automatically stop
location updates for you
at that time so you don't
have any risk of forgetting it
or having a bug there.
Okay. So.
[Applause]
I have a little visualization
of how this works
to explain what we are
doing behind the scenes.
You couldn't generate
this by using this API,
because remember we only give
you one delegate callback,
but to see what it looks like.
This ring represents the
desired accuracy that you set.
Think of it as a diameter.
The fixed accuracy that you want
should be tighter than that.
We are just going
to graph it on top
of this map here as
locations come in.
Now, you can see the center
of a location is represented
by a dark circle
that looks like maps.
The accuracy level
is represented
by a larger diameter translucent
circle we about to see.
See how that changes over time.
The first fix came in quickly
but not terribly accurate.
It gets better over time.
When it gets to a level that's
good enough, we will accept it.
This is the location it will
give to your delegate callback.
All right.
I mentioned this
is configurable,
what your desired accuracy is.
How do you set this?
Fortunately we already have a
property named desired accuracy
on location manager.
You may be familiar with it.
It is how you control what kind
of accuracies you're hoping
for from start updating
location.
It applies also for
request location.
Let's just dial that
down a little bit
and make it very
small, tight accuracy.
And maybe a little
bit too tight.
We'll rerun the simulation
and see what happens.
First fix, we can see
the convergence going on.
Sometimes you have
regressions in convergence.
Overall the trend will be
narrower until you reach kind
of a break-even point.
At that point, notice we
didn't actually meet the
accuracy criteria.
We got to a point where
we weren't getting better.
At this point we
return this location
to your delegate callback.
Now, that means that the
locations that you receive
after you set a desired accuracy
in your request location may
be either higher accuracy,
that's smaller value
for accuracy,
or they could be lower
depending on how we got them.
Maybe you got lucky
in the first case,
and maybe it's challenging
conditions in the second case.
They get delivered to your
location manager delegate
on this delegate callback,
location manager
updated locations.
Bear in mind that last
parameter is an array.
We only give you one location
so it will be the zero
element in the array.
If the user, on the other
hand, does whatever they do,
if you request location
in an environment
where we can't establish
the user's location,
maybe at the bottom of a
coal mine, we'll call back
on location manager did
fail with error instead.
So you're guaranteed as long
as you don't interrupt request
location, you will get one
or the other of these
two callbacks
so you can hang some
application logic off
of that if you want to.
And the error that you get
from the error callback is
KCL error location unknown.
Two other things to keep in
mind with request location.
The first is that it's
mutually exclusive
with start updating location.
Since we are using the
same delegate callback,
if you have a start updating
session already going, started
and didn't stop, then a
request location will be simply
be ignored.
On the other hand if you have
a request location outstanding
but we're still converging, we
haven't settled on a fix for you
yet and you call start
updating, that will take over
and the request will be canceled
and you'll start
getting regular updates
to the delegate callback.
Mutually exclusive.
You can have only
one at the time,
and start updating location
effectively takes precedence.
The other one is that you can
use stop updating location
in order to cancel a request.
We encourage you to do this
if the user navigates away
from the scope where you had
requested their location.
So you are no longer interested,
we can save some power.
Great. So that's the two APIs
that we have for you today.
The first two of
our overall points.
So now let's talk
about the topic
that probably you are
all very interested in,
you are here to see.
That's Apple Watch.
So Apple Watch, first thing
to know about any story
about Apple Watch is
that it is really a story
about Apple Watch and iPhone.
So these devices,
they are a pair.
They have a direct one to one
relationship with each other.
We are going to want to
make them cooperate in order
to get the best possible
user experience.
The other thing that sort
of mirrors this situation is
the way you deliver your apps
to users.
You can now write watchOS apps,
but the user doesn't get them
from a watchOS App Store,
but they get them packed
on with the iPhone from
the regular App Store.
When they do that, if they
configured the system to do this
or choose to, iOS will
ship that component
over to the Apple Watch.
The lesson to take from this
is that your watchOS component
and your iPhone component have
a close relationship as well.
From Core Location's
perspective they are one
and the same authorization
identity.
So if you have, whatever kind
of authorization you have,
whatever state you're
in, it applies to both.
Okay. So subtopics on this.
First one, authorization story.
There's some wrinkles.
We'll get into them.
The second one is cooperation.
Now that we have two devices,
two pieces of your app,
how do we get them to work
together and some best practices
to keep the complexity lower.
All right.
Let's do a quick recap
to make sure we're all
on the same ground
with authorization.
Users know they are in charge.
So you ask for permission to
access the user's location,
either by request when
in use authorization
or with request always
authorization.
When in use, always.
These are new terms in iOS 8.
What do they mean?
What, how does your
ability to use location vary
when you use these different
kinds of authorization?
Well, hopefully this table
will help answer that question.
So on iOS we will consider
an app which has requested
when in use authorization and
been granted it and an app
that requested always
authorization
and been granted it.
And so first the three points
you get for signing the test.
If you have either of these
kinds of authorization
and the user is tapping
on your app,
can you access their location?
The answer is yes.
No doubt you already know that.
So what about the slightly
more complicated case
where the user has
interacted with your app
and they've indicated they would
like you to track their run
or some other reason
they want you
to continue accessing their
location in the background
in a continuous fashion?
As you may know, you can
do this with both forms
of authorization as well.
However, the behavior you get in
this case is slightly different.
So the Blue Bar that
we noticed is reserved
for when in use apps.
The reason for that is an app
which is authorized for when
in use has an implicit
transactional model
with the user.
The user is expected to know
that you are accessing
their location.
They specifically want you to
do so, as in the case with a run
or navigational session.
We reflect that and also help
them in case they get distracted
and forget, remember
it's ongoing
by displaying the Blue Bar.
They can get back to
the app without scraping
around in the launcher
and find your app.
Okay. So what about the
slightly more complicated case?
Oh, that doesn't
apply to always apps
because there's no transaction.
There's no expectation.
If you ask for always
authorization,
then you are basically
asking for carte blanche
and the user doesn't
expect to know
when you are accessing location.
We won't give them
that breadcrumb.
Okay. Background in the case
that I've called
intermittent here.
This is when you're accessing
location from the background,
but it isn't in reaction to a
foreground started or otherwise
like known to the user case.
This is a background
app refresh launch
or a region monitoring launch.
Well, to access the
user's location
in this case you need
always authorization.
That's because they don't know.
That way they can't understand
what is going on intuitively
if they are expected
to consider you in use.
So you can't access the Swift
when in use authorization.
All right.
Brief reappearance of monitoring
API just for the purposes
of this extra row we have.
Little known fact is you can
access monitor API region
monitoring in both cases.
You can access it if you have
always authorization but also
in when in use in using
UI local notifications,
that includes a CL region
as a triggering event
and the user will be notified
whenever you enter or exit
that region and they can
decide whether to pass
that on to you or not.
They are in the loop
and implicitly aware
of what's going on.
How does this story
change for watchOS?
Keep in mind we're talking
about the watchOS component
of your app only, not
the complex of iPhone app
and Watch app, but what can
you do just on Apple Watch?
Can you access location
when the user is poking
at your Watch app?
Yes. But, extensive
background as well.
We only provide the request
location API on watchOS.
You can access single
locations from the user,
but you can't start a
background tracking session
and you can't do
a tracking session
in the foreground either.
Why is this?
Apple Watch is really
optimized around the quick look.
We don't want the user to sit
there and hold their arm up
and get tired looking at it
for a long period of time
as they walk around the block.
The request location API
is the most appropriate one
to use on Apple Watch.
That doesn't mean you that
can't start a background session
from Apple Watch, that the
user can't record the run using
exclusively interaction
with Apple Watch,
but we will use cooperation with
iPhone to do that, and we'll get
into how in a little bit.
Background intermittent.
There are not many cases where
your watch app will be able
to run in the background.
If you find yourself running
in the background
you can get access
to the user's location only if
you have always authorization.
Not in the most relevant
row in the most table --
in most cases for watchOS.
Monitor API is not available.
You can't -- we can't
launch your app
into the background
on Apple Watch.
There's no point in
having these APIs.
Okay. So I have been referring
to this concept of being in use.
Let's drill down on
that a little bit
and get more specific
about what it means.
So your app is considered in
use if it's in the foreground.
This applies to both
iPhone and Apple Watch.
If the user is actively
poking at it.
But since there is such limited
cases, no continuous updates
and there's no background
tracking, that's the only way
on Apple Watch to be
considered in use.
However, on iPhone you can
also be considered to be in use
if you have a Blue Bar,
which means you started a
session and it's ongoing.
So what is the unifying
characteristic here?
How do we extend that
to the Apple Watch case?
Both of these represent
types when you are visible
to the user, yes,
but more specifically
when the user is aware
that you're there, running
and doing something
on their behalf.
So if the user is just
using Apple Watch,
and Apple Watch sends a
message to iPhone in order
to do something on its
behalf, in that case
in use status will
be transferred
to the iPhone app even though
maybe it's in the user's pocket
and they are not using it.
They are using the
aggregate, the whole complex
and authorization is
handled on the complex level.
You need to send the message
using an API we'll get
into in a moment, in
order to accomplish this.
While you are handling
work from Apple Watch
on iPhone you will
be considered in use.
How do you get authorization
in the first place?
Well, you have to ask for it.
Those two APIs that I mentioned
earlier, request with when
in use authorization or
always authorization.
Can you do that from
iPhone, from Apple Watch?
From both, neither?
Neither would be kind of fun.
So, what does this
look like on iPhone?
Well, the user will
launch your app.
And then they'll do
something to indicate
that you need to
access location.
You'll realize you don't
have authorization yet.
You'll call request when
in use authorization.
You'll see that the dialog shows
at the top the request that's
being made to the user.
Then below that we have
your usage description key
which you can set in
your apps info plist
to explain what you're
going to use location for,
and we encourage you to do
a good job of explaining it
so users will understand why
they should grant you this
ability, understand
the tradeoff.
You can see in this
case that it's
for purposes of demonstration.
That sounds pretty appropriate.
Let's allow authorization
in this case.
And you can see immediately
that location updates start.
Okay. So let's send this to the
background after stopping it,
and summarize what we just saw.
When you request location
authorization, from iPhone,
iPhone shows a prompt
you are all used to.
But also note that Apple
Watch didn't show anything.
It was just along
for the ride there.
That's because when the user is
using their phone they are not
likely to be using their
Watch at the same time.
If they do use it, they
want to see the time
or the app that's there.
So we don't want to block it.
What about the direction then?
Can you ask for location
authorization from Apple Watch?
Yes, you can do this, too.
It has a slightly different
behavior so you'll want
to do this in certain
circumstances and not in others.
Let's see what happens
when we do this.
The user launches your app.
And then they navigate to
the part where you are going
to need location authorization
to fulfill their requirements.
Pretend we didn't just
receive it back there,
it's a fresh start.
You call request when
in use authorization.
The prompt appears on
iPhone and on Apple Watch.
There's an alert that
appears on Apple Watch.
The alert on Apple Watch
says go look at your iPhone,
you have a prompt
to deal with there.
But it has a dismiss button.
That lets the user
dismiss this alert.
It is not modal.
You should expect to
see users interacting
with the app while you have
an outstanding request,
which is unfamiliar to iOS.
It doesn't constitute an
answer to the prompt question.
The user hasn't given up
their ability to option
to make a decision here, they
just said get out of the way.
Still appropriate to demo
purposes, so the user will go
to their phone and authorize us.
It is set to reset quickly.
Looks like we didn't, but if you
look quickly you notice we got
a fix.
You can run it again and again
and see that you got one.
What did we see overall?
What is the story there?
Apple Watch initiated a
request on Apple Watch
and Apple Watch does an alert
so the user knows what is going
on so the user understands
that the workflow needs
to be interrupted to answer the
authorization before whatever
they were trying to
do can go through.
The iPhone shows a prompt as
you're used to and importantly,
the user has to answer
the prompt on iPhone.
All right.
This may seem a little
inconvenient,
so why did we do it?
There's two good
reasons for this.
The first one is, we
do really want you
to give a good explanation
for your use
in that usage description key.
If you did, that would mean
scrolling on Apple Watch.
It's not a great
user experience.
We would rather have the large
screen real estate that we have
on iPhone for this prompt.
We want to set user expectations
of where they can
control authorization.
Right now iPhone is
the root location
for controlling location
authorization
and privacy authorization
in general.
We want to have all the
interactions concentrated
on iPhone so the user
is not surprised.
They can go to settings,
privacy, location services later
on and change the settings
there if they want to.
All right.
I mentioned earlier that
request location is the API
that we are making
available in watchOS
to access users' interactions
directly from watchOS.
What kind of accuracy
can you expect?
If you are issuing the
request on Apple Watch,
it depends on whether you
have iPhone on hand or not.
If you do, you get everything,
even indoor location fixes
which are accurate down
to only a few meters.
On the other hand, if you don't,
then you can prototype this
and understand the
expectation here as the same
as if you had specified
a requested location,
requested desired accuracy of
KCL location of 100 meters.
This is not location accuracy
best, but bear in mind
that it will usually be
much better than 100 meters.
In fact, in ideal
environments you can even go
for a run with this.
There's no updates
so don't try that.
The other thing to know
here, it's best effort,
because Apple Watch isn't
connected to the rest
of the world very well.
It could be if it's
in a novel location
where it doesn't have a lot
of experience with the user,
it may be unable to
fix the user's location
in their context.
All right, that's the
best effort disclaimer,
but again it is a
really good effort.
When we have iPhone on hand
we make an aggressive effort
to use its facilities to learn
more about the environment
and cache a good
long distance out.
Probably for a user's run,
unless they are training
for a really long
run, you will be fine.
But just take this into
account when you are trying
to position your
use for your users,
whether they should expect to
bring iPhone with them or not.
If your app is used
around their home or work
or somewhere they
are familiar with,
probably they don't need to.
On the other hand if you are
expecting it to be used on trips
or where the user has
turned the data plan off
so they don't get
charged ridiculously,
you want to encourage them
to bring iPhone along anyway
even if their data is off.
But let's suppose we
have iPhone on hand.
Well, if you need
continuous location updates,
common case in the background,
or you need region monitoring
or for that matter if you need
anything else available on iOS
but prohibited on watchOS,
you want to use cooperation
with your iPhone to do that.
How do we do that?
There is a great session,
actually the last session
in this room today before
this one, before lunch.
Unfortunately it's in the past
but you can go see
it on the WWDC app.
If you were here before, great,
this is a little
bit of overview.
This is a portion
of the framework that's
particularly relevant
to location.
First class of interest
is WC session.
This is the class that
represents the connection
between Apple Watch and iPhone.
There's two methods
on it that are
of particular relevance to us.
The first is SendMessage
reply handler error handler
and the second is update
application context.
SendMessage reply handler
error handler is bidirectional,
you can send it from
either side,
update application context has
to be initiated from iPhone.
Let's take a look at how
these work in practice for us.
We are going to start by
communicating from the Watch app
to our iPhone app using
SendMessage reply handler
error handler.
The user navigates to
the part of the app
where we need help
from the other side.
And they ask us to start.
We send that message across and
you can see the app comes up.
And the Blue Bar came down
too in the video, too,
to indicate that it was able
to get continuous
background location session.
It can start sending
that information back.
And you can see the
updates coming
in on the watch display
if it's not too tiny.
We are going to stop
and put everything away.
And okay? Then we can
review what happened there.
So crucially, if you send
a message to the iPhone app
and it's not running, it
can be launched if necessary
by SendMessage from
Apple Watch to iPhone.
So you don't have to worry
about having the user
go start the app.
They can leave the
phone in their pocket
and everything can
take care of itself.
Of note, in use status
transferred.
I mentioned this before,
you just saw it in action
because the user is using the
Watch, they are using your app,
that means it is entitled
to start a background location
tracking continuous session
on iPhone.
That also means take
special account
of this allows background
location updates flag property.
You need to set this
to yes if you intend
to start a continuous
background location session
and set it to no if you don't.
When the user pulls their phone
out and happens to be looking
at it while they are using their
watch they won't see mysterious
Blue Bars dipping in and out.
What about the other direction?
So iPhone to Apple Watch.
Well, we can use SendMessage
reply handler error handler
because it's a bidirectional
API.
When we do that, you see we
have a bit of a problem here.
Our messages aren't
getting through.
In fact, what happens
in this case,
because the Watch app is not
running, we are just going
to get the error handler called
on our delegate each
time we do this.
SendMessage reply handler error
handler is launching in the case
of app to phone, and
it is not launching
in the case of phone to watch.
Maybe we should look into the
other API I mentioned earlier,
update application context.
This is phone to watch.
We can use this API.
And when we do, something
different happens.
So our Apple Watch app is still
not running, but the messages
that we send hang out.
In particular, the
last one hangs out.
You don't want to use
this method of facility
to send delta updates
but you do want
to send state updates,
full context updates.
When you do, the system
will hold on to it for you
until the user does update,
does launch your app.
Okay, at that time your
app launches and it gets
that update that's
waiting for it.
You can see if you
look carefully
that it already knew
it was started.
You can send continuing
periodic updates
across from your phone app
later on to update the UI.
That initial state
was already there.
That update application
context is appropriate to use
for subsequent communications
as well.
All right.
Then one thing to bring up
with regard to this whole path
from iPhone to Apple Watch is
also take a look at this API
that we introduced
in Core Location
in iOS 6 called allowed
deferred location updates
until traveled time out.
This API will, sort of a
natural complement to the system
because when the user is
not looking at Apple Watch,
you don't need to keep
it up to the second.
You need to keep it
somewhat up to date.
The best way to do that
is batch up the updates,
send them over every so often,
so you don't keep the user's
Bluetooth radio running all the
time and we can save some power.
On the iOS side, on the
phone you can use this API
on Core Location in
order to indicate
that right now you are running
in such a latency tolerant mode
and you don't need to be woken
up until the user has
gone a certain distance
or until a certain
amount of time has passed.
Maybe they went a mile,
this is their pace.
If you hit the timeout
based on distance,
it has been five minutes,
or you want to send an
update to your Apple Watch.
Okay, so that's it.
So we've got allows
background location updates.
This is a new property.
You have to take action on
this but it will free you
from a couple of hassles with
close coupling and high stakes.
After that we've got
request location.
This is a new method on C
location manager that allows you
to cut out some
of the boilerplate you probably
all have and get one location
when that's all you need.
The theme for using both of
these devices is cooperation.
And the great news, I'm happy
to say we've got a
sample called potluck
which demonstrates everything
we talked about today.
In fact, that's the app that
we demoed for these videos,
and you can install it
yourself and run it.
Hopefully if the app you're
working on isn't working,
potluck will and you
can converge and figure
out where the error might be.
Here is a bunch of information,
I'm sure you can all
scribble down quickly.
The top part is probably
the most important.
Check out potluck.
This link takes you
to the sample code.
Scroll down until you get to the
P section and there's potluck.
These are the sessions I thought
might be especially relevant
for you.
They are all in the past, but
they're all on tape as well.
You can go check them out later.
And especially Introducing
WatchKIt 2.0 at the top
and Introducing Watch
Connectivity, that's the API
that I was just talking
about at the bottom.
That's it.
I hope to see you all there.
I can't wait to see
what you can create
with the iOS 9 watchOS
2 and Core Location.
Keep up the good work.
[Applause and cheers]