[Applause]
&gt;&gt; JAMIE WOOD: Thank you.
Good morning, everyone.
Welcome to session 717.
My name is Jamie Wood
and I'm here today
with my colleague, Tommy Pauly.
We are Network Engineers in
the Core OS networking group
at Apple, and we are excited
to tell you about what is new
in Network Extension and VPN.
So you may be wondering what
is Network Extension Framework?
What capabilities does
it have to offer to me
for use in my application?
Network Extension Framework
provide APIs to use in your app
to customize and extend the
Core networking features
of Apple's platforms.
Let's look at specific
examples of kinds
of apps you can create using
the Network Extension APIs.
If your company makes Wi-Fi
Hotspots that are deployed
in public places like hotels,
airports, coffee shops,
you can use the any Hotspot
helper API to create apps
that connect to your
Wi-Fi Hotspots.
If your company creates
a personal VPN service
that your users use to securely
browse the Internet you can use
the NEVPN manager API to
create apps that connect
to your personal VPN service.
If your company creates a
remote access VPN server,
you can use the any tunnel
provider family of APIs
to create apps that
connect to your VPN server.
And finally if your school
creates a network content
filtering solution
for use by schools
to protect the students'
Internet browsing,
you can use the any filter
provider family of APIs
to create apps that
filter network content.
So these are all of the Network
Extension APIs that we are going
to talk about today
during the session.
So let's go ahead and dive into
the any Hotspot helper API.
So the any Hotspot helper
API is used to create apps
that connect to Wi-Fi Hotspots.
Now, some of you may be aware
that there actually are
already APIs that you can use
to create apps that
connect to Wi-Fi Hotspots.
The CNSetSupportedSSIDs and
CNMarkPortalOnline APIs,
but they have limitations.
One problem is that the
Hotspot list you can pass
to CNSetSupportedSSIDs
is limited in size.
If you have a Global Network
of Wi-Fi Hotspots you're trying
to connect your app
to you can quickly run
into the size limitation.
Another draw-back
is that in order
to call CNMarkPortalOnline,
users have to manually
run your application.
This is exacerbated by the
fact that there's no indication
to the user they
need to do this.
It is not a great
user experience.
The users don't know that
they have to go into the app
to connect to the Wi-Fi Hotspot.
So we've introduced the
any Hotspot helper API
to address some of
these limitations.
So the way this works is
you first register your app
with the system as
a Hotspot helper.
Then as the device comes
within range of Wi-Fi networks,
scanning for Wi-Fi networks or
the user selects a Wi-Fi network
to connect to, the system will
call into your app, run your app
in the background,
call into your app
and give your app
the opportunity
to claim the Wi-Fi
Hotspot with a level
of confidence, high,
medium or low.
If you claim a Hotspot with
a high level of confidence,
the system will call you
to actually perform
the authentication
with the Wi-Fi Hotspot.
And it will periodically
call you
to maintain the authentication
session.
The Hotspot helper
API also allows you
to annotate Wi-Fi networks that
show up in the Wi-Fi manager
in the settings app and you can
annotate these Wi-Fi networks
with the name of your app
or the name of your company.
So that's the any
Hotspot helper API.
You can use this
API to create apps
that seamlessly connect
to Wi-Fi Hotspots.
Next let's look at
the NEVPN manager API.
You can use this API to
create apps that connect
to a personal VPN service
that users will use
to securely browse the Internet.
Now, the NEVPN manager
API is not new in iOS 9.
We introduced this API in iOS 8.
We made some enhancements to the
API and made the API available
on OS X, OS X El Capitan.
The way this works is you
can use the NEVPN manager API
to configure and control
the built-in IPSEC client
on the platform.
You can create a single
personal VPN configuration.
I'll talk about what a
personal VPN configuration is
in a few minutes here.
The built in IPSEC
clients supports IKE v1
and IKE v2 key exchange
protocols.
You can use either of these.
You can configure the VPN
to connect automatically
under certain network
conditions.
New in iOS 9 and
OS X El Capitan,
you can configure http proxies
for http traffic
traversing your VPN tunnel.
And personal VPN configurations
coexist and cooperate
with enterprise VPN
configurations.
Suppose the user is
using your app to connect
to your personal VPN service,
and they are securely
browsing the Internet and want
to access something in their
company's internal network.
So they go ahead and connect
to their enterprise VPN and all
of the traffic that's destined
for those internal
resources will go ahead
and use that enterprise VPN.
But everything else
that is not going
to use the enterprise
VPN will continue to go
through the personal VPN.
Personal VPN remains connected
and will continue
to tunnel traffic.
So there's a brief run
down of the features
that the NEVPN manager
API provides.
Another way that we've enhanced
NEVPN manager is we've enhanced
our IKE v2 protocol support.
We think that's a great
tunneling protocol
and made it better
in this release.
We now support MOBIKE.
We will now seamlessly
transition your IKE v2 tunnel
from one network
interface to the other.
For example, if your
tunnel is connected
over the Wi-Fi interface but
the user walks out of range
of that Wi-Fi network, so
now the device switches
over to use the cellular
interface,
the IKE v2 tunnel will
seamlessly transition over.
Very cool.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; JAMIE WOOD: We now have full
support for IPv6, both inside
and outside of the
IKE v2 tunnel.
We now support IKE
fragmentation.
This allows the IKE v2 tunnel to
work more reliably in a variety
of network environments.
We have IKE redirect
supports allowing you
to load balance your
IKE v2 server.
So with all of these
enhancements it is now better
than ever.
IKE v2 works better than ever.
It works more reliably
in a wider number
of network environments.
So now let's take a
look at some code.
How do you use the
NEVPN manager API?
I want to show you some code
that will create this
personal VPN configuration.
So each app that uses the
NEVPN manager API gets access
to a single personal
VPN configuration,
which is represented by a
single NEVPN manager object.
So first I get a reference to
my shared manager object and all
of the VPN configurations
on the system are stored
in the network extension
preferences.
Before I can work with my
configuration, in my code,
I need to load it from those
preferences using this load
from preferences with
completion handler call.
In the completion handler,
the first thing I want
to do is check and see if my
configuration exists or not.
I look at the protocol
property on the manager object.
If that's nil, it means I
don't have a configuration yet.
I want to set one up.
I'll configure a IKE v2
configuration here and I fill it
out with all the IKE v2 specific
configuration parameters.
When I'm done with that I'll
set the protocol property
on the manager object and I'll
enable the VPN configuration.
You can only have one personal
VPN configuration enabled
on the system at a time.
And then when I'm all done,
go ahead and call save
to preferences to
save the configuration
into the network
extension preferences
and apply the configuration
of the system
so they can actually be used.
From here you can use
the API to manually start
and stop the VPN tunnel
and introspect the status
of the VPN tunnel to know
when you're connected,
disconnected, et cetera.
But for great user experience
another thing to do is
to configure connect on-demand.
So with connect on-demand you
can set up rules that state
when the VPN should
connect automatically.
So, for this example, I'm going
to go ahead and set up a rule
that says that my VPN should
connect whenever the device is
on a Wi-Fi network.
So the first thing to do,
I'm going to create an
on-demand rule connect object.
So this is a rule that says
when this rule matches,
connect the VPN.
Next I'm going to set an
interface type match condition
on my rule.
So it says when the device
is on a particular type
of network interface,
then this rule will match.
I'm go to set that to Wi-Fi.
This rule will match when the
device is on a Wi-Fi network.
Go ahead and set the
on-demand rules array
to contain this new rule
and save the result
to the preferences.
So now my VPN will connect
automatically whenever the
device is on a Wi-Fi network.
Okay. So that's the
NEVPN manager API.
You can use this API to
create apps that connect
to your personal VPN service.
Let's go ahead and talk
about the any tunnel
provider family of APIs.
You use these APIs to
create apps that connect
to enterprise VPN servers.
So the way this works is
you create a custom VPN
protocol provider.
This is essentially the
client side implementation
of your own custom
tunneling protocol.
These protocol providers
run as app extensions.
They run in the background
handling background traffic.
You can create two types
of tunnel providers.
You can create a
Packet Tunnel Provider.
These tunnel traffic
at the IP layer.
You can create, or you can
create an App Proxy provider
that tunnels traffic
at the app layer.
The tunnel provider family
also has APIs that allow you
to configure and control your
protocol provider from your app.
So similar to the VPN manager
API where you can configure
and control the IPSEC
client, these APIs allow you
to configure and control your
own custom protocol provider.
Let's take a closer look at the
NEPacket Tunnel provider API.
How does this work?
So suppose we have an NEPacket
Tunnel Provider here running
on the system and it's
connected to a VPN server
and providing a tunnel
to some internal network.
So you've got an app that's
trying to connect to a resource
in the internal network.
So the app will open
up a network connection
that will create a socket and
create a TCP/IP connection
and the packets for that TCP/IP
connection will be routed
to the UTUN0 interface.
This is a virtual interface, so
instead of sending the packets
out over the physical
network it will divert them
to the NEPacket Tunnel Provider.
The Packet Tunnel Provider
then can take the packets,
encapsulate them in
your tunneling protocol,
send them over to
the tunneling server.
The tunneling server
will decapsulate them,
inject those packets
into the internal network
and they will be delivered
to the ultimate destination,
and the return packets will
be encapsulated by the server,
sent back to the provider,
the provider decapsulates them
and injects them back into the
networking stack via the UTUN0
interface, they'll
be delivered back
up through the TCP/IP
stack to the application.
This is the basic
way that this works.
NEPacket Tunnel Provider
has a lot of control
over the UTUN0 interface.
Most importantly, it
can specify the routes.
The IP destinations that will
be routed to the UTUN0 interface
and through the tunnel.
The Packet Tunnel Provider can
specify the virtual address
to assign to the
interface, as well as the DNS
and proxy settings
that should be used
for traffic routed
through the tunnel.
So next Tommy Pauly is going to
come up and give us a brief demo
of how to create an
NEPacket Tunnel Provider.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; TOM PAULY: Thank you, Jamie.
We are excited to have you
write your own custom VPN
protocol providers.
To help you do that I want
to show you quickly the steps
that are involved in building
a Packet Tunnel Provider.
I'm going to start
with an Xcode project
in which I have an app already.
It is using the manager APIs
to create a configuration.
So we are going to skip over
that part and we're going
to assume that I have a
framework that is implemented
to do my own custom
protocol negotiation.
I want to show how to build
this new extension and kind
of put all the pieces together.
All right.
So here I have my project.
The first thing you need
to do is add a new
target for your extension.
To get this, in OS X El
Capitan we've added it
into the network
extension framework.
So on your system if you go to
system, library, Frameworks,
network extension
Framework and you go
into the resources folder,
we've provided an installer
for the templates for
this, these target types.
So you can go through
the installer.
I'm going to install
it just for this user.
And now I have the templates.
If I go into my project and
I try to create a new target,
under application extensions I
now have four new target types.
I have App Proxy providers
for application layer VPNs.
I have two filter control
and data providers.
These allow me to do content
filtering which we'll talk
about later and I have
Packet Tunnel Provider.
My protocol in this case uses
IP level tunneling for my VPN.
I'll choose the Packet
Tunnel Provider.
Going to write in Swift.
Let's just call it
packet tunnel.
Great. Now I have a new target
and I can start building
my VPN provider.
So let's jump ahead to the
actual process of writing this.
My protocol happens to
be based around UDP.
It uses UDP to talk
to the server
and tunnel traffic
from the system.
I have subclassed the
NEPacket Tunnel Provider class
and this is the class going
to be called in my extension
to start and stop my VPN.
The most important
function that I'm going
to overwrite here is the
start tunnel with options.
This will get called
whenever the user
or the system automatically
wants to start your VPN.
And if you notice, it calls and
passes a completion handler.
This completion handler is
what you can use to call
and tell the system that you
are done setting up your VPN.
When you call this, the system
will know you fully connected
and it's ready to go.
So I mentioned already that my
protocol is based around UDP.
I want to in my start create
a UDP connection to my server.
In order to do this I'm going to
create an NWUDP session object.
This is one of many convenience
networking APIs that we've added
to the Network Extension
Framework to help you make good
and very efficient connections.
So UDP session allows me
to create a connection
to a host name.
It will do all the
DNS resolution for me
and asynchronously let me
know when it's ready to go.
I can do reading and writing of
multiple data grams at a time
for the most efficient
connections possible.
Let's implement start
tunnel with options now.
The first thing I need
to do is actually figure
out what I'm trying
to connect to.
I look at my configuration
to get my server address.
This might be an IP
address or a host name.
I then wrap it up in
an NW host end point.
This is just a container
object that takes an address
or a host name and puts
it alongside a port
that belongs to my protocol.
I then call create UDP session
2 end point to start the process
of doing DNS resolution
and creating the
connection to my server.
At this point the system starts
doing that and I am waiting
for the event that I
want to read and write.
I do KeyVO to watch the state
property of the UDP session
to get these transitions.
So at this point I'm pretty
much done with my start call.
The last thing I need to do is
save that completion handler
that I got at the
beginning because I'm not
yet done completing
my VPN connection.
So I'm going to declare a
pending start completion.
And I'm going to
save that for later.
All right.
So I'm going to skip
over the part
where we actually
negotiate with our server.
I assume your protocol
already knows how to do that.
I'm going to skip ahead to where
we have been assigned an address
and other network settings.
We want to apply it to the
system and let the system know
that we're done bringing
up the VPN.
This is just a custom
function that I wrote that says
that I'm done bringing
up my connection.
What I'm going to do is call,
create NEPacket Tunnel
network settings object,
and this is a bundle of settings
that I can apply
into the system.
I can set the IPv4 settings,
I have an assigned
address and subnet.
I have route settings.
In this case I want to be the
default route for the system
but I can also have a long
list of split tunnel routes.
I can define the overhead
bytes that my tunnel has.
For every packet,
how much do I incur
for encryption and
encapsulation.
This helps the system know how
large it should send packets.
And lastly, I can
set the DNS settings.
I can set my assigned
DNS server or domain.
To apply this to the system,
I call set tunnel
network settings.
I get a callback
handler when it is done
and that lets me know it has
been successfully applied
and I can call the start
completion handler letting the
system know that I'm
done bringing up the VPN.
This is great.
I have a full connection up.
But the thing I'm
missing is being able
to route traffic back and forth.
I'll give you a look at
what that looks like.
So as Jamie mentioned,
the way you're doing this,
you have a virtual
interface that is going
to be sending packets up
into your protocol provider
and then you're going to
send that off to your server.
When you receive packets back
from the server you re-inject
them back into the stack.
I want to start first
with the outbound flow.
A packet tunnel provider has a
property called a packet flow.
This represents the
virtual interface
that you can read
and write into.
If I call read packets
with completion handler,
I will get called back
with an array of packets
that have been sent
out into the network.
I can send these into my
protocol to encapsulate
and to encrypt them and
generate a new array
of encrypted payloads.
And very easily I can write
these as multiple data grams
at one time into the UDP session
to send over to the server.
That's all we need to
do to send packets out.
Coming back in is very similar.
Here I have a function
that is taking packets
in from the UDP server.
And I can simply send
these to my protocol.
I can decapsulate them, generate
IP packets which I then write
into my packet flow property.
Great. So now I have
a connection
that can be established
in read and write.
Let's see how this
looks in practice.
All right.
So here I have my device.
If you notice I've
installed already my VPN app.
First I want to show you that
if I go into Safari and try
to access the internal website,
I do not have access
to it right now.
I now can go into my VPN
app and I hit start VPN.
And what this did,
in the background it kicked
off the tunnel packet provider.
If you can see now, I
do have the VPN badge
up in the status bar.
It actually did come up and
establish the connection.
I can then go back
into Safari and I see
that my internal
page has now loaded.
So we have a fully working VPN
protocol provider all written
in Swift.
That simple.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; TOM PAULY: Back to Jamie.
&gt;&gt; JAMIE WOOD: All right.
Thank you, Tommy.
So Tommy just showed us how
to create a can packet
tunnel provider.
It's easy and powerful.
So while we are on the subject
of Packet Tunnel Provider I want
to take a moment and talk about
Per-App VPN for managed apps.
Per-App VPN is great for BYOD or
bring your own device use cases.
In BYOD you have company
employees who want
to bring their own
personal device,
connect it to the
company's internal network
and access network resources.
They also don't want all
of their Internet traffic
to be routed through
the company's VPN.
And then you have
enterprises that want
to give their employees
access, but they want
to restrict the applications
that can access their
internal network.
So this is where
Per-App VPN is great.
So with Per-App VPN
you can set up the VPN
so that only certain managed
applications can use the VPN.
The way to set this up
is using Apple's own MDM
or mobile device
management protocol.
You enroll devices
with an MDM service.
The MDM service has
the ability to push
down configurations including
VPN configurations as well
as managed applications.
And the MDM service can also
link those managed applications
with Per-App VPN
configurations to send
up a Per-App VPN deployment.
Now, we support Per-App VPN
with, we've always supported it
with custom App Proxy providers.
In iOS 9 and OS X El Capitan,
we now support Per-App VPN
with custom packet
tunnel providers
and support Per-App VPN
with a built-in IPSEC
clients on the platform.
So let's go ahead and take a
look at how Per-App VPN works
in the network data path.
We have the same Packet Tunnel
Provider that we had before.
We have the UTUN0
interface again
that the traffic is routed to.
Now we have a managed
application that is linked
to the VPN configuration.
Instead of having the traffic
routed to the UTUN0 interface
by the destination IP,
the traffic is routed
to the UTUN0 interface by
the source application.
Only this managed app
can access the VPN.
If the user uses another
app that is not managed,
it is going to connect
to the network
out the physical interface.
Even if it's trying to
connect to the same IP
that the managed app
is connecting to.
All right.
So that's how Per-App VPN works.
Tommy is going to give us
another brief demo of how
to configure Per-App VPN.
&gt;&gt; TOM PAULY: Great.
Thank you, Jamie.
We are really excited to have...
Now, everyone who is
writing a custom protocol
or even using the built in
IPSEC protocols will be able
to deploy Per-App VPN to
make great UID solutions.
As Jamie mentioned, we create
these Per-App configurations
with MDM.
MDM is pushing down a
configuration profile
that defines the VPN and also
pushes down the managed apps
to associate with that VPN.
I want to show how to modify
an existing VPN profile
to make it work with
Per-App VPN.
I'm going to do it
with a profile
that configures the same
custom app that I just built.
So here is a look
into a VPN profile.
There's a lot on here.
You don't have to
get it all right now.
I want to highlight the
parts that are different.
The three tweaks
that you need to make
to have this profile
work with Per-App VPN.
The first is the payload type.
Normally it is
com.Apple.vpn.managed simply add
a .applayer to the end of that
to make that a Per-App VPN.
There are multiple
types of providers
that work with Per-App VPN.
So we need to specify
which type you're using.
Within the VPN payload,
we have a new key
that is the provider type.
And you can specify either
packet tunnel or App Proxy.
In this case as you saw, my app
uses a packet tunnel protocol.
I'll specify that one.
The last field you need to
add is called the VPN UUID.
Which is an arbitrary
string that acts as the glue
between a VPN configuration
and the managed apps.
When an MDM server pushes down
managed apps, it will mark them
with the same VPN UUID
so the system knows those
apps can only route traffic
through that VPN.
This profile should
work for Per-App VPN.
So because we are so eager
to have you guys make apps
that work with Per-App VPN,
we wanted to make it really
easy to develop with it.
You may not have access
to a full MDM solution
while you are developing.
So we've enabled for development
builds of your app only.
Not distribution builds.
The ability to specify
in an info Plist apps
to associate your
VPN configurations
with to make it easier
to test Per-App VPN.
Here is a look at an info Plist
of your app, it's small here,
but we have a new key
called NETest App Mapping.
This is a dictionary of arrays,
the keys are the same
UUID I mentioned before,
the glue to hold configurations
and apps together.
Within the array you can specify
the string bundle identifiers
of apps that you want to
force to go through your VPN.
In this case I'm going
to use the box app.
Great to show you
what this looks like.
I installed the profile and
the info Plist on my device.
And so here I have
a configuration
for my Per-App VPN.
And you can see that I have my
custom Packet Tunnel protocol.
And listed are the included apps
and it has now associated Box
with my VPN configuration.
That's all it takes to
making Per-App VPN work
with your protocol.
Thank you.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; JAMIE WOOD: All right.
Thank you, Tommy.
So we really think that Per-App
VPN is a great deployment
for BYOD, provides a
great user experience
for company employees.
We highly encourage
you to deploy it.
So next I want to talk about
the NEApp Proxy Provider API.
Now, any App Proxy
providers work exclusively
with Per-App VPN.
So let's take a look
and see how these work,
how they are different from
the packet tunnel providers.
We have a managed application,
an App Proxy Provider running
on the system and the managed
app is going to connect
to an internal network resource.
Instead of having IP packets
routed to the UTUN0 interface,
the data the managed app writes
to its socket is diverted
directly to the proxy provider.
So from there the NEApp Proxy
Provider can send the data
to the proxy server
and the return data
from the proxy server will be
sent back to the proxy provider,
it can inject it into the socket
to be delivered to
the application.
The reason why we added the
NEApp Proxy Provider API is
really about the servers.
So you're connecting to
these transparent network
proxy servers.
The servers are usually
easier to deploy
than a fully fledged
IP layer VPN.
You don't have to provision
virtual IPs to assign
to the UTUN0 interface.
They usually scale
a little better.
We've given you the
NEApp Proxy Provider API
to connect to these servers.
And a new thing that we added
for App Proxy Provider in iOS 9
and OS X El Capitan is the
ability to proxy UDP traffic
in addition to TCP traffic.
Oh, here we have a managed app
to illustrate those
are still connecting
out the physical interface.
Okay. So that's the NETunnel
provider family of APIs.
Use these APIs to
create custom clients
for your tunneling protocol,
to connect to enterprise
VPN servers.
Now let's take a look
at the NEFilter provider
family of APIs.
Use these APIs to create the
network content filtering
solutions for schools.
There are currently some ways
that schools can do
network content filtering
with iOS devices.
They can deploy an on-site
content filter, put a device
on their local network and
route all their Internet traffic
through that content filter
so that they can filter
the content, right?
The draw back with this is
that it's only available
on the school's local network.
If the students want to
take the schools iPads
or iPhones home they either
can't browse the Internet at all
when they are home or browse
the Internet unfiltered.
This is not so great.
To sort of try to solve
some of that problem,
the school can deploy global
proxy, put it on the Internet,
route all of the Internet
traffic through the proxy
to perform the content
filtering.
The draw back, the school has to
deploy and maintain the proxy,
and not all the schools have
the resources to do that.
Another solution is to
use a full tunnel VPN.
That has a lot of the same
problems as global proxy
and may be even harder
to deploy and maintain.
The best solution for schools is
to filter the network
content on the device.
Before it leaves the device
and just before it's actually
delivered to the user.
So this is exactly what the
NEFilter provider family
of APIs allows you to do.
Now, the NEFilter provider
APIs are only available on iOS.
And using API you can
perform dynamic evaluation
of network content.
You have the ability to update
filtering rules on the fly,
for instance downloaded
from the Internet.
And you have the ability to send
back a customizable block page
to the user when they
try to access something
that they are not
allowed to access.
Now, NEFilter provider only
works on supervised devices.
We are targeting
this at schools,
schools that own their devices,
are locking them down so
that users can't install
new apps or change settings.
This is where filter
provider works.
So let's take a look
at how filter provider
works in the data path.
So we have an NEFilter data
provider extension running
on the system.
And its job is to make
pass and block decisions
about network content that is
flowing through the system.
Now, because it has access
to all this network content,
we've locked down this
data provider so it runs
in a read only sand box.
It can't access the network
and it has read only
access to the disk.
So we've also provided
another extension,
the NEFilter control
provider, and its job is
to feed information to
the filter data provider
so that it can do its job.
For instance, download
rules over the Internet,
write them to a location on disk
where the data provider
can access them.
Now, suppose that the user is
running an app using Web kit,
right?
They have a UI Web view in
their UI and so all the content
that is being rendered into
the Web kit is passed off
to the filter data
provider, which makes a pass
or block decision on that data.
So obviously not all
applications use Web kit.
There's some applications that
are using other networking APIs
such as NSURL session,
NSURL connection,
some of the CFNetwork APIs.
For those APIs we added a hook
into the socket layer to send
that traffic over to
the filter data provider
so it can make a
pass/block decision.
As you can see the
filter control provider
and data provider together
provide a comprehensive content
filtering solution
on the device.
So for Web kit applications,
when the data provider
makes a block decision,
decides to block some
access to the content,
the data provider can send
a, instruct the Web kit
to display a block page.
Here is an example
of that block page.
You can, using the API you
can customize this block page
in a number of ways.
You can change the
organization that's displayed.
For example, you can display
the name of the school
and you can customize
this request access link.
You can choose to not
display the link at all,
not give the user the option of
gaining access to the content.
If you display it, you can
display the text of the link
and target of the link.
Point to the Web service where
users can go and request access
to the blocked content.
So that's the NEFilter
provider family of APIs.
You can use these APIs to
create powerful comprehensive,
on-device network content
filtering solutions for schools.
Here is all the Network
Extension APIs we've talked
about today.
And here's some of
the great apps
that you can create
using these APIs.
You can create apps for Wi-Fi
Hotspot, personal VPN services,
enterprise remote access VPNs
and you can create on-device
network content filtering
solutions for schools.
As you can see these
are powerful APIs.
They allow you to extend
and customize the core
networking features
of Apple's platforms.
And because these are very
powerful APIs we do require some
special entitlements for
you to be able to use these.
To use the NEVPN manager API,
you need to select the
personal VPN capability
in your project settings' Xcode.
To use the any Hotspot helper
API, the NETunnel family
of APIs, and the
NEFilter provider family
of APIs you need access to
other special entitlements.
The way to get these
is to send a request
to networkextension@Apple.com.
We'll send you back a
questionnaire that we'll ask you
to fill out and send back to us
and we'll process your request.
We're excited to be
delivering these APIs to you.
We are looking forward to
getting all of your requests
and giving you access
to these APIs.
So what should you do?
Port your Captive Network apps
to use the NEHotspot
helper, which is seamless.
Adopt the NEManager API
in your personal VPN app
to create seamless
user experience
for those using your
personal VPN service.
Use the NETunnel provider
to create powerful
custom enterprise VPN apps
that connect to your VPN server.
Use the MDM to deploy
Per-App VPN
for great BYOD user experiences.
And use the NEFilter
provider APIs
to create dynamic on-device
network content filtering
for schools.
Here is where you can
get more information.
Unfortunately, the documentation
is not yet published.
Coming soon.
Please keep searching for
it on the developer website.
And the sample code is
also not quite ready yet.
Keep searching for the
simple tunnel sample.
We have a great sample going.
We haven't quite
finished it yet.
Please keep looking for it.
For more information you
are welcome to participate
in the dev forums, contact
developer technical support.
Reach out to Paul Danbold
our Core evangelist.
And here is the address you
can send your network extension
request to.
Here are related sessions.
We encourage you
to check these out.
Especially want to give a plug
for the other Core OS networking
session today happening 11:00
a.m., Your app and next
generation networks.
Thank you all so
much for coming.
Have a great day.
[Applause]