[ Applause ]
>> JEFFREY TRAER
BERNSTEIN: Hello, everyone.
And welcome to designing
for future hardware.
I'm Jeffrey Traer Bernstein.
With me are Matthaeus
Krenn and Bill Lindmeier.
Who is this session for?
Perhaps you're creating
a device that's connected
to an application.
That device could be, say,
a dishwasher that you would
like to control from
your application.
Or maybe it's a drone you would
like to control from an app.
Or maybe a golf club that
would send information
about your swing back
to an application.
Perhaps you have an
application and you would
like to create a device for it.
Maybe it's a game you would like
to create a custom controller
for or a messaging application.
Or maybe a device to
go with a dating app.
Who knows what that would be.
You might also find this
useful if you are designing
for a device you just don't have
yet like perhaps an Apple Watch
or some fancy new
thing we've released.
Who are we?
We are a team of inventors,
designers, prototypers.
We work across all
of Apple's products
and explore what new
interfaces mean to our devices,
operating systems
and applications.
We brought you exciting features
such as Multitouch gestures,
Force Touch and a Taptic Engine.
This time last year we did
Prototyping at WWDC 2014.
Was anyone there for it?
[ Cheering ]
>> JEFFREY TRAER BERNSTEIN:
Thank you - excellent.
Thank you for joining us.
Did anyone watch it online?
Less people, all right.
Well, it is not required
for this session,
but I suggest you check
it out afterwards.
I'll give you a brief
synopsis right now.
We unveiled a disruptive,
revolutionary new
application called Toast Modern
that allowed you to browse for
artisanal, overpriced toast
on the streets of San Francisco,
take photos of the toast
you're eating, and share it
with your friends
and loved ones.
We used this application to
explain why to Prototype.
There are two important reasons.
One, test ideas to save time
and money building the right
things for your products.
Number two is to get new
ideas to make the experience
of your product even better.
We also talked about
how to Prototype.
Make fake apps, show people,
and learn from their feedback,
and do it over and over
again until the experience
of your product is incredible.
As you might have
imagined, the reception
on the Internet was incredible.
People said things like,
"The workflow shown is
something I may try."
(Laughter)
>> JEFFREY TRAER BERNSTEIN:
The Prototyping video
for WWDC is great.
"Grab a plate of toast."
" Takeaways: Number one, make
fake apps; number two, um...
missed that part."
"I'm so proud of you."
My mom.
So today, you're all very
fortunate to be here.
We are going to unveil
a brand new,
revolutionary Toast
Modern product
that builds upon the success of
Toast Modern, the application.
We are going to give you a peek
behind the curtain, a little bit
of how Apple and partners
prototype the watch.
We're going to create a device
and an app that connects to it.
We're going to show you along
the way a few prototyping
strategies for hardware
and software.
I would like to share our
Toast Modern product today.
Would you all like to see it?
[ Applause ]
>> JEFFREY TRAER
BERNSTEIN: Excellent.
It's a revolutionary,
disruptive, connected, social,
big data-y Internet of
Things thing and this is it.
[ Music ]
>> JEFFREY TRAER
BERNSTEIN: Thank you.
Thank you very much.
[ Applause ]
So we call this Toastal Service.
It is the world's
first social toaster.
It allows you to
send Toast messages
to your friends and loved ones.
Of course, it's available in
three great colors: Silver,
Space Grey and 18-Karat gold.
[ Applause ]
>> JEFFREY TRAER BERNSTEIN:
So we have an iPhone
and we have a Toaster.
Both have excellent
qualities to recommend them.
The iPhone has a
great interface.
It is connected to the Internet.
And it's always with you.
Our toaster can turn
bread into toast.
So we want to combine
the capabilities of each.
We want to blur the lines
between hardware and software,
create a perfect
meld of the two.
I can think of another
product that has done the same.
That is the Apple Watch.
Now, you might think that
at Apple we would begin here
with the fully formed Apple
Watch springs from the brain
of its designers and is
carved out of aluminum,
and sent to all of you.
In reality, we actually
begin by drawing the Watch
on another device so we can
experiment with the interface.
This is a pretty well formed
watch as it exists today.
We start with this, a rectangle,
and we use this platform
to experiment with the different
things we might need to add
to the Watch to make
the experience great.
We might add a Digital Crown
that we draw on the screen
and scroll over to understand
how that works and experiment
with different buttons.
This is great, teaches us a ton
about the interface of the Watch
and the experience of using it.
But you can't strap an iPhone
to your wrist and go outside
and try it in context.
So some of our app partners
when they were developing
for the Watch before
Watches were available
to them did some clever things.
For example, this
French Transit app.
They created their
own Apple Watch.
It is more rustic but useful.
They drew some pictures of
their different screens.
And then slid them
inside of the watch.
This was important.
This is a Transit app.
I need to be able to see
what it's like to run
for the train I'm late for
and see what train
I'm going to catch.
They have to try it in context.
The German newspaper Bild
printed out a picture
of an Apple Watch and slid
underneath various screens.
It was important for them
to test the legibility
of their articles in the places
where they expect
people to read them.
We learned a few things
about Prototyping
hardware and software.
We learned we can fake
hardware on screens
as with the Apple Watch.
We can fake software
with pictures
as we explained last
year with Toast Modern,
and it is important to try it
in context at the right size,
in the right place as you saw
with the paper Watch Prototypes.
Here is our prototyping
cycle from last year:
make fake things,
show them to people
and learn from their feedback.
This year we are going to make
fake hardware and software.
Before we begin we are going
to ask ourselves three important
questions for each of those.
What needs to be more real?
What can be faked?
That's nearly everything except
for the one thing we are going
to choose to be real, and
where will it be used?
And then we are going to
go and show it to people.
Who do we show it to?
The people you app is for.
If it's not meant
for your office mate,
go find the people it's for.
Where? In the place
where people will use it.
You might have to go outside.
And remember, don't
argue, defend, or dismiss.
You're there to learn
from people's impression
of the Prototype
you put together.
After we've shown it to people,
we learn from their feedback.
We ask ourselves
three questions:
Number one, what is working?
Number two, what is not working?
Number 3, what other
ideas does this give us?
Now we are going to go through
the cycle three times today
and show you a few
different techniques.
We are going to begin with
pictures and animation.
Then we are going to use
a technique we call behind
the curtain.
After that we are going to
create a lightweight interactive
and connected prototype.
I would like to quickly recap
Toastal Service for you guys.
It's the world's
first social toaster.
Allows you to receive toast
messages, we call them Toasties,
and send toast messages,
and we want that
experience to be magical.
To kick it off, I'd like to
ask Matthaeus up to the stage.
[ Applause ]
>> MATTHAEUS KRENN:
Thanks, Jeff.
Cool. So how are we going
to get started with this?
So first of all, let's look
at our hardware and our app
and ask ourselves the question
that Jeff just mentioned.
First of all, what do
we make more real now?
Well, I want us actually
to start with the receiving
and the Toasting part
of the experience.
So on the hardware, let's figure
out a way how we can indicate
that a new Toastie
has been received.
On the app we can look at
new Toastie notifications
and see what kind of information
the app can display with it.
The next question is,
what can be faked?
And really here just go for
as much as possible really.
We are not going
to build a Toaster.
We are not going to look at
how to turn bread into Toast.
All we are going to do is
put pictures on the device
and simulate the
hardware like that.
For the app again,
everything we are going
to take pictures for everything.
We are not going to make
anything really interactive
and definitely not
writing any code.
And third, where will
the product be used?
For the Toaster,
that's the kitchen.
For the app it's anywhere
or at least anywhere
around the house for sure.
So let's start with
looking at our Toaster.
We said that we wanted
to simulate hardware
by putting pictures on a screen.
That sounds awfully a lot
like what Jeff just described
with the Apple Watch
on an iPhone.
Luckily Apple also makes a great
Toaster shaped product called
the iPad.
That is just the right
thing for us here.
To sketch out our Toaster, I'm
going to use keynote today.
For you really, whatever gets
you started easily and simply,
I'm going to use keynote today.
Feel free to use
whatever you can.
I'm going to try to keep it
as simple as possible too.
A Toaster is really just
a box, some feet, a lever,
maybe we will actually
call this a digital lever.
And a slot where you can
put in a piece of bread.
We also said that we
wanted to indicate
when a new Toastie
has been received.
We'll put an LED up
there that can light up.
And while we are in
keynote, we are also going
to add some bread
to the Toaster.
This is the Toaster toasting.
And eventually the
Toastie pops back up
and we can see what's on it.
We can take this.
We can open it in
keynote on our iPad.
And we have a Toaster.
For our app we are going
to do something similar.
We are going to get started with
a home screen, a screen shot
of a home screen on the iPhone
and put our app icon on it.
We are going to take a screen
shot and use it as an underlay
for an application that
we want to customize.
That's simple.
For our app, we're going to take
a screen shot of Toast Modern,
the product that we
unveiled last year.
You can see in the top left
corner there's a convenient open
spot that is the perfect place
for the link to our Toast inbox.
I'll put a Toaster icon up there
and a little notification badge.
On the Toaster inbox
I'm going to use a slice
of bread right now as a place
holder because I don't want
to take away what is
actually on the Toastie.
We don't want to take
away the anticipation,
that surprise moment when
you are sitting waiting
for your Toast to be toasted.
We definitely want to show
who is this Toastie from?
We will put a picture and
name of the sender up there.
And we are also going to add the
date and time when it was sent.
At this point I think
it would be great
if we can immediately also
choose how dark we want our
bread to be Toasted.
We can do that easily
with a slider here.
Now, again let's open that on
our iPhone and see what it looks
like on an actual device.
This immediately gives
us a really life like
but completely fake app.
Now we can look at how these two
things work together in action.
You can see that I'm
just tapping on a screen
to make the notification
appear to open the app
and to go into the inbox.
And on the Toaster, I can also
-- you can first of all you see
that the LED is already
blinking.
Then I can tap to
insert some bread.
I tap again to lower
our digital lever.
Then in a couple seconds later
the Toastie will pop back out,
and we're going to
see what's on it.
That is not too bad for now.
We can immediately take this
and show it to our friends
and ask them how they feel
about this so we can learn
from what they have to say.
So what is working right now?
Well, the LED seems to
be really good indicator
that there is a new
Toastie, and the notification
on the app helps us know that
there is a new Toastie even
when we are not sitting
in the kitchen
in full anticipation
looking at our Toaster.
What is not working so well
is, a lot of people mentioned
to us what happens when you
have more than one Toastie?
That's true, our design doesn't
account for that very well.
So what can we do about this?
Well, maybe we'll actually
upgrade the LED on our Toaster
and maybe our app
can show a list
of Toasties instead
of just the last one.
So let's take it from
the top here again.
Let's look again at our
hardware and at our app.
And at this stage again let's
ask ourselves what needs
to be more real now.
Well, we want our hardware
to handle multiple Toasties
and toast the right one.
On the app we want to be
able to browse Toasties
and select the right one for us.
What can we fake?
Still we are going to
fake as much as possible.
There is not going to
be a real connection
between the two devices.
Anything related to actual
toasting we are not even going
to touch that.
For the app sending data back
and forth, again we are going
to fake that and our UI
is mostly still pictures
and animations.
Where will the products be used?
Still the same as before.
The Toaster in the kitchen
and the app really anywhere.
Let's look at our Toaster again.
We said we wanted to change
something about the LED.
So maybe we can use a dot
matrix display here instead.
We could indicate how many
Toasties have been received.
And instead of using hi res
touch screen that we put
on the Toaster here which would
make our product complicated
to produce and expensive
to buy, we are not going
to recreate capabilities that
we have on the phone anyway.
We'll keep the hardware
simple and focus
on the complicated
stuff on the phone.
So we'll add additional
Toasties to our inbox.
Easy to swipe through
so we can select
which one we want to Toast.
We will create a state where
a different Toastie has
been selected.
We will also add a screen
that shows up on the app
when the Toaster is toasting.
We can add a count
down to the top
so we know how long it will be
until we enjoy our
delicious piece of toast.
Finally the Toastie is toasted
and it's back on the list
and we can see what's
on our app as well.
Now we have an iPhone, now we
have an iPhone running a keynote
of a fake app and we have
an iPad running a keynote
of a fake Toaster.
With those two together we can
start playing more realistic
scenario of our product
experience.
A notification comes in on
both devices at the same time.
We open the app.
We go to our inbox and
select a different Toastie.
We add some bread
to the Toaster,
push down the digital lever
and eventually the Toastie
pops back out on both devices.
Now, that's pretty cool.
But there is a fundamental
problem with this unfortunately.
When we test our product, we
can't just put the devices next
to each other in front of us
and happily tap on both of them
in a really orchestrated way
to play this perfect scenario.
What is more realistic is that
eventually the Toaster is going
to be in the kitchen and
the app is going to be all
over the place with you.
That's a fundamental part
of the experience, right?
You get a notification.
You walk up to the Toaster.
You do a couple things.
It starts Toasting
and you walk away
to brush your teeth,
something like that.
Eventually the Toastie is done
and you come back
to the Toaster.
If you don't capture that
part of the experience,
you're testing for something
that is entirely unrealistic.
How can we make our
two Prototypes talk
to each other over a distance.
Ideally how can we do
that without putting any
additional effort into it.
I want to keep using the keynote
prototypes we just built.
It turns out our team has a
really convenient technique
for circumstances like that.
I want to show that
to you right now.
You can see this is still our
keynote prototype on the phone.
But now the notification
actually comes in on its own.
We can still tap to
open the app and then go
and select the different
Toastie that we want to Toast.
And on the Toaster, you can see
that we can still tap
to insert some bread.
Now look at the app, what
happens when we lower the lever.
The app responds
to it in realtime.
When the Toastie is
back finished Toasting,
it appears on both
devices at the same time.
That's pretty awesome, I think.
But how do we do that?
Especially considering that
this is really just images
on devices, and we didn't
write a single line of code.
Well, it turns out
we have something
that is a little bit cooler
and a little bit faster
and a little bit
smarter than code.
[ Laughter ]
>> MATTHAEUS KRENN:
We call this ...
[ Applause ]
>> MATTHAEUS KRENN: We call this
technique behind the curtain.
It is essentially about a person
pretending to be a computer.
In our case, it's
me behind the sofa,
using two keynote remotes
connected to the iPhone and iPad
and I can supplement
tapping on the Prototypes
by remotely controlling
the state of each device.
When you do something on the
app I can press on the remote
and the Toaster reacts to it.
We create a perfect simulation
of this realistic experience
and we didn't really have to
do anything to achieve it.
You wouldn't believe
actually how many people
at Apple we tricked
into thinking we have
implemented some magical
technology where really, as
we were demoing our Prototype,
some of our team is
just kind of sitting
in the corner controlling
one of the Prototypes.
And so again with this more
realistic setup we can go
to our friends and
ask them for feedback.
And we ask them what's working.
Well, selecting from
many Toasties
and then Toasting the right
one, it's all done, all good.
What is not working?
Well, despite our incredible
Prototyping efforts,
the devices still don't feel
really connected and responsive.
What can we do about that?
Maybe we can have the Toaster
react in realtime to the input
in the app and vice versa.
To do that we are
going to have to step
up our Prototyping
game a little bit.
I'm going to ask
Bill on the stage
to show you guys how to do that.
[ Applause ]
>> BILL: Thank you,
Matthaeus, that's awesome.
Hello, everybody, I'm Bill.
I get to spend my
days experimenting
with top-secret Apple hardware
which is pretty awesome.
So we would like to share a
little bit about our process
that might give you
some ideas for designing
for your own top-secret
hardware or possibly a device
that you just don't have yet.
So after a couple of iterations,
we are feeling pretty good
about the designs that
Matthaeus created for us.
However, with the
keynote prototypes,
it can only take us so far.
We can tap through from
state to state or fake that,
but there is no true
interactivity yet.
For example, the digital lever.
We can't drag that up and
down, which is pretty critical.
So let's return to
our three questions
and decide how can we enhance
the fidelity of these prototypes
with a little bit of
interactivity and a little bit
of connectivity to make
them that much better.
What needs to be more real?
On the hardware side we want
to wire up the digital lever.
We also want to connect
the state
of the Toaster to
the app itself.
On the app side let's
allow our friends
to browse the Toasties
in the inbox.
Also pick a Toastie to Toast.
So we like faking things.
What can we keep fake?
Let's not worry about
servers, edge cases,
turning bread into Toast.
And on the app side,
we are going to keep
that message queue
completely canned
and also the Toasties
themselves,
we'll have them be
images on both devices.
We won't actually send
them back and forth
between the devices
over the air.
Okay. So where are we
going to use these things?
Toasters live in the kitchen,
so we'll use the
Toaster in the kitchen.
The app can be used anywhere
that maybe you're
hungry for a snack.
Maybe it's the first app you
launch when you roll out of bed.
We have to ask ourselves,
what is the best way
of moving forward?
Matthaeus said he wanted to
connect the Toaster and the app.
Maybe we start with a real
Toaster, hack it together
with a microcontroller.
Maybe put a wireless radio
on it, some LEDs to make
that a nice little display.
And this would probably work.
But we are not committed enough
to this design to move forward
in this direction because this
is starting to feel very real.
Maybe it's time to 3D print
a model of our Toaster
and start customizing
Toasties with a laser cutter.
Let's be honest, we are
always looking for excuses
to use the 3D printer
and the laser cutter.
[ Applause ]
>> BILL LINDMEIER: But it is
actually really fun making this
slide, but that is
probably putting the cart
in front of the horse a bit.
Okay. So how about a
virtual reality Toaster?
[ Laughter and Applause ]
>> BILL LINDMEIER: This will
be extremely awesome and fun
to use, but Toaster haptics
are still about five years out,
so we have to put it on hold.
Seriously, all three
examples have in common
that they are distracting
us from the task at hand
which is designing
the experience.
So to the extent that we do
any engineering at this point,
let's keep it to the engineering
which enhances our design
and lets us explore that
a little bit further.
That way when we actually do
go to make this thing we know
that we are making
the right thing.
Okay. So with that in
mind, for the purposes
of our Prototype,
what is a Toaster?
It is not a bread heating
device, but you knew that.
It is a connected state machine.
When I say that I just mean
that it's a physical object
with attributes like where
the digital lever is, whether
or not there's Toast in it,
what message is toasting,
and we want to know how do
these attributes respond
to user input.
We can easily model
this with software.
So we are going to take our
existing keynote Prototypes,
the app of the Toaster.
We are going to port
them to Swift.
And when I say we are going to
port them to Swift, I don't mean
that we are going to
make a fully functional,
feature-rich Swift app.
It is a lot like the Prototypes
in that there are screen shots
and they animate based on user
touches, but then we are going
to sprinkle in just a
little bit of extra code
for features we want
to explore further.
Of course this doesn't
have to be Swift.
It can be another
programming language you like.
It can be another tool that
allows you more interactivity.
But we at Apple happen to
like Swift so we are going
to move forward with that.
Okay. So specifically let's
define what we are going
to implement.
The Toast-a-Toastie flow.
So for the first step we want to
pick a Toastie from the inbox.
Next we want to send the
Toastie to the Toaster.
Third, we want to Toast the
selected Toastie and finally,
we want to indicate that
the Toastie is Toasted.
So here is our new
interactive app prototype.
What we've done is turned this
carousel into a UI scroll view
that allows our friends
to easily paginate
between the different messages.
We have a UI slider at
the bottom which allows us
to pick the color of the Toast.
We've also added a gesture
recognizer to each slice
of Toast so we can pull it
down into the virtual Toaster
and simulate that
it's being sent.
Let's see how that
looks in action.
We launch our inbox.
You can see as we swipe through
the Toastie selected increases.
And we can adjust the
Toast darkness variable.
And then we are going
to drag the Toast
down into the virtual Toaster
which sets Toasting to true,
kicks off an animation and
our Toastie is presented.
All right.
Moving on to the Toaster.
We are going to add a gesture
recognizer to the digital lever.
When you pull it all the way
down, it begins Toasting,
set Toasting to true,
begin a timer.
We have also added a
segmented control at the bottom
that lets us easily pick
the message we want to Toast
without connecting
it to the app,
and finally the animation
will present the Toast.
Let's take a look at that.
We are selecting our Toast
which loads the bread.
You can see we have this nice
animation now in the LED matrix.
When we bring the lever
all the way down to 1,
it is Toasting set to
true, kicks off the timer.
And our Toast is presented.
So this is a critical stage.
This technique of
modeling hardware
with software is super
useful and we use it
in our studio all the time.
You can imagine that you are
making a connected Fireplace
and you want to integrate
that with HomeKit.
You can use a projector or that
large screen TV that you've got.
Put it where you expect the
Fireplace to be in the den
and you can simulate
the controls right
where they are going to be used.
Maybe you are creating the next
great Transit app for the Watch
but you don't have a Watch yet.
Throw the interface on
an iPod, bring the iPod
down into the subway station
and use it in context.
Maybe you're making
the next great drone.
You can simulate the hardware
controls on an iPhone,
strap it to the paper prototype,
and when you're moving it
around, you can stream gyroscope
and accelerometer data back
as if it's the real hardware.
So we've got the interactive
app, the interactive Toaster.
Now we need to send data across.
Pick the Toastie from the
app and send physical states
across from the Toaster
back to the app.
What is the best way to do this?
The best way is whatever is
easiest and fastest for you.
We are not designing
a network API.
We can let somebody
else do that later.
We are not worried
about efficiency.
If you're Prototyping
in the browser,
maybe you use Web sockets.
If you've got that drone and
the phone connected to it,
you can stream the
gyroscope data
with O.S.C. Maybe you
have a back end server
and you can use HTTP requests.
I know that some of you have
probably never programmed a
networking layer before.
So think creatively.
You can use a service like if
this then that to observe emails
that you're sending back and
forth between the devices
and take action upon that.
Maybe you're noticing
whenever a new photo is added
to a shared photo stream.
So we are going to use a
Multipeer connectivity peer
to peer connection.
This is what our network
is going to look like.
We have two iPhones
connected to an iPad
and call our network Toast Talk.
The reason we're using
Multipeer connectivity,
it is incredibly easy to set up.
It doesn't require a server and
it allows an arbitrary number
of devices to connect.
So here is a bit of code.
I'm going to fly right through
because we are running short
on time.
We are going to create
a session.
We are going to name the network
Toast Talk and take any data
that comes in and
convert it to a string.
We can choose devices with
this handy class called the MC
Browser View Controller.
Super easy to set up.
You pass the name
into the constructtor
and also pass in that session.
You can present it on a button
click or when the app launches.
Then you just dismiss it
when they've connected.
What messages should
we send back and forth?
The app Prototype wants to tell
the Toaster the Toasty number
and the Toast darkness.
The Toaster needs to
send the lever position
when Toasting began and
when Toasting ended.
A little bit of code
that does that.
We are just going to
convert our string to data
and send that to the session.
And this is an example of how we
might send the letter position.
We are going to say
we've got our message
which is lever position.
Throw a carat in there and
pass some data along with it.
This is a totally arbitrary
format but fast and simple.
We will split the incoming
messages on that carat
and switch overall the message
names and pass the data off
to whatever function
is appropriate.
This allows us this really
cool dynamic relationship
between our Toaster and our app.
You can see as I drag the
digital lever up and down,
that's reflected in the app.
That's pretty great.
We've closed the loop.
We have interactive
apps and Toasters.
The world is good.
Let's give this to our friends,
let them try it in context
and see what they think.
[ Music and Applause ]
>> BILL LINDMEIER: So
Toastal Service is shaping up
and starting to feel
real and we haven't done
that much engineering.
Let's learn from the feedback.
What is working?
Clearly we can pick
messages from the inbox
and send them to the Toaster.
That's a fundamental
part of this experience.
What is not working?
Our friends told us
it's a little odd
that there's no visual
feedback from the Toaster
when you select the color
from the color slider.
Maybe in the next round
of Prototyping iteration we
adjust the color of the LEDs
on that matrix to reflect that
the data is being sent over
and the color is
being remembered.
So with that, I would like to
invite Jeff back up to the stage
and he can wrap it up for us.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> JEFFREY TRAER
BERNSTEIN: Thank you, Bill.
Thanks for taking so much time
on that last sentence,
all right.
Quick recap for everybody.
We Prototyped using
pictures and animation
so we could quickly
see different inputs
and outputs for the Toaster.
We showed you the behind
the curtain technique
to see how the app and
the device work together.
Then we created a
lightweight interactive
and connective Prototype
so we could try the entire
end-to-end experience.
Along the way we learned a
few things about our Toaster.
We don't need a darkness
setting on the Toaster
where most Toasters have that.
We need a number
display on the Toaster.
We need a sensor on
the digital lever
to communicate back to the app.
We figured all of this
out really, really fast.
Look at all the time
and money we saved.
Imagine that we had to build
a real Toaster to learn all
of these things and we got
really cool ideas along the way.
So all of that reminds me:
There are two important
reasons to Prototype.
Number one is to test
ideas to save time
and money building the
right things for your app.
Number two is to get new
ideas to make the experience
of your product even better.
How do we do it?
We make fake things.
We show people and learn
from their feedback.
And we do it over and over again
until our product is incredible.
So here is what we would like
you to go and do after this.
If you are creating a
thing connected to an app,
for the thing, fake
it on a screen.
In context.
For your app, fake it
with pictures in context
and for the connection between
the two, just tap through both.
Or use the behind the curtain
technique or behind the sofa.
And maybe create a
lightweight network prototype.
If you just don't
have the device,
especially perhaps
the next thing
that we unveil, don't wait.
Fake it on a screen, in context.
Here is some stuff
about more information.
There are related sessions.
Most importantly, tomorrow
Designing with Animation.
Some of our teammates at
3:30 in this very room.
I think you'll find
it very useful.
Thank you very much, everybody!
[ Applause ]