[Applause]
>> Hi. My name is Qasid Sadiq,
and I am on the Apple
Accessibility team.
Welcome to Accessibility
on the Watch.
Before we get into that,
let's talk a little bit
about accessibility.
As you know, there are many
different kinds of users,
and as you can imagine, these
users have many different ways
of interacting with the world.
But for the sake of our
conversation, we are going
to focus on a certain subset of
these users, users, for example,
who are visually impaired
or hard of hearing.
As developers, these
users present us
with a very special opportunity.
It's something that's
unique to us.
It's the opportunity to not
only accommodate these groups
of individuals, but to also
really enable and empower them
to do things they otherwise
might not have been able to do.
Now, all of you are here
because you guys are creating
applications which will allow
people to do amazing things.
So let's let everyone
do those amazing things,
regardless of who they are
or how they interact
with the world.
Now, Apple is committed to
this idea, and this is evident
through our accessibility
features on iOS and OS X,
things like VoiceOver, Switch
Control, Assistive Touch, Zoom,
Guided Access, and
so on and so forth.
The Apple Watch is no different.
We try our hardest to make
this device accessible
to as many users as possible.
So let's get into that.
Now, first we are going to talk
about what is accessibility
on the Apple Watch, who
it's for, how it works,
then I want to tell you guys
about how you, as developers,
can make your WatchKit
apps accessible,
and you guys will get to
see those APIs in action.
Finally, we will round
it out with a few tips
and tricks you should consider
when you are designing your
accessibility experience.
Let's talk about the
accessibility features,
starting with VoiceOver.
Now, VoiceOver is an alternate
interface for blind users.
The idea behind it is simple.
VoiceOver simply
reads out whatever is
under the user's finger.
So for example, if my
finger is on the Clock icon,
VoiceOver will read out "clock."
Additionally, we provide a
set of gestures so it's easy
for a VoiceOver user to safely
and effectively navigate
an interface.
I am going to demo
this later on.
Now, for low-vision
users, we have Zoom.
Just like you can
imagine, Zoom allows you
to zoom into an interface.
On top of that, we provide a set
of two finger gestures inspired
by the iOS zoom gestures
and utilize the Crown
to really make it
seamless and easy
to navigate a zoomed interface.
I am going to demo
that, too, later.
In the same vain as Zoom, there
is the X-Large watch face.
This provides large, simple,
uncluttered readout of the time,
so it's easy for a user
to pick up their wrist
and determine what time it is.
Now, the Apple Watch
has a compact screen,
and although the fonts go a long
way in terms of readability,
some users may need to
increase the text size.
For these users, we have the
text size slider and settings.
Now, for users with certain
light and color sensitivities,
there's a Grayscale
switch, which filters the UI
across the whole Watch to
be completely grayscale.
This creates a much easier to
read and undistracting interface
for these particular users.
Now, certain users have
trouble reading interfaces
with blurs on them.
Either the contrast
isn't high enough
or there's distracting
blur or artifacts.
For these users, we have the
Reduce Transparency switch.
This removes transparency from
screens like Notification Center
and Siri so a user can much more
easily read what's happening
on these screens.
Then there's Reduce Motion.
This reduces movement on
the screen all around,
and where movement is
absolutely necessary,
makes it directly correlated
with the user's action.
An example of this is on the
transition from the clock face
to the Home screen, where
instead of zooming in to icons,
we simply have it appear.
This creates a much more
orienting experience
for certain users.
Finally, users with hearing
issues can adjust the left/right
balance and set mono-audio on
their Bluetooth-paired headsets
with their Apple Watch.
So let's see these in action.
Okay. So let's start
with VoiceOver.
You can turn on VoiceOver
one of three ways.
You can use the Apple Watch app
on the iPhone, the Settings app
on the Apple Watch, or
if you have it assigned
in the Apple Watch app,
an Accessibility shortcut.
This allows you to simply
triple-click the Crown
to turn VoiceOver on..
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver on.
Weather.
>> QASID SADIQ: To
demonstrate how VoiceOver works,
let's try to do something
with VoiceOver.
Let's try to find out what
time it is in New York.
Before anything else, we have
to get a sense of where we are
on screen, and a good
way of doing that is
by placing your finger on
screen and having VoiceOver read
out whatever is under
your finger.
I am going to go
ahead and do that.
>> VOICEOVER: Calendar.
Music. Maps.
Alarm.
>> QASID SADIQ: So now
I actually have a sense
of where I am on screen.
And I want to move through
these elements and get
to the World Clock app icon so
I can open that application.
Now, the way a VoiceOver user
moves through these elements is
by swiping right to move to the
next element or by swiping left
to move to the previous element.
So I am going to go
ahead and swipe right
until VoiceOver speaks
World Clock,
indicating that it is focused
on the World Clock app icon.
>> VOICEOVER: World clock.
World clock.
Stop -- world Clock.
>> QASID SADIQ: Now
VoiceOver spoke "World Clock."
That means I am focused
on World Clock.
Now to actually open the app I
need to activate the element,
and to activate the element,
I can double-tap
anywhere on screen.
So let's wait for this to load.
>> VOICEOVER: World Clock.
World Clock.
Back. Cupertino.
1:37 p.m. Today.
>> QASID SADIQ: Now, I want
to find out what time it is
in New York, and since
this is my Watch,
I know that New York is at
the bottom of this list,
so I can simply scroll
to the bottom.
The way a VoiceOver user scrolls
is by placing two fingers
on screen and scrolling
in the direction --
or flicking in the
direction of the scroll.
So I want to go ahead and do
that until I get to the bottom.
>> VOICEOVER: Rows 4 to 7.
Row 6 -- row 7.
New York. 4:38 p.m. Today.
Plus 3 hours.
>> QASID SADIQ: Now I know
what time it is in New York.
So that's VoiceOver.
Now let's go ahead
and look at Zoom.
To first things first, I
have to turn VoiceOver off,
and I can use my Accessibility
shortcut to turn it off
by triple-tapping the Crown.
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver off.
>> QASID SADIQ: And all the
Accessibility settings are
in Settings.
Accessibility.
Zoom. Now, I want
to read this text,
and it's actually a bit small,
so it seems like a good
place I can zoom in.
So to zoom in with Zoom,
you simply two-finger
double-tap on screen.
Now that I am zoomed
in, I actually want
to adjust the zoom level a bit.
To adjust the zoom level,
I simply two-finger
double-tap and scroll.
So that's perfect.
Now I have to move
the zoom focus
around so I can actually
read this text.
Now, I can use a two-finger
pan gesture, which is similar
to the iOS pan gesture in
Zoom to move this around,
but there is an issue with this.
It's a bit slow, and also
my fingers are in the way
of what I am trying to read.
Just for this problem, we have
actually utilized the Crown
to allow you to move
the zoom focus around.
If I rotate the Crown forward,
it takes me from left
to right, like so.
Once I hit the end of the line,
it takes me to the next line.
Similarly, if I rotate
it backwards,
it does the exact
reverse of that.
There you go.
That's Zoom.
Now, as you can see, the
Apple Watch is quite an
accessible device.
But for it to be
completely accessible,
it needs to have
accessible applications.
This is where you come in.
This is where you really
get to be the champions
of accessibility and the
champions of our VoiceOver users
by making your applications
accessible.
And the way you make your
applications accessible is
through our WatchKit
Accessibility API.
For the most part, this
is actually a relatively
simple task.
It involves setting a
couple of properties
on a few interface items.
Now, each interface item is a
subclass of WK Interface Object,
and this is exactly where you
annotate your accessibility
information to make these
interface items accessible.
You only need these two
core functions to make most
of your application accessible,
so let's go ahead and talk
about these, starting
with Existence.
Before anything else,
VoiceOver needs to know what is
and what is not an element.
Accessibility elements are those
things that you saw me swiping
through and touching in my demo.
Now, by default, our frameworks
give a lot of this to you,
things like buttons, labels,
and switches are all
accessibility elements.
But sometimes you might need
to get away from the default.
For example, if you
want to expose an image
which is not an accessibility
element,
that presents valuable
information to the user.
Or if you want to group together
a few accessibility elements
to make it easy for
your VoiceOver user
to navigate the screen.
Like we did here in
the Conversation group,
where we grouped together
those three labels
so that a VoiceOver user does
not have to swipe three times
to get past one Conversation.
You can set this
by passing a bool
into the function set
Is Accessibility Element
on an interface item.
The way a VoiceOver user
sees what's on screen is
by hearing a short
description of that element.
This short description is
called an accessibility label.
Now, just like Is
Accessibility Element,
a lot of this is
determined for you.
Accessibility infers a label
by doing things like looking
at the text contained inside an
interface item, but sometimes
that inferred label may be
misleading or nonexistent.
An example of that
is a Home screen,
where each of these app
icons are not associated
with any text.
In these particular situations,
you have to set the
Aaccessibility label yourself.
And the way you do that
is by passing a string
into the function,
et Accessibility Label,
on an interface item.
So now these apps will get you
90 percent of the way in terms
of making your application
accessible --
or these functions, sorry.
But to really complete your
accessibility experience,
you should try to use
these three functions too.
Let's talk about these.
Now, you might remember
VoiceOver saying certain things
like "button" or
"adjustable" or "not enabled."
What's actually happening
here is
that each accessibility
element is associated
with a set of traits.
These traits let
VoiceOver know how
to present an element
to the user.
An example of where we
use this was actually
on the Conversation group,
where we added the button trait
so that a VoiceOver
knows they can double-tap
and activate this element.
The way you set traits
is by passing a bit mask
into the function Set
Accessibility Traits
on an interface item.
Now, sometimes the label and the
traits are not enough to express
to the user exactly
what an element does.
For these particular
situations, it might be useful
to use an accessibility hint,
which is a string spoken
out after the label is spoken
that lets the user
know what they could do
when they are focused
on an element.
You can set an accessibility
hint by passing a string
into the function Set
Accessibility Hint
on an interface item.
Now, certain elements are
associated with a value,
which change quite often
throughout the lifecycle
of that element.
An example of this is the
Minute Picker and the Timer app,
where that value is the number
of minutes that's
currently selected.
For this particular situation,
we have something called
an Accessibility Value.
This is something that's spoken
out after the label is read out
or anytime the value changes.
You can set this
by passing a string
into the function Set
Accessibility Value
on an interface item.
So these are the core
accessibility functions.
Let's talk about something
a little bit more complex,
image regions.
Now, it's a common pattern
on the Watch to take a bunch
of information, put
that into an image,
and present that to a user.
An example of this is a
weather dial in the Weather app.
We can try to annotate an
accessibility label to this,
but it would be pretty hard
to actually express what's
happening in this image
with a few concise words.
As you can see, there are 11
conditions, each associated
with a time, and there's
a current temperature.
What we really need
here is the ability
to take the relevant regions,
carve them up into
separate regions,
and associate information
with them.
So for example, one
Condition icon is associated
with 1 a.m., partly cloudy.
You can do this through the
WK accessibility image region
object, where the
region is a CGRect frame,
and the information
is a string label.
You can take an array
of these objects,
pass them into the function
Set Accessibility Image Regions
on an interface item to present
them to a user as a series
of accessibility elements
that they can swipe
through and touch.
Finally, as you are designing
your accessibility application
user experience, you might
come across a situation
where you might need
to adjust the UI a bit
for your VoiceOver users.
And to do that, your
application needs
to know whether VoiceOver
is running or not.
So for this, we add a new API,
WK Accessibility is
VoiceOver running.
Let's see this in action.
So I created an application
which allows you
to order a sandwich
right off of your wrist,
and it's actually
pretty straightforward.
First thing you do is you
actually make your sandwich
by selecting the layers that
you want on your sandwich.
So I want to take some bread,
add some roast beef on top
of that, maybe I'll
have some lettuce,
and end it with some more bread.
And I can go back, see a visual
representation of my sandwich,
and then I can go
ahead and order.
So we want to see if this
application is actually
accessible to all of our users,
especially our VoiceOver users.
And a good way of
actually doing that is
by actually just
turning VoiceOver on
and trying the application out.
So let's turn VoiceOver on with
our Accessibility shortcut.
>> VOICEOVER: VoiceOver on.
Make sandwich.
Button.
>> QASID SADIQ: Okay.
So we have one issue right away.
We can see that this image
representation of our sandwich,
which presents us valuable
information in terms
of what our sandwich
actually is composed of,
is completely inaccessible, so
we should make this available
to our VoiceOver users.
>> VOICEOVER: Make sandwich.
Order. Button.
I button.
>> QASID SADIQ: Now,
although it's obvious to us
because we can see this is
an information button based
on the visual cues, a VoiceOver
user will only hear the letter
i, and it could be confusing
as to what this actually does.
We should add an
accessibility label to this
that speaks information.
Also, this button
looks a bit small.
If you can imagine, it
might be a bit difficult
for a VoiceOver user
to feel around
and find this information
button.
So for this, we should
actually make it larger
when VoiceOver is running.
Let's go ahead and see.
>> VOICEOVER: Make sandwich.
Make sandwich.
Tap what you want
in your sandwich.
One layer of, roast beef, 210 c.
Two layers of.
Button.
>> QASID SADIQ: The first issue
is VoiceOver is speaking 210 c,
and VoiceOver speaking
isn't necessarily limited
to the screen space
that our interface is.
We should make it
speak 210 calories.
Also, notice we have
to swipe it three times
to get past one layer.
If you can imagine I am
really hungry and want
to make my sandwich right
now, I don't want to have
to swipe three times
to get past one layer.
I have a large sandwich.
We are going to have to fix that
by grouping together each layer.
Let's go ahead and fix that.
So you can actually fix a lot of
your accessibility issues just
through the Storyboard.
So let's go ahead and tackle
the Make Sandwich screen first
and fix the grouping
of the elements
in the Make Sandwich screen
so a VoiceOver user only has
to swipe once per layer.
First things first, we
have to find the group
that contains these
three labels.
And that's here.
We can go over to the sidebar
and set "Accessibility Enabled."
This turns it into an
accessibility element
that a user -- additionally, we
should add a button trait to it
so a user knows they
can double-tap
and activate this element.
The other issue we had on this
screen was the calories label
was being spoken "210 c"
instead of "210 calories."
So let's go to wherever
the number
of calories are being
said, which is right here
on the Calories label.
Setting text to be the
number of calories and c.
Let's add a line to Set
Accessibility Label here too.
What we are doing here is
taking the calories label,
calling the function set
Accessibility Label on it,
and passing in a string,
which uses the number
of calories followed
by the string Calories.
So a user will hear "210
calories" instead of "210 c."
So we fixed the Make Sandwich
screen in terms of accessibility
and we want to test our changes.
We can build onto the Watch,
but that's going to take time
to build on the Watch for
every iterative change.
Instead, let's use
the Simulator.
I am going to run
this on the Simulator.
Now, to test accessibility
changes on the Simulator,
you have to use Accessibility
Inspector, and the way you turn
on the Accessibility Inspector
is by going to Settings,
General, Accessibility,
Accessibility Inspector.
This is a Simulator-only tool.
This allows you to inspect the
accessibility of your elements
by clicking on them, displaying
exactly what is contained inside
the element in this red box,
and also seeing descriptions
of that element, such
as label, hint, value,
and traits associated with it.
So this is awfully
useful when you are trying
to make an element accessible.
So let's go ahead and
see if our changes took.
Now with the Accessibility
Inspector,
clicking only selects
an element.
To activate an element,
you have to double-click.
Now, let's click this.
So let's notice a
few things here.
First of all, notice how the
whole layer is one element.
So now a VoiceOver user only has
to swipe once for each layer,
so they can make their
sandwich quicker and easier.
Also, notice how the Calories
label now speaks "210 calories,
" so it's much more clear
to the user what this
is actually saying.
And finally, it has a button
trait, so our user now knows
that they can double-tap
and activate this element.
So we fixed a screen.
Let's go ahead and fix
the starting screen
where we actually -- the
interface controller.
Now, the first issue
we had here was
that sandwich image
representation was not
accessible at all.
And that sandwich image
representation actually provided
a lot of information
to the user.
So it's a bit hard
to actually try
to just add an accessibility
label to that image
because we want to express
what layers are on there
and the order of those layers.
So this seems like a job for
accessibility image regions.
So let's first find out where
the sandwich image is set.
That's set over here, and
the image is generated here.
Let's generate the
image regions.
So I am going to add a function
to generate the image regions.
What this function is doing
is enumerating each layer,
creating an accessibility
image region, setting the label
of that image region to
be the name of the layer
or the sandwich layer,
and setting the frame
to be the frame used to
generate the original image.
Finally, we are adding it to
an array and returning that.
Let's go ahead and add this to
the header so we can call it
from the interface controller.
And then let's go
ahead and call it
from the interface controller.
So we are taking
the sandwich image,
we are calling Set Accessibility
Image Regions on it,
or the generated image regions.
Now, the second issue
we had here was
that the information button
only being spoken as "i."
Since the label doesn't change
at all throughout the lifecycle
of the information button,
we can simply set it
in the Storyboard.
Let's select that
information button.
Let's go ahead and set the
label to be "information."
Like so. Okay.
So now we fixed that label.
But the other issue we had
with the information button was
that it wasn't large
enough for a VoiceOver user
to easily feel on screen.
So we need to resize it based
on whether VoiceOver is running.
So I am going to add
a function to do that.
What this is doing is it checks
whether VoiceOver is running
with a WK Accessibility
Is VoiceOver Running call,
and if it is, it sets the
height and width to be 40.
Otherwise it sets it to be 20.
Now, we have to call this on
Will Activate, so this ...
And also, just in case someone
turns VoiceOver on while
on this screen, we should
go ahead and register
for the notification and
have it call this function.
Notification is WK accessibility
VoiceOver status changed.
Now, let's see our fixed
application in action.
>> VOICEOVER: Eats.
Eats fixed.
Make sandwich.
Button.
>> QASID SADIQ: Right away,
we can see that that information
button is already larger.
>> VOICEOVER: Information
button.
>> QASID SADIQ: And the label
is being spoken correctly.
So let's go ahead and
make our sandwich.
>> VOICEOVER: Make sandwich.
Button. Tap what you
want in your sandwich.
Roast beef, 210 calories.
Button. One layer of roast beef.
Bread, 130 calories.
One layer of bread.
One layer of roast
beef, 210 calories.
Button.
>> QASID SADIQ: Okay.
So right away you can see the
calories label is being spoken
correctly, and that's a
lot more clear to the user.
Also, each layer is
a separate element,
making navigation
significantly better.
Now let's go ahead and look
at our image representation
of our sandwich and see
how accessible that is.
>> VOICEOVER: Make sandwich.
Roast beef.
Image. Bread.
Image.
>> QASID SADIQ: Now,
our VoiceOver user can literally
swipe through their sandwich.
So there you go.
>> VOICEOVER: Home.
[Applause]
>> QASID SADIQ: Now, as you
guys know, you, as developers,
now have the ability to
make your own custom clock
face Complications.
And just like your applications,
these need to be accessible too.
Now, our frameworks can
determine an accessibility label
for most complications, but
there are a couple situations
where that accessibility
label may be misrepresentative
or nonexistent.
You see, each clock face
Complication is composed
of a set of image and text
providers, and although most
of these providers have very
obvious accessibility labels
associated with them,
a couple don't.
Image provider and
Simple Text provider.
So for these two
particular providers,
we've added a property,
Accessibility Label.
This works just like the
accessibility label does
on a normal WatchKit
application,
and it's actually pretty easy.
So I made a complication to
make it really easy for you
to order a sandwich, just in
case you are really hungry
that you don't have time
to open the application.
You simply want to
lift your wrist
and get a sandwich right now.
So this is the Complication
right here.
And since it's an image,
it has no accessibility
label associated with it.
So let's go ahead and actually
set an accessibility label
on it.
So we go to wherever the
Complication is created,
or the provider is created.
And we set an accessibility
label.
And there you go.
It's that easy.
So let's see how a
VoiceOver user will hear this.
>> VOICEOVER: Get sandwich now.
>> QASID SADIQ: So
if you couldn't hear,
the label spoke "get
a sandwich now,"
so now our VoiceOver
users have the ability
to order a sandwich
on a double-tap.
So as you can see, it's
actually really quite easy
to make your applications
and Complications accessible.
Let's talk about a few things
you should keep in mind
when you are designing your
accessibility experience.
First of all, try to make
your images accessible.
Especially if they provide
valuable information
to the user.
You should set an
accessibility label on them.
Or, if they are providing a
very complex set of information,
use the accessibility
image regions API.
When you design your
application,
think about how a
VoiceOver user is going
to navigate your screen.
You don't want to make it
so a VoiceOver user has
to swipe several times to
get past one logical item.
So group your accessibility
elements together by using Set
As Accessibility Element.
Now, this is probably true for
non-VoiceOver users as well,
but you should avoid
tiny interface items.
It's difficult for a
VoiceOver user to feel
and find a tiny interface
item on screen.
Finally, most importantly,
try accessibility
on your application.
See what your application looks
like with increased text size.
Or, see how your application
works with VoiceOver on.
You might be surprised
at what you find.
In conclusion, the Apple Watch
is quite an accessible device.
But for it to be
completely accessible,
it needs to have
accessible apps.
This is where you guys really
get to be the champions
of our VoiceOver users.
And as you guys just saw, this
is actually a pretty easy task.
So let's empower all of our
users to do those amazing things
that our applications let us
do, regardless of who they are
or how they are interact
with the world.
Thank you for your time.
You can actually
get more information
on the WatchKit Programming
Guide.
You can ask questions
on the Developer forums,
or contact your Evangelist,
Paul Marcos.
Thank you for your time.
I appreciate it.
[Applause]