[Applause]
>> NATHAN DEVRIES:
Good morning, everyone.
My name is Nathan deVries,
and shortly you'll meet
my colleague Chloe Chang.
We are here to present
WatchKit in depth part 2.
In the previous session, part 1,
we talked about the
architectural differences
between watchOS 1 and watchOS 2
and how it relates
to your applications.
In this talk we will be
looking a little bit more
into the new APIs enabled
by this new architectural
change bringing your watch app
and extension to the watch.
Now, to start with, I will
be talking a little bit
about something that's
pretty exciting.
We are enabling Digital Crown
experiences in your own apps
so this will be great.
Next, we will be
talking a little bit
about media playback both for
short video and audio content
as well as long form
music, podcasts,
et cetera, in the background.
This is also a great new API.
Next, we will be talking
about audio recording.
You can now record audio
straight from your wrist
and send the short clips of
audio to friends, to a server,
share them on the
internet, and so on.
And lastly, we're going
to be talking a little bit
about storing sensitive
data on the watch.
Now that your watch is
fully responsible for all
of the data it shows,
it's important to keep
in mind the sensitive
data you might be storing.
So let's get started.
The Digital Crown is a brand
new user input mechanism
that allows you to fluidly and
very tactilely scroll through
and pick elements on the
screen using the Digital Crown.
It's a really fantastic way
to interact with the device.
Let's take a look at some
of the core interactions
that are enabled by
the Digital Crown.
To start with, the one that
you will be most familiar
with is, of course, scrolling.
Place your finger on the Crown,
turn slowly to scroll slowly
or flick quickly to
scroll with momentum.
It's a really natural
experience.
It feels like when we did
Multi-Touch scrolling.
Next, you can use the Digital
Crown to choose options.
This is a similar
picker style to S iOS,
but on the watch you can
use the Digital Crown.
Here I'm selecting my age
in the activity set up UI
where I have a sheet that shows
three different pickers allowing
me to have a concise and precise
UI for choosing my age all
in a single modal sheet.
Next, we have a different way
of presenting option picking.
In many cases, the options
that you are choosing have a
more special or specific way
of presenting the data.
In this case, I'm setting
a timer of 45 minutes,
so we think that setting
time it makes sense to lay
out the information in a
way that's specific to time.
In this case, it's
a 60 second dial,
so turning the Crown shows you
progress as you are rotating
through each of those minutes.
In each of your applications,
you will need to find ways
to present the options that
you are presenting to the user
in ways that are
relevant to the data.
So keep this in mind.
Lastly, because the Crown
provides smooth, precise
and continuous movement, here
we can use the Crown to rotate
through continuous
values like volume
in the now playing glance.
So these are a few of the
core interactions enabled
by the Crown, and we are excited
to be able to provide those
to your application too.
So stepping back a little bit
from the core interactions,
what are some of the
benefits of the Digital Crown?
Well, we believe that the
Digital Crown is an incredibly
intuitive experience when you
first put on an Apple Watch,
the first thing you reach
for is the Digital Crown.
People love to play with it,
and it's a very natural way
to interact with
content on the screen.
Next, and very importantly,
it keeps the UI visible,
by not obstructing the
screen with your finger,
you can see what you
are interacting with.
So exposing different
interactions using the Digital
Crown allows your users to
clearly navigate the system.
Thirdly, it's a very
precise input mechanism.
If we look back at
the timer example,
you can't imagine trying to
tune between 0 and 60 minutes
of a timer using touch alone.
With the Crown you can
very precisely tune a 2,
3 or 4-minute timer
or zip through
and create a 60-minute
timer very quickly,
just with a few flicks
of the Digital Crown.
Finally it's a playful.
This is a fun experience.
It's very tactile and we think
the users are going to love it.
So what are we exposing
in watchOS 2?
This one you will be
very familiar with.
It's the same style of
picker that we use elsewhere
in the system, like in
complication editing
and activity setup.
We call this the WKInterface
picker, and it's available
in watchOS 2 applications.
We have the list style.
This is great for
selecting a range of options
where the options
are showing in text,
in a list with a little bit of
context to either side to show
where you are in the selection.
Next, we have the stack style.
Now, the stack style is perfect
if you have a very visual,
graphical way of
presenting your data.
It could be photographs,
it could be stickers
in a messaging application.
This is really great if you want
to show in place presentations
of your data that you can turn
through using the Digital
Crown like a flip book.
And finally, we have the
sequence style picker.
Now, this picker is really cool.
I'm excited to see
what you are going
to be able to do with this guy.
Here, I have used it to create
an emoji picking interface.
So if you turn the
Digital Crown,
we cycle through
different emotions.
This can also be used to
create your own sliders, knobs,
meters and even games if
you get creative enough.
So that's the sequence style.
The three styles are
list, stack and sequence.
Let's talk a little bit about
what we call focus styles.
In addition to the three
visual styles of pickers,
each of these styles also
supports focus styles.
What does that mean?
So here we have an example
of another emoji picking UI
where we have the opportunity to
choose both a face and a hand.
It's not immediately obvious
what turning the Crown would do
in this case.
It's not even obvious that there
are two pickers on the screen.
What we can do is change
the default focus style
of these two pickers
to an outline style.
What this does is it
outlines the picker
to show it's an interactive
element,
and it also clearly shows
in the system green color
that the selected or
focused element is editable
with the Digital Crown.
Now, when I tap the
other item on the screen,
I see the focus outline changes,
and I know what turning
the Digital Crown will do.
There's an additional level
of control that you have
over the focus outline.
If the items in your picker need
more context to describe what's
in them, we can use an outline
with caption focus style.
This allows you to
build a UI similar
to the complication
editing UI where you want
to show a little breakout box
that clearly shows
what the item is
that you currently
have selected.
And, again, if I
move to the other,
move focus to the other
picker, you will note
that the caption
also moves with it.
The way that I have achieved
this here is I have each item
in my picker with
the same caption,
but you could also have
a different caption
for each item in the picker.
Now, there are other useful ways
to provide context while
the user is interacting
with the Digital Crown.
One of these is the system style
of showing a contextual
indicator,
the Digital Crown indicator.
This is shown beside
the Digital Crown
and as the user turns the
Digital Crown it gives them
context on the range of values
available to them for picking.
It also shows how far through
the values they currently are.
So it's good for getting your
bearings when you have a picker
that doesn't necessarily show
where you are in the options,
just through the visuals itself.
For applications that want
to show a more customized
progress UI, they don't want
to show the little
Crown indicator,
we have fantastic new ways for
you to build those experiences.
It's best to show
with an example.
In this case, I have a picker
in the center of the screen
which allows me to tune
between 0 and 100%.
So as I turn the Digital Crown,
you will see the values tick
up in increments of 10%.
This is kind of cool,
but we don't know
that the bottom limit is 0
and the upper limit is 100.
It's not a very visual
experience.
It's not a pleasant experience.
We could use the
contextual indicator,
but in our app we would like to
show progress using a slightly
different UI that is more
relevant to your application.
Here, I have chosen to use an
arc or a progress ring style UI.
So as I turn the Digital Crown,
I have coordinated the picker
with another interface element
in my UI so it updates the image
as I turn through
the picker's items.
With this coordinated image
API, you can build all sorts
of fantastic Digital
Crown experiences.
So there are all the different
knobs and bells and whistles
that you can configure
on a WK interface picker,
how you create one.
Let's jump into looking
at that right now.
So those of you that are
familiar with watchOS 1,
this is a very straight
forward process.
If you go to your storyboard and
select an interface controller,
you can simply drag a new
picker object straight
from the objects library
into your storyboard.
Once you have a picker, you
can obviously configure its
various attributes.
We have already been speaking
about these such as the style,
list, sequence or stack.
The focus style and
whether or not you would
like that optional Digital
Crown indicator to be shown.
In this case, I'm
using the list style,
the outline with caption style,
and a disabled indicator,
because I'm going to provide
my own, or I don't feel
like the context is necessary
with the data that
I'm presenting.
Next, we need to jump into
the interface controller code,
and we need to create an
IB outlet for the picker
so we can hook up our code and
the object in the storyboard.
This gives us a reference
to the picker.
And finally, we jump
back to the storyboard
and hook these two things up.
So there are just a few
simple steps similar
to creating buttons
and images and so
on with the picker
very easy to create.
So now we have a picker,
and we have hooked it up,
and we have build and run
and this is what we get.
It's possibly the most
useless picker in the world.
Turn the Digital Crown and
you can quickly navigate
through nothing.
It's great!
So what we need to do is
configure what we call items
as you can see from the title.
To do that, now that we have
a reference to the picker
through the IB outlet, we can
simply call the set items API
and specify an array
of WKPickerItems.
These are the very
simple objects
with a few optional properties.
Here I'm using the title
property, the caption property
and the accessory property
to define the visual style
that I'm presenting
on the watch.
Now, if I want to have full
control over what's shown
in each row of the picker,
I can also use the content
image property of each
of these different
WKPickerItems.
This gives me full
control over what's shown
for each item in the picker.
For the stack and
sequence styles,
the content image is used
to define what's shown
in those two pickers.
So for those two styles,
you will just use the
content image property.
So new in watchOS
2 we have a new API
for specifying images you would
like to be shown in your UI
for pickers and for
a few other objects
which you will see later.
This is called the
WK image class.
And I will give a few examples
of how you might use this class.
The most common example will be
that you have your
images included
in the application already
in your asset catalog
or in the bundle itself, and
so you can use the WK image,
image name API to
load those images
into the application
just prior to display.
All the extension needs to do is
specify the name of the image.
For cases where your extension
has downloaded the image
from the internet or from
the companion using watch
connectivity, instead of
turning that image and turning
that image data into an image,
you can save the necessary
overhead of decoding the image
in the extension and pass the
image data into the application
where it will be converted into
an image just prior to display.
These first two ways of creating
images are the preferred way
if you already have
the imimage data.
There is no sense in creating
UI images unnecessarily
in your extension
because they are displayed
by the application.
The last case is where
you do need UI images.
Now that core graphics available
on the watch, you can use it
to render custom effects
into images to use
in your WKPickerItems.
So here I'm using the
WK image image API,
which takes a UI image object.
Now, we have a picker
configured with items
and turning the Digital Crown
will move through those items,
but it's useful in your
application to know
when the selected item
changes, and to do this,
we use a similar technique to a
button or a slider or a switch
by hooking up an IB action.
Now, the IB action for pickers
in particular is a method
that takes a single argument,
which is an integer representing
the index of the selected item
in your items array that you
specified using set items.
So in this case, I am indexing
into my picker items using the
selected index provided to me,
and I'm printing the
title of that picker item.
So really easy to handle
selected item and changes.
One thing to note is
that you don't want
to do particularly
expensive work
in response to item changes.
As you saw in the core
interaction section,
you can turn the Crown quickly
to move through items quickly
so your picker action is going
to be called very rapidly.
If you are doing very expensive
things I suggest you hold off
until you haven't received
a picker action call
in a little bit of time, and
then you do the expensive work
like refreshing your
table view and so on.
Next we have image coordination.
This is what allows you
to build those custom,
beautiful interactions
where many parts
of your interface
are coordinated
with the picker as
its value changes.
This is also very
simple to set up.
In this case, I have a picker
in the center of the screen
which shows 70%, and the
outline, the progress ring,
is a WKInterfaceGroup which
is the parent of the picker.
Very easy, very simple
UI to set up.
Now, to configure this in code,
all we need to do is create
a set of animated images
which will be managed
by the picker.
So here we create a
progress images variable
and use the UI animated
image with images API
to specify an array of those
progress images we have either
drawn in code or we already
have in our asset catalog.
We will give it a duration of 0
because the picker will
automatically manage seeking
through this animation,
and then finally
on the progress interface group,
which is hosting
the progress ring,
we will call set
background image
to make the animated image
the background image.
Finally we call set
coordinated animations
on the picker giving
it a list of all
of the different interface
objects that we would
like the picker to coordinate
as you turn through the picker.
In this case, we only
have a single group,
but we could also
specify multiple groups,
a group in an image, and so on.
This supports as many
objects as you like.
Now, as I turn through the
WK interface picker's items,
we coordinate with any
associated groups and images
which image is shown in that
particular interface object.
In this example, I have matched
the number of items to images,
but I will show you
in a little bit
that that doesn't necessarily
need to be the case.
So that's how you coordinate
images with a picker.
Now, to finish things
off for this section,
I thought I would give
you a little demo of how
to do this in your application.
So let me just get that set up.
So here is a little app
that I created earlier.
It shows each of the
different styles of picker
that you can create as
well as the last one
for a demonstration
of coordination.
So let's start by going
to the list style picker.
In this particular case,
I have created a picker
with accessory images drawn
as random colors using core
graphics and I have quite a few,
quite a few items here.
You can see it's very fluid
to scroll through these items.
Everyone time the item changes
I'm also updating a separate
interface element
in my storyboard.
This is a simple label,
and I'm updating the text.
So these kinds of things are
very possible to do in response
to selected item changes.
It's really only more expensive
things that you want to defer.
So let's go back to
the top level menu
and into the stack style.
Here I'm also using
core graphics
to render random
squares of random color,
and here you will see that I can
very smoothly and quickly flick
through images in this
stack style picker.
Also note that in the
upper right-hand corner
as I turn the Digital
Crown, you will see
that the Digital Crown
indicator shows my progress
through this stack of items.
It's really useful.
The third example
is a sequence style.
I thought I would show the kinds
of things you could achieve
with the sequence style
because the emoji case was kind
of obvious what you
could do with that.
Here I can create a pretty
compelling experience
for choosing a random
color using a color wheel.
Here as I turn the
Digital Crown,
I'm selecting different images
in the sequence representing
a new color.
So this is pretty cool, and also
note that this supports momentum
so I can still flick on
the Crown and it will move
through the values very quickly.
Finally, let's talk a little
bit about coordination.
I have created an example here
with a left and a right picker
where I have got the
left picker focused.
As I turn the Digital Crown,
I'm moving through 12 options
on the left-hand side.
If I focus the right
hand picker,
now I'm moving through 60 items.
You can see that this is
maybe an approximation
of the timer UI.
So one thing to note is
that both pickers share
the same coordinated image.
So my coordinated image includes
60 different progress arcs
for this right hand picker, but
my left hand picker can also use
that same progress image.
This is a really handy
technique to use if you want
to save the number of
resources you are using
between your pickers.
So that's the demo.
[Applause]
So just to recap some of
the things you have learned
about the Digital Crown, the new
experiences you can use provide
to your users in watchOS 2,
we have three brand new
customizable styles, the list,
the stack and the sequence.
Each one is tailored to
displaying different types
of information, so you should
choose which one you use based
on what your users are
interacting with in your apps.
Each of these styles supports
focus and indicator support
so as you are turning through
the items in the picker,
we both show you what the Crown
would do by showing focus,
and we also provide support
for showing the standard
Digital Crown indicator.
And finally, for
creating truly customized,
compelling interfaces with
very tailored graphics,
you can use the image
animation coordination APIs
to synchronize other aspects of
your interface with the pickers
that are currently being edited.
And with that, I would like to
hand off to Chloe who will talk
about media play
back on watchOS 2.
Thank you very much!
[Applause]
>> CHLOE CHANG: Hi, everyone!
I'm here to talk about more
new features in watchOS 2.
The first one is media playback.
So let me show you what it looks
like to play a simple video
in the new media
player in watchOS 2.
First, the content
is loaded and,
once the user presses the play
iCon, it will start to play.
And at any point in time the
user can turn the Digital Crown
to adjust the volume and also
if you tap on the screen,
the player control will come up.
And for audio only content,
we also have a built
in UI for that.
The audio for both
cases will be routed
to the selected output source.
That could be your
Apple Watch speaker
or a paired bluetooth device.
Now, let me show you
how to do this in code.
Let's say you are trying to
present this media player
from your interface controller.
The first thing you
do is to figure
out the URL for the content.
Suppose you have a simple movie
from your extension bundle.
This is how you come up with
the URL for the content.
You can also use remote URL.
In that case, the media player
would handle the download
for you.
And also, it would update the
UI with a progress indication.
And with the URL, we can
then decide how we are going
to play the content.
We offer a few options here.
The first one is auto play.
When it's set to true, once
the media player is on screen
and the content is loaded,
the playback will
automatically start.
The next one I use
is start time.
I make it to start at the
3 second mark of the video.
This is really useful if the
playback was previously paused
and when user comes back
to the media player,
you want to resume the
playback from the same spot.
And the third option
here I use video gravity.
This key actually determines how
the video will be resized once
it's in the media player.
And with all of this
information,
now you can call present
media controller with URL.
And you can specify
completion handler.
It will tell you how
the playback ended.
And that's how easy you
can present a media player
from your code.
And in some other
cases, for example,
in the social media app, you
want to embed a snippet of video
in some kind of context.
We have the object
that you need.
In watchOS 2, now you have
the WKInterface movie object
that you can insert into a UI.
This object has a player icon
overlaying a poster image
that represents your content.
Once user taps on the play icon,
the media player I showed you
at the beginning shows
up here automatically.
You don't have to write
any code to do that.
So let me show you how
to do that in Xcode.
In the new Xcode, you will
find this movie object
in your object library.
You can drag and drop
it into your storyboard,
and you can use the
attribute inspector
to customize this movie object.
You can specify the video
gravity, or the poster image.
You can also do this
in code if you want
to dynamically configure this.
Suppose in your code you
have member variables
for the content, and
you have the URL for it,
and the poster image that
represents the movie.
And you drag the IB outlet
from the interface builder
and that represents the movie
object that you are using.
And once you want to update
your UI or your content has
to change, you can
use this method
to configure your movie object.
And because the -- is so
different on Apple Watch
than other iOS devices, we have
a few specific media formats you
should use for any
content you are trying
to play on Apple Watch.
If your content works
best in full screen mode,
then the recommended
resolution is 208 by 260.
If your content actually works
best in a 16:9 aspect ratio,
the recommended resolution
is 320 by 180.
If you follow this
set of media specs,
you can expect the best result
for your playback feature.
That's how easy you can play
audio and video in your app.
The next feature I want to talk
about is called long
form audio playback.
The features I showed you so
far present some UI for you
and once the UI is dismissed,
the playback will stop.
Long form audio is different.
It doesn't come with any
built in UI for your app.
That means you can
create your own,
and once your own
UI is dismissed,
the playback can actually
continue in the background.
A common use case for this is
a podcast app or a music app.
The user might be listening to
the audio tracks while he is
out for a run or
doing a commute.
The audio for this feature
would be routed only
to the paired bluetooth device.
And the playback
status would be updated
in the now playing glance.
So it's very convenient for the
user to control the playback.
Now, let me show you the API.
If you are familiar
with AV foundation APIs,
you will think these
are very familiar.
Let's say you have the URL
for the audio you
are trying to play.
You can create an
asset like this.
With this asset you can create
the audio file player item.
The player item has
the presentation status
for the asset.
And you can use KVO
to observe the status.
Just like with AV
foundation APIs.
And with the player item,
you can create a player
and call play to play it.
Super simple!
For the example I
mentioned, a podcast app,
you can create a list of items
that you are trying to play,
and if you want to provide user
a gapless listening experience,
instead of using
audio file player,
just use audio file
Queue player,
and that will give you
exactly what you want.
Just like on other iOS devices,
if you want to create
background mode playback,
you need to enable it
in the apps info list
just like this in Xcode.
Super simple!
Now, I would like to take
a couple of moments to talk
about where you should store all
of this media data in your app.
As you know now, your app on
Apple Watch has two components.
One is the app, the
other is the extension,
and when it's installed,
the extension bundle sits
inside the app bundle.
Each component has a container
for storing dynamic data,
and each container
can only be accessed
by the individual component.
So let's say you have a static
image that you want to use
in your app, and you
want to use WK image,
image named to reference
it, you should put it
in an asset catalog
in the app bundle.
If you have other
resources, for example,
audio or video playback, and
the image data that you want
to directly manipulate in
your code, you should put it
in the extension bundle, so that
you can create the URL for them.
Now, in other cases, if you
want to have dynamic content
for playback, you can either
use watch connectivity
to grab those content
from the iPhone,
or you can download your
content from the internet
by using NSURL session.
For these contents,
you cannot put them
in either container I show you
here because they won't be able
to be accessed by both
the app and the extension.
So what you need to do
is create an app group,
which provides a
shared container for you
to store these data and they
can be accessed by both.
So that's all you need to know,
and if you want to learn more
about app group, please take
a look at this documentation.
The next feature I want to
talk about is audio recording.
Let's take a look at the UI,
and see how it works in action.
Once the user presses
the record button,
the recording will start, and
the wave form will be updated.
You can do this with
just one function call.
In your interface
controller sub class,
you can just call present
audio recording controller
with output URL and
specify the URL.
Now, you know this URL will
point to the shared container.
And then you decide a preset.
I will talk about
preset in a few seconds.
And then you can specify
the maximum duration
for this recording.
It's really useful if you
want to control the file size.
Right now, I set
it to 60 seconds.
And you can also customize
the action title which shows
up on the upper right-hand
corner of the UI.
Suppose your app
provides a feature
to send this recording output
to another person, customize it
to say 'send' would
be appropriate.
Otherwise, the default
will say 'done.'
You can also specify
completion handler.
It will tell you if
the content gets saved
and if there is any error.
Let's go back to the URL.
The URL has the file
name, and the extension
of the file name actually
determines what codec we are
going to use for
generating the output.
These are the file types
we supported, MP4 and 4A.
They will use AAC codec and
wave will use PCM codec.
We support three
different presets.
Each of them has different
sample rate and based
on the codec you choose,
the output bit rate
will be different.
As you expect, the higher
the quality the output,
the output file will be larger.
So it depends on your use case.
So if you are recording
for a voice memo case,
the narrow band speech
preset will be ideal for you.
If you are trying to record
something with higher quality,
maybe for post processing
purpose, then you might want
to consider high
quality audio preset.
With these presets,
audio recording becomes really
straight forward and easy
to customize for your feature.
Next I would like to
talk about security.
In watchOS 2 you can
now use key chains
to store your user's
sensitive data.
You can make those
data only accessible
when the device is unlocked.
Apple Watch is unlocked when
user enters the correct password
on the Apple Watch when the
device is on the user's wrist.
And then the data always
becomes available to you
until the user takes the
watch off their wrist.
This is really useful if you
are creating a complication
for the watch face.
And in the complication you
might be showing some user data
which is sensitive.
And so this is really important
to protect those
data with key chains.
And one thing I want
you to bear in mind is
that the key chains you create
on Apple Watch do not
participate in key chain sync.
They are not icon key chains
even though the usage is exactly
the same as other platform.
This is an example of
creating a key chain
to store user credentials.
Suppose you have a secret
password and you want
to store it, make
it only accessible
when the device is unlocked,
you can do something like this.
And call item add to
add these tributes.
So you would create a key chain.
To summarize our talk
today, at the beginning,
you heard Nathan introduce you
to a few new styles of pickers.
Each of them can be controlled
by a Digital Crown
that's really fun to use.
Then you heard me talk
about media player for audio
and video, and you can
also play long form audio
in the background.
For audio recording,
now you can do this
in just a couple
of lines of code.
And finally, in watchOS
2 you can use keychain
to protect your user data.
If you need more information,
take a look at this slide.
There is documentation in
sample code that you want
to reference to, and there are a
few related sessions throughout
this week you can attend
in person or take a look
at the video recording.
Thank you for listening!
[Applause]