[Applause]
>> ANUSH NADATHUR: Thank you.
Hello, everybody.
Good afternoon.
Welcome. Thanks for coming.
My name is Anush Nadathur
and I'm a software
engineer on HomeKit.
Today, my colleague Naveen
and I are going to talk
about what's new in
HomeKit for iOS 9.
Now for the past few years
we have seen a proliferation
of home devices in the market.
What this gives you is
a tremendous opportunity
to influence the experience
people have when interacting
with these devices in the
comfort of their own home.
Apple introduced HomeKit in iOS
8 so that we can work together
to bring home automation
to a much wider audience
than in the past, and to deliver
a consistent user experience
for our customers.
We had a great session last
year, but for those of you
who may have not seen
it, here's a brief recap.
HomeKit provides
a common protocol
that all HomeKit-enabled
accesses implement
and interact with iOS.
On this protocol, we
have defined profiles
that describe many of the
commonly used accessories.
However, we also
made it flexible
so that you can define profiles
that define custom features
of your accessory and
still be HomeKit-enabled.
One of the key features
in HomeKit is
to provide a common
view of the home
across all HomeKit applications.
So what that means is if you
use app A and switch to app B,
both get the same home data.
This is critical
for our customers
because that delivers the
consistent user experience
that we want them to have.
If your accessory implements one
of the Apple-defined profiles,
Siri works right out of the box.
Yeah. And the HomeKit framework
on iOS models a home
very naturally.
So we have objects which
describe rooms, zones,
which are a collection
of rooms, and of course,
accesses that you can control.
Now, none of this would
matter to our customers
if their data is not
private or secure.
HomeKit was designed
with privacy and security
from the very beginning.
All communication between iOS
and the HomeKit accessories
is end-to-end encrypted,
and we never use keys
across different sessions.
So when you have a key, that key
cannot be used to dig up data
in the past or in the future.
And all home data is encrypted
on the device using keys
that are local to that device.
So your data is completely
private and secure.
So that's HomeKit in iOS 8.
So let's talk about what we
have in store for you today.
I'm going to go over features
and enhancements for HomeKit
in iOS 9, and Naveen
will go over updates
in our accessories space.
So let's get right to it.
We've got some great
features for HomeKit in iOS 9,
but we have also added
enhancements based on feedback
that we have received from
developers in the past year.
So please keep those
feedback coming.
We absolutely love them.
So let's begin with a
small change that we made
but has a tremendous impact
on your daily development.
Let's take an example
of a light in a bedroom
and we move it to
the living room.
In iOS 8, if your app
comes to the foreground,
we would have notified your app
of this change using home
manager did update homes
delegate callback.
Now, this tells you
something has changed
but also gives you a new set of
objects that now you have to use
and figure out what exactly
has changed in your home.
We thought we should do better,
so in iOS 9, HomeKit is going
to maintain your objects
and only update properties
that have actually changed.
[Applause] Thank you.
So what that means is, in
our example, you're going
to get a single delegate
callback:
home did update room
[unintelligible].
I think this is going to
simplify your code base
and let you focus on your
features for your app.
That's not the only
enhancement that we have added.
Let's talk about another
one using an example.
Let's say I have a living
room, and I have a photo
of the living room that I
want to show in the app.
So what that means is you
need to be able to associate
and find a HomeKit
object representing a room
across relaunches of your app.
Now, a room in HomeKit
is represented using a
HMRoom class.
This has a name property,
and names are not immutable.
So any HomeKit app
can change this.
To solve our problem, we need
something more persistent.
So in iOS 9, we are introducing
persistent identifiers
across all relevant
HomeKit classes.
[Applause]
Thank you.
So you are going to have a
unique identifier property
on these classes.
These are unique applications,
and now you can use this
to associate context data
in your app and apply that
and associate that with
the HomeKit object.
Next I want to talk about
user management in iOS 8.
Your app had the following three
APIs to let users manage people
in their homes so they can
add users, remove users,
and list users in their homes.
In iOS 9, we are deprecating
these and replacing it
with a much simpler API, manage
users with completion handler.
So this API presents a full
view controller that is going
to let users manage
people in their homes.
Developers need to move
to this new API in iOS 9
so that our customers can
get a much richer experience
with respect to home sharing.
I want to stay on a related
topic, user capabilities.
When you share your
home with a user,
they can control the
accessories in the home,
but they cannot make any
configuration changes.
For a good user experience, your
app needs to show capabilities
that are only relevant
to that user.
To achieve this, you now need
to know the privilege
level of that user.
So, for example, if they
are not an administrator,
you should not let them
edit the name of a room.
So we are going to give you
APIs to let you figure this out.
So on HMHome, we are adding
a new property, current user.
That represents the currently
signed-in user on that device.
You can use this and pass along
to a new method on HMHome,
home access control for user.
That returns a HMHome
access control object,
which encapsulates the
privileges of that user.
Let's see what this
class looks like.
It has an administrative
property that will be set
if you are the administrator
of the home.
So now you can update your
apps and use this property
and share only relevant
features for that user.
Moving on, let's talk about a
great feature in iOS 8, scenes.
Now scenes allow our customers
to control multiple accesses
with a single command.
So I can have a good night
scene where it switches out all
of the lights, secures my
home, and sets the temperature
down to a comfortable level
with a single command.
This is a very powerful feature.
In iOS 9 we want our customers
to use this even more.
To help this, we are
introducing predefined scenes.
There are four common events
that most people
experience every day.
They are getting up, you
leave home, you return home,
and then you go to bed.
Now that you know what these
four predefined scenes mean,
you can apply context to them.
So in your app, you can
actually make suggestions
to let customers configure
these four predefined scenes
with meaningful actions.
And to have a good
experience for our customers,
predefined scenes cannot
be deleted from a home.
Let's walk through the APIs.
A scene in HomeKit is
represented using a HM action
set object.
We have added a new
property, action set type,
that describes the kind of scene
that you are working
with in your app.
We have four constants
that correspond
to the four predefined scenes
I talked about earlier.
We also have a fifth type,
the user defined type,
and this is set on the
scene that your app creates.
How do I access these
predefined scenes in a home?
They are automatically
populated for you as part
of the action set property
on an HMHome class.
But we also have
a convenience API,
built-in action set of type.
That takes the action set type
and returns a HM action set
object that corresponds to one
of your predefined scenes.
So that's the APIs, but we want
to make scenes even much
easier for our customers.
So now Siri works even
better with scenes in iOS 9.
Siri now recognizes
the names of all scenes
and simply speaking the name
of the scene will
actually execute it.
This is a great way for our
customers to use scenes.
Now let's talk about
the experience
of adding an accessory
to your home.
Let's say I have two accessories
from the same manufacturer,
and they can have the name
of the manufacturer as part
of the accessory's name
and a model number,
and when I add this accessory
to the home, I can always look
up the packaging and figuring
out I am adding the
right device to my home.
But a better user experience
for our customers is
to give some kind of indication
that provides more
information about the accessory.
Let's say, for example, we
can give them visual clues,
present an icon that
tells them the type
of accessory they are adding
is a much better experience.
To attain this feature,
we are adding accessory
categories in iOS 9.
This information is available
to your app during
setup of that accessory.
So when you browse and you
are finding these accessories,
it is already available for you.
And it specifies the primary
category of that accessory.
Moving on to the APIs for this,
we are introducing a new class,
HM accessory category.
This has a property category
type that gives more information
about that category,
so, in our example,
you will have category
type light bulb
and category type fan.
And the way you access this
category is use the category
property on an HM accessory.
So this is available when you
browse for these accessories.
So we recommend that you use
this new feature and enhance
that user experience
for our customers during
first-time setup.
Now let's talk about
HomeKit and the Apple Watch.
[Applause]
Yeah. As announced
in Monday's keynote,
HomeKit is now available
on Watch OS.
Now, this means you can
now go out for a run
without your iPhone, come back,
and if you have your watch
with you, you will be able
to unlock your door
and get back in.
How cool is that?
[Applause]
All your home data is
mirrored from your iOS device
onto the watch, so you can
make changes on your phone
and they will automatically
synch to the watch.
You can view homes from the
watch, control your accessories,
and execute all your scenes.
We cannot wait to see the
creative experience you are
going to deliver
to our customers
with HomeKit on the Apple Watch.
Finally, I want to talk
about a new feature in iOS 9,
and I am really excited about it
because I spent a
lot of time on it.
[Laughter] Let's
talk about triggers.
Now, in iOS 8, we
have timer triggers,
so that lets you execute scenes
that specify time of the day.
I can have an evening scene that
executes at 7 p.m. every day.
But what if I could do
something like this.
I return home, I
unlock my front door,
now that generates an event.
Let's say it's before 6 p.m.
and I have a motion
sensor that's right next
to my front door.
That gets activated
and detects motion.
If I have an arrive home scene,
I want that to be
automatically executed.
And your home is ready
and welcoming you.
I'm happy to say
you can now do this
in iOS 9 with event triggers.
One or more events
activate a trigger.
Let's talk about what
kind of events we support.
We have events corresponding
to the state of an accessory,
so this would correspond to
our front door unlocking.
And we also have
geofence-based events.
So you can generate
events corresponding
to when I leave home
or arrive home.
Let's go through these and how
we represent them in the APIs.
For the state of an
accessory, we have a new class,
HM characteristic event,
and that takes the
characteristic you want
to be the source of that event
and a trigger value that,
when that characteristic
meets that value,
that event will automatically
be fired for you.
For location-based events, we
have a HM location event class
that takes a CLRegion.
You can configure the CLRegion,
and when that criteria is met,
the HM location event class
will automatically fire.
Let's walk through an example
of our front door being unlocked
and capture that as a
characteristic event.
Here's how you do it.
Create a HM characteristic
event class,
give it the front door
current state characteristic
as a characteristic that
you want to capture.
And for the trigger value,
just specify door state open.
Now this event would
be fired when it's part
of an event trigger as soon
as your front door unlocks.
I talked about conditions.
Conditions get execution of
a scene in a given trigger.
We support three types of
conditions: time-based,
so I can have something
corresponding
to before 6 p.m. We also support
the state of an accessory.
This would be our motion
sensor detecting motion.
Finally, we also have
significant events in a day,
like sunrise and sunset.
Let's go through
each one of these
and see how we create
them in the APIs.
Conditions are represented
as predicates,
NS predicates, in the APIs.
And we have convenience
measures for all of these.
You don't have to
worry about them.
It's very simple to create them.
On an HMEventTrigger, class, we
have a class method predicate
for evaluating trigger occurring
before date with components.
That takes an NS dates component
that you can configure.
And you can use this,
for example,
to create the before
6 p.m. condition.
We have one for after
date with components.
We also have the third
one, which is predicate
for evaluating trigger occurring
on date with components.
This is really useful.
You can use this to
create a condition
for a specific day --
for example, Sundays.
Let's walk through an example
of creating our condition
for before 6 p.m. First, we
create an NS dates component
and set the hour
property to 6 p.m. Next,
we just use that NS dates
component and pass it along
to a convenience API predicate
for evaluating trigger occurring
before date with components,
and that's going to give you
an NS predicate corresponding
to before 6 p.m. Next,
the state of an accessory.
So we also have a convenience
API on the HMEventTrigger class,
namely predicate for evaluating
trigger with characteristic,
that takes a characteristic
and a matching value that needs
to be met for that condition
to be evaluated through.
So for our motion sensor,
here's how you would create
a condition corresponding it
to being detecting motion.
Just call the convenience API,
specify the front door sensor
characteristic as a source
of the characteristic, and
for the matching value,
set it to true.
This would mean motion
has been detected.
It's as simple as that.
Finally, significant
events in the day.
We have two convenience
APIs for this:
predicate for evaluating trigger
occurring before significant
event, that takes an optional
applying offset parameter,
which is an NS dates component.
And the second one, as you
guessed it, is predicate
for evaluating trigger occurring
after significant event.
We have two constants defined
for significant events:
sunrise and sunset.
Let's walk through an
example for condition
for our event trigger
that would correspond
to 30 minutes before sunset.
How do we go about doing that?
You first create an
NS dates component
and specify the minute
to negative 30.
And now, just use
our convenience API,
predicate for evaluating trigger
occurring before significant
event, give it sunset as
the significant event,
and give the offset that
we just created above.
With this, we can now
gate execution of a scene
if that event fires
after 5:30 p.m. As long
as it's before 5:30 p.m., it
will always execute that scene.
So now we have events that
can trigger our event trigger,
and then we have conditions.
How do we tie it all together?
That's when you create
an HMEventTrigger class,
and the method takes the name.
You can give one or more
events that activate a trigger.
Once a trigger is activated,
we evaluate the corresponding
condition.
The condition is optional, so if
you don't specify a condition,
it just means we
assume it to be true,
and we will always execute the
corresponding scene associated
with that event trigger if any
one of your events activates.
Now let's walk through
a completer example
that I talked about earlier.
We have created a characteristic
event corresponding
to the front door being locked.
We created our two conditions,
which is before 6 p.m.
and the motion sensor
detecting motion.
How do we tie it all together
and create our event trigger?
First thing you need to do is
create a compound predicate
because we want both
our conditions
to be ended and evaluated.
Both have to be true for
us to execute our scene.
For that, just use NS compound
predicate and predicate
with subpredicates, and
specify the two subpredicates
that we just created earlier.
Next, create an event trigger
object, give it a name,
arrived home, and for the events
that can activate this trigger,
just specify an area
of one element,
which is a front door
characteristic that corresponds
with it being unlocked.
Finally, we just need
to associate the arrive
home predefined scene
to this event trigger.
Use our convenience API on
our home, built-in action set
of type, give it the
home arrival type
that now returns your
predefined scene corresponding
to arrived home, just add
that to the event trigger.
It's as simple as that.
Now I'd like to show a demo
of this example I just talked
about using our HomeKit
Accessory Simulator
and our HomeKit catalog
sample app,
which has been completely
rewritten in Swift.
[Applause]
There you go.
So over here we have our
HomeKit Accessory Simulator.
This simulates HomeKit
accessories that are used
by our developers to develop
their HomeKit applications.
And over here we have our
HomeKit sample app that,
you know, that you can use --
that accesses all
our HomeKit APIs.
I want to show you a
demo of event triggers.
Now, you can see that I have
a door lock, a motion sensor,
and a bridge with
two lights behind it
in the HomeKit Accessory
Simulator.
And I have added my
accessories to my home.
So let's go down to the
scenes section of the app,
and I have configured two of the
predefined scenes in this app.
I have the "bye, house," that
corresponds to leaving home.
Let's see what that looks like.
That sets the light to black
and switches off all
the power on our lights.
I am going to go ahead and hit
cancel because I don't want
to make changes on this, and
let's go down to the "hi,
house," that corresponds
to arriving home,
and let's see what
that looks like.
Now, that sets the lights to
on and sets my stereo light
to green and the
kitchen light to blue.
Let's try to see
these two scenes
in action and see what happens.
So when I execute
the "bye, house,"
it switches off the two lights.
And when I execute the "hi,
house," which corresponds
to arriving home, that switches
on the two lights
behind the bridge.
Now, let's simulate leaving home
and now create our
event trigger.
I am going to go down to the
trigger section of the app
and select add trigger.
You are presented
with three options.
For our example, it's the
front door being unlocked,
which is the source
of our trigger.
That corresponds to a
characteristic, so I am going
to go ahead and select
characteristic.
I am going to give
it a name now.
So this is the name
of my event trigger.
And now let's go ahead
and select the characteristic
corresponding
to the front door
being unlocked.
So let's go down to the
characteristics event
of the app.
So add a characteristic.
And now go down to the front
lock and select unsecured.
This will correspond to
the door being unlocked.
I am going to go
back and hit done.
So now I have captured my
front door being unlocked
as a source of my trigger.
Next, let's add our
two conditions.
For that, let's go down
to the conditions section,
add condition, and since we
are going to use before 6 p.m.,
that would mean it's time.
Go to the time section,
and we have two ways
to add time-based conditions.
One is, of course, the
significant events, sunrise
and sunset, but I am just going
to use 6 p.m. at my example.
And I want to select before.
I am going to go
ahead and hit save.
Now I have captured
my first condition.
Now let's do the
second condition,
which is the motion
sensor detecting motion.
Go add my second condition.
Now I am going to
select characteristic
because this is an accessory,
which would mean I need
to capture a characteristic
as a source of that condition.
Select condition,
find my sensor,
and set motion to be detected.
I am going to go
back and hit done.
So there you go.
I have my event trigger, given
it a name, given it the source
of my event, specified
my two conditions
that both need to be met.
I tie it all together,
I just need to associate my
arrive home scene to this.
Let's go down to
the scene section
and just select "hi, house."
And go ahead, hit done.
Now that saves the
entire event trigger.
Now, let's see this
event trigger in action.
For that, first I
am going to go ahead
and unlock my door
and see what happens.
I have a view over here
that shows the door state
and the motion sensor so
that it's easier for you
to see what happens
behind the bridge.
If I hit unsecured,
which corresponds
to opening the door,
nothing happened.
And why is that?
The door opens, so that causes
the event to be activated.
It is before 6 p.m. So one
of my conditions was met,
but the second condition was
not met because, as you can see,
motion detected is set to no.
So this is working as expected.
I don't expect my
scene to be executed.
Now let's go ahead and close
the door and set the motion
to detected and see
what happens.
I am going to go ahead
and unlock the door.
There you go.
That switched on the lights and
executed my arrive home scene.
How cool is that?
This is an awesome feature,
and I work on this every day.
[Laughter]
[Applause]
But what is really
exciting to see this work,
when I see that light goes
on, it just gives you,
you know, that happy feeling.
[Laughter]
For those of you who have
used the Accessory Simulator,
you see there's a motion sensor.
This is new in iOS 9.
We have added new
categories of accessories.
To talk about this and
new features we have added
for our accessory classes,
I'd like to invite Naveen.
[Applause]
[ Background Sounds ]
>> NAVEEN KOMMAREDDI:
Thank you, Anush.
Good afternoon, everybody.
I am Naveen Kommareddi,
and I am here to present
to you even more features in
iOS 9 for HomeKit accessories.
Starting with remote access and
new features and enhancements
for Bluetooth Low Energy
HomeKit accessories
and new accessory categories.
So let's get started
with remote access.
With remote access,
you'd be able
to control your accessories even
when you are away
from your house.
So let's take an example
of a thermostat that works
with HomeKit here in your house.
You would be able to
securely connect to it.
But what if you are
away from your house?
How do you control
this thermostat?
Say you want to come home,
but you want to set it
to the temperature even
before you come home?
How do you do that securely?
Well, in iOS 8, remote
access is supported
if you have an Apple
TV third generation.
All you need to do is sign
in with the same Apple ID
as the one you used
on your iOS device,
and you'd have secure
access to your accessories.
Now, this is great, but what
if you don't have an Apple TV?
Because we know that
not every one
of our customers may
have an Apple TV.
[Laughter] So in iOS 9, I
am very excited to announce
that we support HomeKit
accessory protocol,
HAP, over iCloud.
[Applause]
Thank you.
Yes, it is really exciting
because what this means is you
can now control your accessories
and get notifications from
them no matter where you are,
and even if you don't
have an Apple TV.
Let's pause to think
what this really means.
To accessory manufacturers
who have thought
about providing secure
and remote access
to their accessories, you know
it's a hard problem to solve.
We built and deployed a
dedicated iCloud service
to securely relay HAP
messages between iOS devices
and accessories, and we
scaled the infrastructure
that runs the service to handle
billions of HAP messages.
And we thought: How can
we make this better?
So to use this service,
the accessory manufacturers
and all our customers
will now get it for free.
[Applause]
Well, thanks.
But most importantly,
privacy and security.
The end-to-end connections
between iOS devices
and accessories are HAP secure,
and privacy is maintained.
Even Apple can't see the
content of the communication.
This is extremely important.
Now, with HAP support
over iCloud and Apple TV,
our customers will now
have more ubiquitous access
to their accessories.
Now, moving on from remote
access to Bluetooth Low Energy.
So we are working with
several of our partners
to bring more Bluetooth
Low Energy accessories
that that work with HomeKit.
Let's say a Bluetooth door lock.
Now, if you are within Bluetooth
LE range within this accessory,
let's say a door lock,
say 20 to 30 feet,
you can securely connect
to it and control it.
But what if you are far
away, like in the corner
of your house or
in the backyard?
How do you securely connect to
this accessory and control it?
Wouldn't it be great to have
a mechanism or a feature
that would connect these
two endpoints together?
Well, in iOS 9, you
can do exactly
that with HAP secure tunneling.
HAP secure tunneling enables an
intermediate device to associate
over Bluetooth Low Energy
and expose it as an artifact
over Wi-Fi to an iOS device.
Now you have a device that
is a HomeKit accessory
that provides range extension
with HAP secure tunnelling.
So what's even better is this
range extender will also be able
to provide remote access
to this Bluetooth accessory
and any other Bluetooth
accessory
that works with HomeKit.
What this means is not only can
you reach your accessories no
matter where they
are in the house,
but you can also reach them
wherever you are, home or away.
Ultimately, privacy
and security.
The end-to-end connection
through this intermediate
device is still HAP secure,
and privacy is maintained
because this intermediate
device, the range extender,
cannot see the content
of the communication.
We didn't stop there.
We added several
more enhancements,
starting with notifications.
Your Bluetooth Low Energy
accessories now have full
support for notifications,
regardless of the
state of connectivity.
So whether they are
disconnected or connected,
they can send HAP notifications
to your iOS devices.
Really useful.
We also added support
for metadata.
This way, custom characteristics
can describe themselves fully
to HomeKit applications.
And finally, we added support
for multiple transports.
With this, you can now have a
HomeKit accessory that can work
over IP or Bluetooth
LE simultaneously,
and the iOS device will
be able to recognize
that it's the same accessory
regardless of the transport
that the accessory uses
to communicate with it.
Really a compelling feature.
Now, let's move on to the last
topic of our presentation,
which is accessory categories.
Last year with iOS 8, we added
support for several accessories
that are most commonly found in
your house, like your lights,
fans, switches, plugs,
garage doors, et cetera.
Now, adding native support
for accessory categories is an
evolutionary process in iOS,
and in iOS 9, we added
support for more devices in iOS
so that you can connect more
accessories in your house.
Starting with window coverings.
You can now use iOS to
control your awnings, blinds,
and shades, and motorized
doors and windows.
Alarm systems are
also a new category.
Now, this is a category
that several --
and alarm system and security
system providers have asked
for native support, and
which listened to them.
But we also found that alarm
systems can be really complex
with a lot of features, but what
we did is to distill the key
and the most used features
in an alarm system service.
Now, you as an accessory
manufacturer will be able
to add more features using
custom characteristics,
of course.
Alarm systems typically work
hand in hand with sensors,
so we added support for several
sensor categories: motion,
air quality, and smoke
being just a few of them.
And last but not least --
and this is a category I
am very excited about --
is programmable switches.
A programmable switch is a
HomeKit device whose main
purpose is to generate events.
iOS makes this accessory
compelling.
So to understand this better,
let me walk you through
an example.
So let's say it's bedtime,
and you're in your bed,
you stow away your
electronics, charging somewhere,
but you don't know if
your house is secure.
Your lights are probably off in
some far corner of the house.
But fret not.
You have this programmable
switch, nothing
but a simple switch
with a button.
Now, you press the button.
It generates an event.
And you know now in iOS 9
we support event triggers.
So our users will be able to
map this event to a trigger,
which will execute this
beautiful predefined good
night scene.
Now, iOS, wherever it is,
wherever the phone is,
it will get this trigger and
execute all of it magically.
Powerful but simple.
Now, programmable switch and
all the other new accessory
categories are available,
as Anush mentioned,
in our updated version of the
HomeKit Accessory Simulator,
so that you, as developers,
can develop apps
to support these new categories.
The HomeKit Accessory
Simulator is one
of the several tools
available to you as developers
and accessory manufacturers.
We also have HomeKit
Accessory Tester,
which is also being updated to
support many of the new features
that we talked about today.
Now let me talk a minute about
HomeKit Accessory Tester, HAT.
We urge you, as accessory
manufacturers,
to exclusively use HAT all
through your development cycle
because this way you will ensure
that your accessory is compliant
to HomeKit specifications
and also ensure
that your accessories work with
past and future versions of iOS.
Now, HAT also provides
the debug information
that may not be available
to you when you use iOS,
but the most important reason
is that we use HAT at Apple
to certify your accessories.
Now, HAT is also
one of the tools
that is exclusively available to
members of Apple's MFi program.
Now, if you are already
a member of this program,
then you'd be able to get
updated specs and tools
in the near future
at the MFi portal.
If you are not a member
of the MFi program
and you are making a HomeKit
accessory, you need to enroll
so that you would be able
to download the specifications
and tools.
And here is a link
to get you started.
Now, in summary, today you
learned about many new features,
like HomeKit and Apple
Watch, event triggers,
a new way of remote
access, and several features
for Bluetooth Low
Energy accessories.
We at Apple are really excited
about all these features,
and we can't wait to see what
you are going to do with them.
If you have any more questions,
any questions on HomeKit,
here's where you can get
more information from.
Thank you very much for
attending our session.
[Applause]