[Applause]
&gt;&gt; STEFAN HAFENEGER:
Welcome to session 211,
Multitasking Essentials
for Media-Based Apps
on iPad and iOS 9.
My name is Stefan Hafeneger and
today Jonathan and I will talk
about adopting Picture
in Picture
and mastering shared resources.
If you have already or plan
to integrate a media-based app
on iPad and iOS 9 this is
the right session for you.
This is the second in a
series of three sessions
about multitasking
on iPad this year.
By now you should
be familiar with all
of the iPad multitasking
features we have introduced
this week.
I want to remind you
about the concept
about primary versus
secondary app.
The primary app is
always the one
on the left unless the device
is set up right to left
which means it's the opposite.
In the first session we
showed you how to get started
with multitasking
on iPad in iOS 9.
In this session, I will show you
how to adopt Picture in Picture.
When you are playing
video on an application,
in iOS 8 when you are
playing video, and you switch
to an application the
video stops playing.
With Picture in Picture in iOS 9
the video automatically animates
into a floating window
allowing you to use other apps
on the iPad while the
video keeps playing.
I'm going to say Picture in
Picture a lot in this section
so from now on I will
refer to is as PiP.
PiP is supported on all of
our latest iPads, iPad Air 2,
iPad Air, iPad mini 2 and 3.
Now, you might be wondering
should my app adopt Picture
in Picture.
If your application provides
an immersive video playing
experience, then absolutely.
If your application provides
a kid's viewing experience
like a game, then probably not.
If you think your viewer was
like to keep videos
playing while playing
with other applications.
Let's take a look at the
video player APIs in iOS 8.
The media player
framework has been
around since the first iOS SDK.
Last year we delivered AVKit
as a new high-level media
framework, replacing parts
of the media framework.
AVFoundation is available
for clients that want
to create their own video
player with user interfaces.
[inaudible] using
their technologies.
Let's talk about the
media player for a moment.
In iOS 9 we are deprecating
MP movie player controller
and MP movie player
view controller.
In iOS 8 we are providing
AVPlayerViewController
as a replacement
for both classes.
And last year, in the Mastering
Modern Media Playback session we
showed you how easy it is
to adopt AVKit instead.
In this session we
are focusing on AVKit,
AVFoundation and WebKit.
All three media frameworks
rely on AVPlayerLayer
to display video content.
Let me show you how PiP works.
We start with an AVPlayerLayer
in your application.
In order for the
video to keep playing
when the application transitions
to the background we need
to reroute the video frames
to a different process.
For that, the system
adds a new layer
that can host your
video content.
When PiP is started, a PiP
window is created in this layer
and positioned over
an AVPlayerLayer.
Now, the video frames
can be rerouted.
There is a seamless transition
and the video will
just keep playing.
To be clear, we are not
touching the AVPlayerLayer
on your application.
We just stopped delivering
video frames.
Now, assistant can position
and size the PiP
window however needed,
and the video currently
keeps playing even
when your application
transitions to the background.
So which of our modern
video players support PiP?
I'm happy to announce
all of them.
In the first part of the session
I will show you how to adopt PiP
in your applications using
all three media frameworks
and we will start with AVKit.
AVKit's main API
for video playback
is AVPlayerViewController.
A modern AV controller subclass
that provides standard
controls and behaviors.
In iOS 9 AV view controller
smarts Picture in Picture
and it's a button
in the lower bar.
When the user taps this button
the video automatically animates
into the PiP window.
My colleague Felix will show you
now what exactly you have to do
in your AVPlayerController
application
for the PiP button to show up.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; FELIX HEIDRICH:
Hello, everyone,
I'm excited to show you the
new Picture in Picture support
of AVPlayerViewController.
For this I have a demo
application running
in the simulator that
shows a collection
of videos using a
collection view controller.
I can tap on one of the videos
to reveal detailed
information about it.
I can also tap the big
play button to bring
up AVPlayerViewController
and start video playback
in full screen, but as you can
see, the user interface does not
yet contain a PiP button
in the lower right corner.
For the button to appear, two
simple steps are required.
Let me show them
to you in Xcode.
The first step is to set
the apps background modes.
For this, I switch to
the project settings,
select the targets, and go
to the capabilities tab.
Here under background notes
need to be enabled and the audio
and air play check box
needs to be selected.
The second step is to set
the app's audio category.
For this I go to
the app delegate
and first import AVFoundation.
Next, an application did
finish launching this option.
I can set the audio
session category
by asking AV audio session
for its shared instance
and then setting the category
to AV audio session
category playback.
With this code in place,
let's launch the demo again.
I again select the video,
start playback in full screen,
and now in the lower
right corner,
the PiP button is present.
When I tap the button,
the video starts to play
in Picture in Picture.
The user interface in the PiP
window contains three buttons,
the central button toggles video
playback and I will talk more
about the other two
buttons in a bit.
Also notice that there is a
playback progress indicator
present in the UI.
Now, while the video is
playing, I can navigate back
to the collection of video,
of videos and, for example,
look at detailed information
of a different video.
I can also simulate
pressing the home button
and launch a different app
all while the video continues
to play.
On the left button in the PiP
window should return video
playback to the application.
When I tap this button, the
demo app is brought back
to the foreground,
but as you just saw,
the PiP window is simply
dismissed and that's
because our PiP machinery does
not know if the app is ready
to handle video playback.
Let me show new Xcode how to
restore the user interface
to handle video playback just
as you're users will expect it.
For this I switch to the
collection view controller.
New in iOS 9, we are
adding a delegate property
to AVPlayerViewController
and in this code I already made
the collection view controller
the delegate of
AVPlayerViewController.
To reinstall the user interface
the collection view controller
needs to implement a simple
delegate message has a very
descriptive name and is
called player view controller,
restore user interface for
Picture in Picture stop
with completion handler.
In this code, I ask the
navigation controller
for its top view controller, and
then use the top view controller
to present the player
view controller
that the delegate provided.
The other thing in the code is
to call the completion handler
once the player view controller
is presented on screen.
By doing this our
PiP machinery know
that it can start animating
the video back into place.
So let's run the demo again.
I again tap on one of the
videos, play it in full screen,
switch to Picture in Picture and
now when I return video playback
to the app,
AVPlayerViewController
is presented
and the video nicely
animates back into place.
Another thing I want to
show you is what happens
when I leave the application
while the video is playing
in full screen.
For example, if I now simulate
pressing the home button,
in this case, we automatically
start Picture in Picture
so that the video
continues to play.
At any time users may tap
the right close button
to dismiss the PiP
window and that's Picture
in Picture support of
AVPlayerViewController.
Thank you.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; STEFAN HAFENEGER: So let's
review what you just saw.
You have to do two things.
First, you have to enable
the correct background mode
otherwise your application
won't be able to keep playing
when it transitions
to the background.
You do this in Xcode
[inaudible] capabilities.
Audio and air play is the
one you need to enable.
In the future iOS 9
[inaudible] rename to audio play
and Picture in Picture.
Second, you need to set a valid
AV audio session category.
A good place to do this is did
finish launching with options.
You ask for the shared
audio session,
and then set the category to AV
audio session category playback.
If the application also
supports audio recording,
you can alternatively use AV
audio session play and record.
If the application
supports background audio
on air play iOS 8 you are
already doing both things.
If you think the application
should not support Picture
in Picture in iOS 9
we have a new option
on AVPlayerViewController
that allows you to disable it.
Notice how Picture in Picture
is automatically started
when the user taps on
the message notification.
Why does this happen?
When the primary application
transitions to the background,
an AVPlayerViewerController
is presented full screen,
the system starts Picture in
Picture on the user's behalf.
If the video [inaudible]
is playing, then Picture
in Picture is possible.
Keep in mind though that the
user can turn off this behavior
in settings in general
multitasking persistent
video overlay.
Felix showed in the demo
that you automatically dismiss
the AVPlayerViewController
and the user starts
Picture in Picture.
We don't know the
structure of the application,
or where the user navigated
to when it was active,
so we need your help to
restore the AV viewer controller
by implementing this
delegate method.
In a simple case you could
just call presentViewController
animated, by using
the [inaudible].
A few applications have
more sophisticated structure
than the demo application,
you might have
to do a few more things.
In either case, don't forget
to call the completionHandler
when you are done
with the restore.
And that's AVKit and
AVPlayerViewController.
Next let me show you
how to do Picture
in Picture using AVFoundation.
As a client of AVFoundation
you have an AVPlayerLayer
and most likely player controls.
I'm going to show you what you
have to do and get from here
to here in your applications.
In iOS 9 we have a new
class called AV Picture
in Picture controller.
It allows you to implement same
PiP viewers I just showed you,
but using your own
user interface.
Before I create an
instance of an AV Picture
in Picture controller you
should check whether Picture
in Picture is supported
on the current device.
You create an AV Picture
in Picture controller
by providing an AVPlayerLayer.
Think of AV Picture in Picture
controller as an objects
that allows to present
the content
of the AVPlayerLayer
in the PiP window.
Setting a delegate is
optional but it is very likely
that you will need it.
Next, you have the PiP
button to use interface.
So that the user can
start Picture in Picture.
You should only add the button
if the device supports
Picture in Picture though.
There are situations
where starting Picture
in Picture is currently
not possible,
even though the device
supports it in general.
In this case, you should
disable your PiP button.
For that we have a property
on the PiP controller
that you can observe and
then update the enable set
of your PiP button.
The implementation of your
PiP button action will look
something like this.
You first make sure that
PiP is not already active.
And then you can start Picture
in Picture in the pipController.
Do not call this method
without user interaction.
If you use this inappropriately
the App Store team will
reject submissions.
If the application provides
additional content while PiP is
active you may want to
dismiss the video player viewer
controller after PiP is started.
In order to do so could
implement the did start delegate
method and then call
dismissViewControllerAnimated
on your controller.
When you do this
though make sure
that you don't release
your PiP controller.
Because if it does happen,
the PiP window will disappear.
So make sure you structure
your application accordingly.
AV Picture in Picture
controller has a delegate method
for restoring your
view controller.
In a simple case you could
just call present view
controller animated.
Again, make sure you call
the completionHandler
when you are done
with the restore.
Because when you call the
completionHandler it is assumed
that the AVPlayerLayer used
to initialize the PiP
controller is back on screen.
If this is not the
case, we won't animate
to video frame spec. Your
AVPlayerLayer won't show
on video frames while
PiP is active
so if the application provides a
non-modal view player experience
like this example you might want
to update the user interface.
AV player viewer controller
shows [inaudible] like this
and hides viewer controls.
This behavior is not required
but we highly recommend
this for consistency.
In order to do this you could
implement the start delegate
method, hide your
player controls
and show your place
holder art work.
When PiP stops you
do the opposite,
you implement the did
stop delegate method,
hide your placeholder art work
and show your player
controls again.
Very simple.
Finally if you want to allow
PiP to automatically start
when application transitions to
background you have to be sure
that the AVPlayerLayer
covers the entire UIWindow.
If this is the case, and
the video is playing,
and PiP is currently possible,
the system automatically
starts Picture in Picture
on your user's behalf.
And you will see all
of this in action,
we have brought a great sample
project you should check
out after the session.
So you saw how easy
it is to adopt Picture
in Picture using
AVFoundation as well.
Finally, let me show you
Picture in Picture with WebKit.
WebKit's main API for
video play is WKWebView.
This part of the session is for
those among you using WebKit
to present your [inaudible]
web technologies.
In iOS 9 WKWebView
supports Picture in Picture
for HTML5 video if
the application is set
up the same way as
for the other APIs.
If your web content
uses iOS default
in the playback controls,
PiP will just work.
If you are a website
developer interesting
in incorporating a PiP button
into your controls check
out section 501 what's new
for web developers
in WebKit and Safari.
If you want to support
background audio air play
but don't want to allow
Picture in Picture,
we'll have a property in
WKWebViewConfiguration
in the future iOS 9 seed
that allows you to do so.
And that's WebKit.
So you saw how easy and straight
forward it is to adopt Picture
in Picture in your applications
for all three media frameworks.
I can't wait to see
PiP support in all
of your iPad video
player applications.
Picture in Picture is a
lot like background audio.
If the application
is not on screen
but the user is enjoying
your media.
The same rules apply
to background audio
and air play apply here as well.
For instance, do not perform
any task unrelated to playback
and limit your memory
usage to only these tasks
when the application
is in the background.
Properly sharing resources is
critical not only for PiP apps,
but for all iPad applications.
And to discuss this further let
me welcome Jonathan on stage
to tell you everything you
need to know about this topic.
Thank you.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; JONATHAN BENNETT:
Thanks Stefan multitasking
on an iPad allows you to use
multiple apps onscreen at once.
But hardware resources are
still shared between all
of the presented apps.
I would like to explore with you
some of the iOS media policies
and updated best practices you
can use to manage audio, video,
and camera in your applications
with multitasking on iPad.
The good news is that some
of these best practices
should already be familiar.
And many apply to all
iOS devices so it's easy
to make your app
shine everywhere.
Now, before I dive into
specific media resources,
I'd like to take a few
moments to discuss some
of the roles your
app may take on iPad.
In iOS 8 apps are
presented full screen.
And new in iOS 9 you can have up
to three apps on screen at once
with the new multitasking modes.
These apps may be vying for
some of the shared resources
so to help manage that, the
system categorizes your app
into one of three roles.
Full screen apps are
considered primary.
And they continue to be so when
a secondary app is presented
in slide-over.
The full screen app also remains
primary when it's resized
to fit next to a pinned
app in split view.
And a Picture in Picture
application can be put
into the background while
the video remains visible
to the user.
In this case your app's
considered background media.
For certain shared resources
these roles help define the
system's policies and
your app's capabilities.
So let's dig into some
of these resources.
Starting with audio.
The audio system on
iOS is well-suited
for multiple applications.
If your app currently
using audio,
you have configured the AV audio
session API to state the nature
of the audio in your
application.
The system uses this to figure
out how your app's
audio mixes with,
docks or interrupts other
app audio on the system.
The good news is a properly
configured AV audio session
should just work with
multitasking on iPad.
To this end, never change
your audio configuration based
on how your app is
presented on screen.
It's all about the audio.
With that, I would
like to go over some
of the audio session best
practices most relevant
to multitasking on iPad.
If you are not following
these practices,
your app may have
worked okay on iOS 8
but showed issues on iOS 9.
First off, only activate
your audio session
when audio is first needed.
This is especially true
if you have an application whose
audio interrupts other apps
such as music or video
application using audio sessions
playback category.
Never solely determine to
activate your audio just
because your app launched
or came into the foreground.
Wait until the user interacts
with your audio feature before
activating your session.
For example, a music and
video application would wait
until the user taps
the play button.
Next, there is a huge category
of apps that don't need
to interrupt other audio.
For example, if you have a game
or have other ancillary audio
like sound effects, you should
use the ambient audio category,
this category provides
appropriate behaviors
for this kind of audio including
mixing with other applications.
This is critical for these
kind of applications on,
with multitasking on iPad,
because your app may remain
in the foreground while
other apps come and go.
And you don't want your
game audio interrupted
and having the user have to
restart your app in order
to get its audio back.
Lastly, some apps have
secondary audio Soundtracks.
An example of this
is if you have a game
with bold sound effects
and a music Soundtrack
that plays during the game.
Now, if the user is
already listening to music
in another application,
you would like to silence
your secondary Soundtrack.
So that the user it
continue listening
to their music while your
sound effects still mix in.
We provided a great way in
iOS 8 to know when to do this.
Simply check AV audio sessions
secondary Audio Should Be
Silenced Hint and listen to its
began and ended notifications.
So these are some of the
most important best practices
for using audio on iPad,
and as a bonus following these
will insure a great experience
on all iOS devices.
If you would like to learn more
about configuring your audio
session, there is a bunch
of great tips in last
year's Core Audio talk
and in our detailed
programming guide.
Next up, video.
And first off, a lot of video
has audio associated with it.
So if you have an app that
provides movies or TV shows,
you will want to properly
configure your AV audio session.
In that example, you will want
to set audio session's
category to play back.
Next. If you support air
playing video in the background
or add the new PiP support
or add the new PiP feature
in your application, you will
be considered a background media
app when you are playing
media in the background.
This means that you will have
lower maximum memory limits
so it's really important that
you discard any unnecessary data
such as view controllers, views,
images, and other data caches
that aren't necessary when
your app is off screen.
You will want to do
this proactively.
Don't wait for a memory
warning to do this.
You will also want
to limit yourself
to performing just the task
necessary to perform playback
in order to help share the CPU.
Now, many iOS video apps
provide their content via HTTP
live streaming.
If you have a streaming
video application,
you will want to do two things.
First, make sure that you are
providing multiple variants
in your stream including
a smaller resolution,
low bandwidth variant.
And second, make sure you are
annotating all of your variants
with the resolution attribute
in the master play list.
Now, if you get your video
from an external vendor,
be sure to check with them to
see if they are providing you
with these diverse
well-annotated variants.
And this is important
for three reasons.
On iPad and iOS 9 your video may
not take up the entire screen.
Providing well annotated
variants allows iOS
to choose the right-sized video
for how it's currently
presented.
And when it's presented
in Picture
in Picture a smaller resolution
low bandwidth variant lowers
your memory footprint, and
helps avoid terminating apps due
to memory pressure.
And lastly, following these
practices help users avoid
unnecessary data plan usage.
And they will really
appreciate that.
The last topic I would like
to talk about today is camera.
In iOS 9 only one app can
use the camera at a time.
In addition, for certain camera
features they may only be
available when one app
is visible on screen.
This means that camera
availability can change
at any time and your app's
camera usage could be
interrupted because
the user is interacting
with other app using
multitasking.
For this reason, it's important
to consider how people
use your application
and its camera features.
If you have a camera centric
application, you may want
to consider being
full screen only.
Our camera app is a
great example of this.
If your users expect an
experience like this,
you can add the UI requires full
screen key to your info P list.
This will help let
users get quick access
to the camera inside
your application
and use the entire
iPad as a view finder.
Now, if using the camera
is not the primary feature
of your application,
you will likely want
to adopt the multitasking
enhancements on iPad.
Our notes app is a
great example of this.
People are going to
love the flexibility
of using the new
notes features inside
of slide-over and
split-view modes.
However, this mean that's some
of the app's camera features
may not always be available.
So let's take a look
at how our camera
and notes apps handle
camera availability on iPad
and how your apps
can do the same.
When one app is on the screen,
UI image picker can let you
see a preview, take a photo,
or do a video capture,
just like today.
And when multiple
apps are on screen,
you can still see a preview
and take a photo, however,
video capture will be disabled.
So let's dig into this case.
Here we have full screen maps
with your app presented
in slide-over.
The UI image picker is in photo
mode so you can see a preview
and the user can take a photo
if they tap the shutter button.
When the user swipes
over to the video mode,
they will see a message that
says your app needs to be
in full screen in
order to take video.
What does this mean
for your application?
First off, active video captures
can be interrupted at any time.
An example of this is if you
are recording video full screen
and an app slides over a new
app in the slide-over feature.
Your video will be interrupted
and it's important to note
that this kind of
interruption can happen
to any video capture
app regardless
if you support the multitasking
modes or full screen only.
Next, the UI image pickers start
video capture method may fail
because we are in a multitasking
mode that doesn't support it.
If you are not currently paying
attention to this return value,
now is the time to do so.
So these are some of the
things for UI image picker.
Let's transition to
AV capture session now
and see how the API differs.
When one app is on the screen,
you can still have full
access to the camera.
And because AV capture session
is a flexible low level API,
you can do more than just these
three features listed here.
And we have been amazed
at some of the creative
and powerful features you have
added in your applications.
In order to ensure that we
can offer you the resources
necessary to provide the highest
quality camera experience inside
your application, an AV capture
session using the camera will
only be available when one
app is visible on screen.
This means that whenever
slide-over, split view,
or Picture in Picture is active,
your camera's session
will be interrupted.
You should handle these
interruptions and communicate
to your users that the camera
is currently unavailable.
Let's see how you can do this.
The first step is to listen
to AV capture sessions
interruption reason
or excuse me, was
interrupted notification.
And new in iOS 9,
the notification's user info
dictionary states a reason
stating why your
camera was interrupted.
There is multiple reasons
you could be interrupted
but when it's due
to multitasking
on iPad you will be told that
the video device is unavailable
with multiple foreground apps.
This is your opportunity
to adjust your UI
by disabling any capture
buttons and also identifying
that the camera is
currently unavailable.
Now that you have handled
these interruptions,
what do you do when they end?
When an interruption ends,
AV capture session automatically
resumes the session,
there is no need to
manually restart it.
You can be notified of this
by observing the
interruption ended notification.
And, again, this
is your opportunity
to restore your camera UI by
re-enabling any of the buttons
that you previously disabled.
Be sure to check out our updated
AV cam sample code for examples
on using these new interruption
reasons inside your application.
So in review, Picture in
Picture is a great new feature
for video playback applications.
You can adopt it easily with any
of our modern playback
frameworks and remember
that if you are using
MediaPlayer framework
for video playback to transition
over to AVKit to get the benefit
of PiP and other great features.
Also be sure to follow best
practices Stefan talked
about to ensure a
great experience inside
your application.
As an example, make
sure to restore your UI
so that the video animates
right back into your app.
Multitasking on iPad
provides the power
to use multiple applications
at once.
However, this comes
with a responsibility
of sharing resources.
Three things you can do are
to properly configure
your audio session,
provide adaptive video streams
and handle the new camera
interruption reasons.
For more information, get
in touch with our evangelist
and check out the forum.
And also we provided a new
document called adopting
multitasking enhancements
on iPad.
Now, sharing media
resources is only part
of the story for
shared resources.
Be sure to check out
the optimizing your app
for multitasking session
happening next up in Presidio.
There is also a great
Friday talk
on delivering performance
on iOS.
And if you missed it,
the getting started session
is a great place to learn
about adopting adaptive
UI in your apps.
On behalf of Stefan,
Felix and myself.
It's been great to talk
to you this afternoon.
Thanks, and have a
great rest of the week!
[Applause]