[Applause]
&gt;&gt; JAKE BEHRENS: Good morning.
Welcome to "WatchKit
Tips and Tricks."
My name is Jake Behrens,
and I am the watchOS
Frameworks Evangelist at Apple.
Now, today we are going
to talk about various ways
that you can optimize your
existing watchOS applications
under watchOS 1.
There are going to be many
things that we're going to talk
about that are equally
applicable to watchOS 2,
and I will point those
out as we move along.
Now, leading up to the
release of Apple Watch,
we worked with many developers
on their first Watch
app experience,
and we learned a lot along
that way, and today I am going
to share a lot of this with you,
things like optimizing
your networking,
how you can decrease your
loading times, and much more.
So let's start with
data and communication.
As I mentioned previously,
this is essential
for getting information
from your web service,
or from the containing iPhone
app, so that you have something
to actually display to the user.
Now, imagine that your user
is waiting at the bus station.
They raise their wrist,
they are interacting
with your application, and you
kick off a network request.
Suddenly, the bus comes
around the corner,
so they put their arm
down, they get their stuff,
they are hurrying to the
bus, and then they get
on the bus and get settled.
Well, you want to make
sure that the next time
that they raise their wrist to
go back to your application,
that that data is there
and waiting for them,
not that you have to
refetch it all over again.
So how do you do
this effectively?
Well, the first part is you
need to have a network request.
This is how you are going
to get your information.
The next thing that you need
to do is you actually need
to ask the system for
what's called a background
task assertion.
This is a way to ask the system
and say, 'hey, I need some time
because I may need to finish
some process once you start
suspending my WatchKit
extension.'
Even further, if you get that
background task assertion,
you are going to
need to hold it open
so that your network
request actually finishes.
So how are we going
to do these things?
We are going to walk
through it together.
The first thing that
you are going to need
to do is get your network
request set up, and for this,
we are going to use a
default NSURLSession.
Now, recognize that I am not
using a background NSURLSession
because in that case,
if our WatchKit extension
was suspended,
then the completion
would come back
to our containing iPhone app.
We want to do everything
we can right
in the WatchKit extension
itself.
So next we need to ask for
that background task assertion.
How are we going to do that?
We are going to do that by
using 'perform expiring activity
with reason,' which is a
method on NSProcessInfo.
This is going to ask the system
for a background task assertion
and say, 'hey, I may need to
still do something once you go
to suspend the WatchKit
extension.'
So what happens is you
pass in a debugging string.
Here it says networkReq.
And then this block is executed.
Now, this block is going
to be called immediately
when 'perform expiring
activity with reason' is called.
Now, there are some
things to keep in mind
that are really important
about this.
The first thing is that this
block is going to execute
on an asynchronous queue.
So your main queue is still
freed up, the user can interact
with the interface,
there's no problem there.
The user doesn't recognize that
anything different is going on.
And if expired is set to
false, then that means
that our time has not expired.
So the system has given us
a background task assertion.
However, if expired is
true, then this means
that the system was unable
to give us a background
task assertion.
This means that it said no.
However, if it said that we
did have a background task
assertion, it could later
execute this block again
with expired set to true because
maybe the system has decided we
are completely out of time now.
And so you're given a moment
to make sure that you clean
up any state that you have.
Or something that you may need
to do before the WatchKit
extension fully suspends.
So as I said, the key thing
here is that this block executes
on an asynchronous queue.
The second really
important piece of this is
that once this block
finishes executing,
then your time goes away.
It gives up that
background task assertion.
So how are we going
to actually make sure
that we have enough time to
finish our network request?
Could take two seconds.
Could take ten seconds.
Could take more.
We are going to use something
called dispatch semaphore.
Dispatch semaphore is part of
Grand Central Dispatch, or GCD,
and this essentially allows us
a way to pause execution over on
that asynchronous queue.
So you call 'dispatch
semaphore wait,
and that will pause execution.
But then, when you need to
get going again and resume,
you can call 'dispatch
semaphore signal.'
Now, notice in the way
I'm passing in a time,
this is essentially a time out.
I have set it to
30 seconds here,
and it could be any
number; however,
I want to make sure that, you
know, once it hits 30 seconds,
I should have either gotten my
data or I'm calling it lost.
So this is a little abstract,
and it's a little bit
of an advanced concept.
So let's actually take a
look at the code in practice.
Okay. So here I have a WatchKit
extension built for watchOS 1.
And I am here in a subclass
WK interface controller.
You can see that the first thing
that I do is I create a property
for an NSURLSession data task.
This is the data task
that we are going to use
to get our information
down from our web service.
Next in will activate --
and realize you can do
this wherever you are going
to do your networking code.
For simplicity's
sake, in this example,
I am doing it in will activate.
First I am checking the state
of the data task, and I am going
to see if it is already running,
because if the user raised
their wrist, started interacting
and kicked off a network
request, put their wrist down,
had background time going, and
then raised their wrist again
and it hadn't completed
yet, I don't want
to just kick off
another network request.
I only want to do
another network request
if I don't currently
have one going.
So next I am going
to create a URL,
and now this is just
pointed to my web service.
Here it's pointed to the
metadata on the App Store.
Once I have this URL,
I create my semaphore
by calling 'dispatch
semaphore create.'
Next I am calling a method
that I wrote called 'ask
for assertion with semaphore,
passing in this newly
created semaphore.
So if we look down here at
what's going on in this method,
this is where we are actually
calling 'perform expiring
activity with reason.'
We are passing in our debugging
string, and if expired is set
to false, then that means
that we've gotten
some background time,
and I am passing in my timeout,
and I am calling
'dispatch semaphore wait.'
Remember, this is going
to pause the execution
of that asynchronous queue.
The user can still interact with
the application, no problem.
It's just holding there,
ensuring that we
have enough time
to finish our network request
if the WatchKit extension were
to go into the background.
Now, if expired is set to true,
which means that we either were
not given a background task
assertion or maybe we were
but now the system has called it
again saying you're out of time,
well, we're going
to call a method
that I created called 'release
assertion with semaphore,
again, passing in
that semaphore.
And all this method does
is actually call 'dispatch
semaphore signal.'
This allows execution to
resume, and it allows the block
to complete, and this is
also very crucial to call
because if we halt execution for
too long, the system might think
that our process has just
hung, and that's no good
because eventually it's just
going to kill it outright.
So we don't get any opportunity
to save state or do any cleanup.
We just get killed.
Okay. So let's go
back to will activate.
So we've asked for
our task assertion.
And the next thing we are going
to do is we are going to create
that data task with
the URL that we have.
Now, notice that I
am not gating this
on whether I have a background
task assertion or not.
The background task
assertion technique is a means
to get some borrowed
time, right?
I mean, it's not
guaranteed, but we're hoping
for a better experience here.
So I'm just going to
create my network request
because probably the
user is interacting
with the app at that time.
The network request has
kicked off and come back
in mere moments, and
everything's great.
You'll also see here
that there's a convenience
completion handler
for the data task, so
when the request finishes,
I am going to call in
to 'release assertion
with semaphore,' passing
in that semaphore again.
So we're allowing
execution to resume
on that asynchronous queue,
which lets that block complete,
and then the WatchKit
extension can fully suspend.
This ensures that the
system doesn't think
that our process has hung.
Okay. So once we have
created our data task,
then we are just going
to call resume on it
to actually start it, so
it can go to the network,
grab the information, and
we'll take care of the rest.
So now you've seen a little
bit of a nice technique
that you can use to try and do
all of your networking right
from within the WatchKit
extension itself.
This is really great because
moving on to watchOS 2,
there's a whole lot of stuff for
you to take advantage of there.
And we'll talk about
that in a little bit.
But if you're already
moving your networking
to the WatchKit extension
itself, this is going
to prepare you so that things
are already broken apart.
I've seen many examples where
open parent application is used
to have the containing
iPhone app actually do all
the networking.
This breaks that bridge.
Now, in some cases our data
isn't on a web service,
and our data is actually in
the containing iPhone app
and we need to get that.
So we actually need to reach
across the process in watchOS 1
from the WatchKit extension
to the containing iPhone app.
We can do this by using
'open parent application,
and this is a method on
WK interface controller
that allows us to send a
dictionary of information
over to the iPhone app,
launch it in the background,
allow it to do some processing,
and then send a response.
So on UI application delegate,
we have 'handle WatchKit
extension request reply.'
This is going to take in that
dictionary of information,
do some processing, and
then send back a reply.
There are some things to think
about when you are using this.
First, if you are doing
any asynchronous work
in 'handle WatchKit extension
request,' you should make sure
that you're creating
a background task.
You want to do that right away,
right when you enter
into this method.
The reason why is because
if you go off and decide
to do some asynchronous
work, no matter how trivial,
the system is going
to say, 'oh, well,
I guess we are not actually
doing some work, so I am going
to go ahead and suspend
the iPhone app.'
And then you are not
going to get the chance
to send the reply back.
The other thing is when you
are going to send your reply,
if you are using custom objects,
you should be turning
those into NSData.
If you have a custom binary
format that you can use,
that you can unpackage in
the WatchKit extension,
that's even better because
the name of the game here is
to make the data as
small as possible
so that transmission
is quickest.
Now, for true device-to-device
communication, we've got a lot.
Now, 'open parent application'
is marked as unavailable
in watchOS 2, and this is
because it's no longer
necessary.
It's no longer needed.
Because we now have the
WatchConnectivity framework.
The WatchConnectivity
framework gives you so much.
Not only can you send
messages between the iPhone app
and the Watch app, but
you can transfer files.
You can also -- and
should also --
take advantage of the
application context.
So you can update this context
with whatever your
newest information is,
and that allows you to get some
information in your Watch app
from the network -- maybe it's
the latest in your feed --
and then you can say, 'well,
the iPhone app is going
to need this later, so I
am going to pass that off.'
It's going to be
transferred over,
but the iPhone app
isn't launched
because it doesn't actually need
to process anything right now.
So in this case, it's
just waiting there
for next time the
iPhone app launches.
This is a much more
efficient way
to do your communication
between devices.
Now, there's an awesome
session called
"Introducing Watch
Connectivity,"
and you should definitely check
it out if you haven't already.
Now, once we have our data, then
we're going to want to manage it
and take care of however
we need to have it on disk.
Under watchOS 1, making use
of app groups is a
great way to do this.
You can use the shared
app group container
to store some model data
or some shared assets
that both the containing
iPhone app
and the WatchKit extension
can both point to and find.
Now, you can also use
shared NSUser defaults,
but you should probably be
using this for small state data,
like a Boolean configuration
or something like that,
not for your model data.
Your model data is
probably pretty large,
and it's probably best if it's
sitting there as a flat file
of some sort in your shared
container or in your data store.
In general, for watchOS
1 or watchOS 2,
you should definitely think
about simplifying your model.
The experience on Apple
Watch is very different
from the experience on iPhone.
And so you want to make sure
that you only are actually
getting the information there
that you need.
An example of this
is the WWDC app.
So over the years
in the WWDC app,
we've ended up adding
quite a few entities
to our Core Data models.
And when we went to go create
our experience for Apple Watch,
I looked at it and I said, well,
we don't actually need
all of this on the Watch.
And so we discussed it, and we
realized at the end of the day
that all we needed was a
simplified version of this data.
We just needed a simple
list of the sessions,
which are the sessions
and labs, and favorites.
So what we did was we created a
process where any time the data
in the containing
iPhone app changes,
it exports a simplified
set of JSON files
into the shared group container
that the WatchKit
extension can then just read
and display to you.
This worked really well.
One final means
of device-to-device
communication is using Handoff.
Handoff is an awesome
way to allow your user
to continue an activity
from Apple Watch to iPhone.
So an example of this would be,
say you go to the WWDC
app on Apple Watch.
Then you will notice on the
lock screen of the iPhone
at specific areas,
you are going to see
in the bottom left-hand corner
the icon for the WWDC app.
Now, if you swipe up from
that bottom left-hand corner,
it puts you exactly
where you need to be
within the WWDC app on iPhone.
This is really great for users.
And using Handoff
is really simple.
You use update user activity,
which is on WK interface
controller,
and you can send over,
for the user info,
an NS dictionary of data.
Now keep in mind that
this dictionary needs
to include everything
that you may need in order
for the iPhone app to
get the user exactly
where they need to be.
So whatever small data and
bits of data you need in there,
you need to send that
across in that dictionary.
Now, the system is going to do
a lot for you automatically,
and one of those
things is it's going
to automatically
invalidate the user activity
after some moments.
And so you don't
need to do anything.
It's going to give the
user enough time to take
out their phone, get to
where they need to be.
Or if you call 'update
user activity' again,
then that's going to be
the current activity.
Or if they switch to
another application
and that calls 'update
user activity,
that will be the
current activity.
Now, if you've called
'update user activity'
but then the user is interacting
with your application,
they tap a button and the
context really changes,
you can actually manually
invalidate the user
activity yourself.
If that's not the situation,
you don't have to do anything.
So that's enough about data.
I hope that the technique for
watchOS 1 is useful for you,
especially since it's
going to help you get
through that migration
to watchOS 2 once you start
using the WatchConnectivity
framework over there.
Now let's talk about
interface elements.
The last thing that
you want your user
to experience is the loading
indicator while you invent the
world and you are
creating all this data,
you are creating all these
things for a controller.
Everything the user
may ever want or need.
Let's look at some ways that we
can optimize that experience.
How can we load quicker?
One of the ways that
we can do this is
by prioritizing how the
content loads and when it loads.
So you can see here the
Weather app for watchOS 1,
and we have this big,
beautiful ring of information.
Right? And we want to get
this to the user immediately.
But we also have
this 10-day forecast,
and this 10-day forecast
includes additional images,
table rows, data, and we don't
necessarily want the user
to be waiting while we
load all of this as well.
So we used a technique where
we load this 10-day forecast
within a 'dispatch async'
call within will activate.
Now, doing this allows
will activate to finish,
and once we have that graphic,
that's the first thing
that gets displayed.
So we get that in will
activate, it finishes,
and then that 10-day
forecast gets loaded,
right immediately after.
So the user doesn't actually
see anything different.
By the time they go to scroll
down to the 10-day
forecast, it's already there.
But we've been able to
give this impression
that all the data has
loaded immediately
and a little bit quicker.
Something else you can do is
load fewer table cells up front.
Right? If you have really
complex cells that have images
and data, then you might only
need four or five of these cells
up front to display to the user.
You're probably going to
be able to load in the rest
after those have been loaded.
So take a look at that.
Also, only update
the information
that has actually changed.
I have seen many
occurrences where one tiny bit
of data has changed and
everything is reloaded.
There's no need for that.
Just only update
what actually needs
to be updated on the screen.
Now, once we move into Interface
Builder, you can see here
that I've started creating
my layout for a controller.
And I'm using a lot
of different groups.
I am hiding and showing
different groups
because depending on
certain data or heuristics,
I am only going to show one at
a time or maybe two at a time.
But what happens is I actually
have all of these objects
in my controller, which means
that the system is going
to instantiate these
all up front
because we actually don't know
when you are going to decide
to hide things or show things.
And so you can optimize this
a little bit in some scenarios
by breaking these out
into separate controllers.
If you have the ability to
load whichever controller you
actually need when you need it,
then that's going
to be most optimal.
Now, moving through
our interface elements,
one that you probably
use a lot are images.
And images should be properly
sized from your server
or the containing iPhone app.
I've seen many cases
where there's a bigger
image that's even bigger
than the dimensions of
the 42-millimeter watch,
and it's just reused
and rescaled everywhere.
I mean, there is additional
performance implications here
for the scaling, and also
that image isn't going to look
as good as it could look
because you didn't give it
at exactly the size
you needed to.
So give properly sized assets.
In watchOS 2, this also is
going to be crucial for video.
You can also optimize
your images
by using 'set image data'
instead of just 'set image.'
In this case, 'set
image' is just going
to use whatever default
compression we use.
With 'set image data,'
you have the ability
to have specific PNG
compression or JPG compression,
and then that turns it
into this NS data blob
for transmitting
over to the Watch.
So you can ensure that
it's getting as small
as you may need it to be.
Also -- and I'm sure you have
heard people banging this drum
-- you should be
using asset catalogs.
Asset catalogs are
not only a great way
to organize your content,
but they also do a lot
of other things for you.
You can set which specific
devices that this asset is for,
and you can set and easily see,
'okay, I've got a 2x asset here,
a version for 38 millimeter, and
a version for 42 millimeter.'
Now, I have been asked by
many developers when and where
to use each of these slots.
So let's go through
these together.
The first is the 2x asset.
And this is going to be used for
an image that you want to use
at the same size
on both devices.
So if that's the case,
you can just put it
in the 2x slot, you
are good to go.
It will be used the
same everywhere.
You can also provide a specific
asset for 38 millimeter.
Now, this will probably
be the same image
that you would have put in
the 2x slot, and that's okay.
And then you can
provide a specific asset
for 42 millimeter, which will
probably be a little larger,
something will be different.
Now, it's okay if you
have a 38 millimeter
and a 42 millimeter version,
it's okay to have that 2x asset
as well because we are going
to fall back to that asset.
So if there's a situation
where we can't use that 38
or 42 millimeter
version, we are going
to fall back to that 2x asset.
So that helps you
future-proof your code base.
One other technique, and
we've found this really useful
in the WWDC app, is using PDFs.
By using PDFs you
can get a whole lot
of free work out of the tools.
First, you can set
the scale factors.
You can also set the
type of image rendering
as template image, so if
you are tinting this image,
then it's just going to look
at the alpha value of the PDF.
Or you can set it
to original image
if you still want those colors
that you specifically
put into your asset.
The neat thing here is that when
the system builds your package,
when you go ahead and build it,
we are going to cut this PDF
at all the sizes and
scales that you need
for the devices you support.
So that's a whole lot
of work just free.
The other cool thing is
that you can actually mix
and match PDFs and bitmaps.
So you could have that 2x
asset be a fall back PDF,
and you can have very specific
assets as bitmaps for the 38
and 42 millimeter versions.
Moving from images, let's
talk about animated images.
In watchOS 1, we have an
animated image sequence
that you can take
full advantage of.
You can do this in
watchOS 2 as well.
Just know that if you have
multiple animated images
on screen at the
same time, well,
that means more processing
and more rendering.
The other thing is that
you should try and reduce
and restrain yourself
with the amount of frames
that you have for an animation.
Now, I have seen cases where
for a two-second animation,
there are 300 frames.
Seems a little overkill.
You would be really
amazed with what you can do
with fewer frames and still get
that effect that
you really want.
Another thing that you can do
with these animated image
sequences is run them
in reverse.
You don't have to create
a whole other image set.
You can just take one
that you are already using
and set the duration
to a negative value.
Now, you do this when
calling 'start animating
with images in range.'
You provide that
negative duration.
Notice that my range is
still forward looking.
It's going from location
0 to a length of 15.
I haven't changed that.
Just the duration.
Now, if you like animations,
there are a lot of things
that you can do under watchOS 2.
With watchOS 2, we are
introducing an animation API
as part of WatchKit, and this
allows you to make really fluid,
great effects within
your Watch apps.
This is similar to how
UIView animations work,
so you have a duration that you
set, and then you have a block
where you can reset
some properties
and they'll all be
animated together.
You can animate things such
as height, width, alpha,
content insets, and much more.
I've seen some really incredible
things that people have done
with this so far, just using
spacer groups and moving items.
It's really, really great.
There's a lot more if you want
to check it out in "Layout
and Animation Techniques
for WatchKit."
And as far as the image
handling, I encourage you
to check out the
"Apple Watch Design Tips
and Tricks" session today.
It's going to take a
lot of those aspects
from the designer mentality,
and they are going to talk
about a ton of other
great things
that you can do and be aware of.
So check it out.
One final piece of
configuration is the use
of the text input controller.
Now, I've been asked by many
developers how can I get the
user from my UI directly
into the dictation UI?
They don't want their
users to be having to get
to this intermediate screen
and tapping on the microphone.
This is really, really
straightforward.
All you do is when you call
'present text input controller
with suggestions,' you set
the suggestions to nil,
and then you set the
'allowed input mode' to plain.
This is going to take the
user right from your app right
into the dictation UI and then
right back to your app again.
Super easy.
So let's also talk
about notifications.
Notifications are a really
meaningful experience
on Apple Watch, and a
huge part of what makes it
so convenient and so amazing.
Let's take a look at
an example payload
for a remote notification.
Let's go over some things
that you should make sure
that you are using in
order to deliver the best
and greatest experience
to your user's wrist.
The first thing to note is
that you should be using
the dictionary value
for the alert key.
This allows you to not
only provide a body,
but also a title.
And this title is
going to be used
in the short-look notification.
So when the user receives the
notification on Apple Watch,
the first thing that they are
going to see is your app's big
and beautiful icon,
and then it's going
to see your app name
at the bottom.
If you've provided a title in
your payload, then you are going
to see that title between
the icon and the app name.
This is an amazing way to
provide a lot more context
to the notification because a
lot of users are going to look
at their wrist, they are
going to see that notification
and decide off that information
whether they are going
to continue to the
long-look notification
or whether they are going to
put it down and visit it later
in Notification Center.
So take advantage of this.
The other thing to be
using is the category.
Categories allow you to specify
which specific controller you
want to use from your storyboard
for which type of notification.
So if you click on the
notification category object,
you can see here that
you can set its name
to that same name used in
the payload, and so you can,
per notification type, set a
sash color and a title color.
So you can provide
other means of intricacy
into your notifications
to really give the user
a great experience.
Now finally, if you want them
to receive the notification
and hear that notification sound
and receive haptic feedback,
you need to set the
sound value to default.
This is going to make sure
that they receive the
sound and feedback.
Now, I'm excited to tell you
that you can do all of this
with UI local notifications
as well.
So it's not just for
remote notifications.
Now, with notifications,
you have two concepts.
The first is the
dynamic notification.
Maybe you receive some
information in that payload,
you need to process it,
you need to get an asset,
you need to do something,
and then you load
that more rich content into
your dynamic notification.
There's also a static
notification,
and I have been asked many
times where that's kind of used.
So a static notification
is always going to be used
from Notification Center.
So if the user taps
on the notification
from Notification Center,
they will always see the
static representation.
So you should make sure
that that experience
is also a great one.
The other time that the
static notification is going
to be used is if your dynamic
notification is taking too long
to load.
Maybe you are processing some
data, retrieving some asset
from the network, and
it's just taking too long.
Then we're going to
just call it a loss
and give the user some
meaningful information right now
in the means of the
static notification.
Now finally, let's
talk about Glances.
With Glances, it's a great
way to provide your users
with meaningful,
timely information.
Now, maybe you've seen this,
where you come to a Glance
that you haven't viewed in
a little while, and it shows
that it's updating the content.
You see this updated last
title string at the bottom,
and you see this spinning
progress indicator
in the top right.
But maybe while it's been
loading, you've seen this.
So let's see that again.
You're loading in the content,
everything's going great,
and then, oh, where did
content go, and then boom,
it slams in when it updates.
Why does this happen?
This happens because 'will
activate' should be treated a
little bit differently within
your Glance controller.
So what happens is
that system-provided snapshot is
going to be removed from the UI
when 'will activate' finishes.
So a little contrary to what you
do within the Watch app itself,
here you want to make sure
that you are doing your
full setup before 'will
activate' finishes.
You want to get all the
information you need,
set it so that the UI is
up and ready to go so that
when we remove that
snapshot, it's right there.
There's no in-between state of
the whole screen disappearing.
You might have placeholder
text in your storyboard
that you might see or
something to that effect.
That doesn't really
provide a great experience.
The other thing that you
should do is reload the
content deliberately.
As a user is swiping
between Glances, well,
'will activate' is going
to get called on yours,
and so if they swipe past yours
and in 'will activate' you're
loading a whole bunch of stuff,
doing some processing, doing
a network request, well,
that's probably not the
most efficient you could be
doing that.
So make sure that you are
reloading very deliberately,
depending on other circumstances
and not just, 'hey,
they looked at my content.'
The other thing, as
in with Watch apps,
is to limit the number
of alternate layouts.
Because again, we
are going to need
to instantiate all
those objects up front.
Finally, you should be using
WK interface date labels
or absolute times and dates
if you're displaying that kind
of content in your Glance.
So if you look here
at an example,
it says that this session
started 35 minutes ago,
and if this is at 1:00 p.m.,
well, it's kind of confusing.
I am seeing that it's updating.
I know. But it started
35 minutes ago,
and it's giving me kind of like
that knee-jerk reaction
of, like, wait.
What time is it actually?
So the better thing to do here
would be to give an absolute.
It started at 10:00.
This allows me already
that affordance of, 'oh,
it was earlier today because
now it's 1:00 or 3:00.'
I am not confused.
That content is loading
in, and it's all good.
So we've talked about
a lot of stuff.
First, we talked about ways
that you can already start
optimizing your watchOS 1
application's networking
so that the transition
to watchOS 2 is even easier,
and hopefully this will really
help you in your application.
Then we talked about ways that
you can improve your layouts
for performance to
take down that amount
of loading time and
do much more.
Then we talked about
how to ensure
that your Glance always
has content visible
so that you are not
leaving an empty screen
in front of the user.
Finally, there's a ton to
check into in watchOS 2.
Aside from updates to watchOS 2
in WatchKit, we've got ClockKit
to create complications
for clock faces.
We've also got the
WatchConnectivity framework
to do all this device-to-device
communication.
And you can still take
full advantage of NSURL
from the WatchKit
extension itself.
If you'd like more information,
we have great documentation.
We've got sample code.
If you have technical
questions, the Forums are there,
as is Developer Technical
Support for one-on-one help.
Finally, if you have
any general questions,
please feel free
to reach out to me.
My email is there.
Today we still have one amazing
design session for Apple Watch,
and that's "Apple Watch
Design Tips and Tricks."
They are going to
go over a whole lot
of really awesome information
to help you create
great Watch apps.
We also had the "Designing
for Apple Watch" session,
the "Introduction to WatchKit
for watchOS 2," and much more.
With that, thank you very much.
[Applause]