[Applause]
>> MICHAEL TURNER: Welcome
to the final day of WWDC,
and 'What's New in UIKit
Dynamics and Visual Effects.'
My name is Michael Turner,
joined by my colleague
David Duncan.
We are both on the UIKit
team here at Apple.
So before we get started today,
I just want to recommend
some great sessions.
Since this is an
introductory talk,
we have some great sessions
from years past covering UIKit
Dynamics and visual effects.
So today we are going to
start with a brief overview
of the dynamic animation
system, and we'll do
that with a basic example, and
then we are going to dive right
into what's new this
year with UIKit Dynamics.
Then David's going to
come up and talk to us
about visual effects, and
how you can utilize those
in your application.
And finally, we are going
to talk a little bit
about best practices
using UIKit Dynamics
and auto layout in
your application.
So when we talk about UIKit
Dynamics we are talking
about a 2D, physics-inspired
animation interaction system.
This has a very composable
and declarative API
for exposing high level
animations in your app.
We are not talking about
replacement for Core Animation
or UIView animations,
rather another tool
to help you create great
custom effects in your app.
So let's look at an example.
So here we have a
basic sliding view
and the user can pan the view,
but if you let go it falls back
down as if under the
influence of gravity.
Now, it doesn't fall through
the bottom of the phone.
Rather, it stops on the
bottom edge, bounces a bit,
and then comes to rest.
So let's look at how we can
create this basic example.
First you need to start
by determining a
great reference view.
Here, we've chosen the
view controller's view
that contains our sliding view.
And once we have a
reference view, we then need
to create a dynamic animator and
associate that reference view.
The dynamic animator will
hold the overall context
for our animations, and its
main job is to keep track
of behaviors and dynamic items.
So for our sliding example,
we have a sliding behavior.
And one of the great things
about UI dynamic behavior,
is that higher-level
behaviors can be composed
of more primitive ones.
So our sliding behavior is
nothing more than a composition
of gravity, collision,
and attachment.
And later on, we will show you
how we used UIAttachmentBehavior
and the new things we've added
there to make this even simpler
than it would have
been in the past.
So once we have our
sliding behavior,
we now need a dynamic item.
Here we've chosen the
sliding view, just a UIView
which automatically conforms
to the dynamic item protocol,
so it's a great option.
So we take our dynamic
item, associate it
with the sliding behavior,
and the sliding behavior
to the animator.
Now the animator will
automatically determine
when the system is at rest or in
motion, so this is all you need
to create this great effect.
So now we have seen
a basic example.
This is what's new this
year in UIKit dynamics.
We have support
for non-rectangular collision
bounds on UIDynamicItem.
We have a brand new
UIDynamicItemGroup
that allows multiple items
to behave like one item
in the engine, and we
have a brand new behavior
that models vector force fields.
We have some basic enhancements
to UIDynamicItemBehavior,
as well as UISnapBehavior, and
we'll see some great additions
to UIAttachmentBehavior,
and we will finish
up with some new
ways that you can use
to debug your dynamic
animations.
So, in iOS 9, we
added UIDynamicItem
CollisionBoundsType which
offers you three new ways
to specify the collision
bounds for your dynamic item.
And by default your collision
bounds will be rectangular
matching what's returned
from the bounds accesser
on the dynamic item protocol.
And now you can specify an
ellipse type, which will derive
from the bounds width and
bounds height on the protocol.
And finally, you can specify
a UI BezierPath to use
for the collision bounds
of your dynamic item.
Now, to accomplish this, we have
taken the existing dynamic item
protocol and we have extended
it with two optional properties.
And if you don't
implement either
of these optional properties
you will receive rectangular
collision bounds, as
you have in the past.
If you implement the first
collision bounding type
and return ellipse,
will derive one,
an ellipse from the bounds
width, bounds height.
If you implement the
first and return a path,
we will then call you
back for the second
at which point you will need to
provide a UI BezierPath to use
for the collision bounds.
So if we were to model a
collision between items
with different collision bounds,
and let's add a few more here
for good measure, it might
look something like this,
where this collision
looks a lot more realistic
than it would have in the past,
had all the items had
rectangular collision bounds.
Now, there are a few
restrictions when using a path
for collision bounds
and in particular,
the BezierPath must be convex,
counter-clockwise wound,
and non-self-intersecting.
And these are pretty basic
if you think about it,
nothing too fancy there.
We also need to keep in
mind that the point 00
in the BezierPath will represent
the dynamic item's center point
when the item is on screen.
So that's what's new
in collision bounds.
Let's talk about
dynamic item groups.
And this is a basic way
to take multiple items
and make them behave as one
item in the underlying engine.
And the group preserves
respective positions
and each individual collision
bounds for each item.
So for this reason, you should
associate items with a group
and not with behaviors
individually.
Instead associate them with
the group and the group
with any behaviors you would
like to associate
with the animator.
And this will impose
those behaviors
on the items as a whole.
And a group cannot be
added to other groups.
This is a one-level abstraction.
So this can be a great
way to create concave
or other complex
geometry not capable
with the dynamic item
bounds path, and also have
that influenceable by
behaviors as a whole.
So, let's return to that
sliding example for a moment.
So instead of just panning and
having it to fall back down,
let's say we want it to bounce
slightly when the user taps,
maybe to indicate
that we can pan.
And to do this, we just need
to add a brief force
to the sliding view.
So let's take a look
at that force.
So we can model the force as
a vector at the item's center
where the length of the vector
corresponds to the magnitude
of the force and the
vector points up to indicate
that the direction of the force,
in this case we are trying
to move the view
up, so it points up.
And to apply the force, we're
going to use UIPushBehavior --
where UIPushBehavior, if you
recall, has two distinct modes.
It has a continuous mode that
represents a constant force
over time, and an
instantaneous mode
which represents a brief
force at an instant in time,
otherwise known as an impulse.
So for this interaction, we just
want a brief force so it bounces
and comes back to
rest, so we're going
to use the instantaneous mode.
So we do that; we
get a brief force.
But what is causing the
view to come back down?
We are putting a force on
it that causes it to move up
but it's falling back down.
This is our composite behavior
that was composed of a gravity,
a collision, and attachment.
And so gravity is causing
it to move back down
and then it bounces with
the collision behavior.
But let's look at a
little bit more at gravity
and how that's affecting
our item.
So we look at the
vertical motion over time
of the sliding view,
starting with the instant
that we apply the impulse force.
You will notice that the
force is applied at one point
and then the item kind of moves
up and then arcs back down.
This is because gravity is
affecting it at all positions
and all times in
our diagram here.
If we add those forces in from
gravity, it might look something
like this, where
the force is applied
at all positions and all times.
So this is tricky to model.
Maybe we could try and
use UI push behavior,
but it would be pretty
complex, pretty quickly.
So we really need to think of
gravity as more of a field.
And a field's quite
simple, it's just a function
that assigns a vector to each
point within a given domain,
where our domain,
in this example,
is the entire reference view.
So we want gravity to
affect our sliding view
in the entire reference view.
Pretty simple.
So we have taken this idea of a
field and we have extended it.
In iOS 9, we are
introducing UIFieldBehavior.
And UIFieldBehavior is a way
that can be added to a region
of your reference view, and the
field is evaluated at each point
within the reference view,
and any resulting forces
are automatically applied
by the dynamic animator
to the items
that have been associated
with the field.
And if you are wondering,
our existing UIGravityBehavior
has been implemented
as a field all along, and
it's important to keep in mind
that this is simplified physics.
It's been well tuned
for performance.
I wouldn't use it for building
interstellar space stations
or anything like that.
So let's look at the built-in
field types that we offer.
We've got a rich variety here.
We have linear and
radial gravity, velocity
and drag fields, a vortex field,
we have got a great spring field
that models Hooke's
law, we've got electric
and magnetic field types.
And if these all don't
quite meet your needs,
we also offer a custom
force evaluator,
and we'll see this in a moment.
But let's start with
linear gravity here first.
So the first thing you will
notice is it exists in a region,
in a domain as we previously
said, and it has a strength,
we've used the default
strength of one here,
but it's also a directional
force,
and then we have used
the familiar direction
of gravity here, down,
to show this example,
but this can be directed
anywhere, really.
So let's look at how
radial gravity differs
from that of linear gravity.
And along with existing in a
domain and having a strength,
this has a position
which can be modeled
with radial gravity
as a point mass.
And if you recall, the
gravitational force
between two masses is
inversely proportional
to the distance squared
between the two masses.
So, here, that distance
squared between the masses,
that exponent, this is the
fall off value of the field.
So as you get farther away
from the position of the field,
the force due to the
field, it gets -- decreases.
And we also have a minimum
radius property here,
and this is just a
way to specify how far
from the position point
an item must be in order
to feel a resulting
force due to this field.
So we also have a noise field,
and the first thing you will
notice about a noise field is,
it's time varying, and you can
adjust this using the animation
speed with a default
value of one,
and zero would indicate
a static field.
You can also adjust
the level of noise
in the field using the
smoothness property.
So let's look at a
custom field evaluator.
And this is really
quite easy to use.
You create a UIFieldBehavior
and initialize it
with a field evaluation block.
We will then call your block
with several field samples
containing the position,
velocity, mass, and
charge, and time associated
with that field sample
and then you can use
that to determine
any resulting forces.
Here all we did was take the
position, the x position,
and map it to a sin wave.
Pretty cool result.
So these are the -- some of
the basic built-in fields
and a basic overview
of UIFieldBehavior.
I would like to invite up David
to give you a quick example
of showing an inaction.
[Applause]
>> DAVID DUNCAN: Hello,
everybody, and we are going
to take you through an
example of something
that I'm certain you
have all seen before.
As I'm sure you have all
used FaceTime at some point
or another, and so we
just have an example
of building a very similar UI
for managing your
face in the screen.
As you have been able to see
as I have gone through here,
the square moves very nicely
as I move it around the screen,
and if I pull it a little away
from the corner it bounces back.
If I pull farther, it has
that nice ease-in
curve as we are going.
And if I throw it down, it kind
of bounces off very playfully
all around the edges.
And you will note when I threw
it down, it didn't just kind
of go straight to where
it was supposed to go,
it actually had a little
physics, it bounced off the side
of the screen and came
back into position.
Now, I can do a little thing
and trigger a debugging view
of what those forces
fields look like.
In this case you
can see that we --
[Applause]
In case, you can see that we
have four spring fields running
around here, and we have got an
easy way to explain what's going
on so if we put this
right on the edge,
we know it is going
to bounce back.
And if we kind of straddle
two, then depending
on where we straddle it will
pick one side or the other.
And go through the middle,
and it just picks
whichever is closest.
So let's see how we set this up,
and how we can actually
set this all ourselves.
So the first thing that we have
is this StickyCorners behavior,
and as Mike mentioned, it's
built up of other behaviors
to form this complex behavior
that does everything we want.
In this case, it has got
a collision behavior,
because we wouldn't
want your face
to rocket off the
side of the screen.
And we have a dynamic
item behavior,
that affects the
properties of that face.
In this case, we
reduce its density
to it's really light
feeling in the engine,
but we increase its
resistance to motion so that
when it finds a place to
settle it doesn't keep spinning
around in that location.
And finally we disable rotation,
because that wouldn't
make any sense.
You don't want your
face spinning
around as it's going
around the screen.
Finally, we have
these field behaviors,
the four spring fields that
map out the four corners,
and we add those to
the behavior too.
Now whenever somebody adds
this StickyCorners behavior,
they get all of this
behavior for free.
Next, over here in
the view controller,
we go to all the usual
stuff where we set
up our view hierarchy, but
then we also add a pan gesture
recognizer so that the
user can pick up the face
and move it around the screen.
This long press gesture
recognizer we have here lets me
actually toggle on and
off the debug interface.
We create our dynamic animator
and add the StickyCorners
behavior to it.
So how does that
gesture recognizer work?
Well, as usual, the gesture
recognizer goes between states.
It starts at begin, and when we
begin, we do some bookkeeping
so that we can keep
track of the item,
but we also disable
the sticky behavior.
And I will show you how
we do that in a second.
Similarly, when it's changed
we just move the item around.
And when it cancels or ends,
this is where we do
something really special.
We check the velocity that
the pan gesture recognizer had
when the user stopped
interacting with it,
and we use that to
add velocity back
into our dynamic item system.
And this is so that when the
user throws that view around,
it continues moving with the
force of the user's action,
rather than just suddenly
stopping and being taken
over entirely by the field.
And the whole reason
why we disabled
and enabled it is
for the same reason.
We don't want the fields
to be active while the
user is moving it around,
otherwise it is going to slip
out from underneath
their finger.
So we can go back
over here briefly
and see how the enabled works,
and as you can see,
it's really simple.
When it's enabled, we
add all of the items back
into the behaviors, and when
it's disabled, we take them out.
It's really that easy to
create a system like this,
and you can have your own
FaceTime-like behavior
in your applications.
And so to show you how
to put that debug UI
into your own applications,
I am going to bring
Mike back up on stage.
[Applause]
>> MICHAEL TURNER:
Thanks, David.
So it's really, really quite
cool, in David's example,
to visualize those field lines,
to understand what
was actually going on.
This is pretty mysterious
until he turned that on.
So those lines were basically
an overlay that shows the field
in your animators'
reference view.
And specifically, this overlay
can help you visualize fields,
collision bounds,
attachments, and whether
or not a particular item
is in motion or at rest.
Now, you might be wondering,
it's not going to be API.
But it will be accessible in
LLDB, and we are advertising it
as an available debug
feature on UIDynamicAnimator.
And it's really simple to use.
Just pause the debugger,
find a reference
to your dynamic animator,
set debug enabled to true,
and you will have this
great overlay depicting all
the physics.
[Applause]
Now in addition to debug
enabled and disabled,
we are also offering
debug interval.
And this is a way that you
can tune how often we update
that debug overlay.
So, by default, that
will be updated
on every animation frame,
but if you have a lot
of complex physics, it might
be beneficial to change
that to five, for example,
to only update the overlay
on every fifth frame.
And, we're also allowing you
to adjust the animation speed
of the dynamic animator.
Now this might be helpful
for slowing down things
to observe what's
actually going on.
And then it's important to
keep in mind when using this,
this can affect the
results of the simulation,
when you slow things down.
So always ensure
correction at 1x.
So, next, let's talk about
UIDynamicItemBehavior.
Now, if you recall,
this is a way
to alter the physical properties
of your view or a dynamic item,
and it can be applied to
one or more dynamic items.
And in David's example,
he applied a lower density
and a higher resistance
to the FaceTime square
to make it really stick
to the field corners.
So a few more examples of
the existing properties here.
We have elasticity, friction,
we saw density and resistance,
we have angular resistance,
and these are all great ways
to adjust how your item feels
in the animation engine.
In iOS 9, we have added two
additional properties: charge --
this affects the degree to
which your item participates
in our new electric and
magnetic field types;
and we also added an
anchored property.
This one is a little
bit different.
But what it does is it allows
your item to participate
in the dynamic system, and
participate in collisions,
but it will obtain no
velocity of its own.
So it really behaves more
like a collision boundary.
So next, I would like to talk
about UIAttachmentBehavior.
And this allow you to
constrain two dynamic items
such that they maintain
a particular distance
from each other.
And you can configure this
with the damping and frequency
to make it behave more like
a spring as opposed to a rod.
And this is a great attachment.
You know, it's very useful,
but it's really only one way
to constrain two items
with respect to each other.
So, in iOS 9, we have added some
additional attachment types.
The first of which is
a limit attachment.
This is quite similar to
the distance attachment
that we just described, however,
instead of being constrained
by what could be thought
of as a rod or a spring,
this one behaves more like a
rope between the two items,
where the only constraint
is a maximum distance
from each other.
And you configure this similar
to the distance attachment
by specifying two points
offset from each item's center.
Very simple.
Next, we have a fixed
attachment.
And this one is a little
bit different than the limit
or the distance attachment.
And you create this
type of attachment
by first specifying
an anchor point.
This anchor point is
in the coordinate space
of your reference view, with
respect to each item's center.
And this type of attachment
offers no movement whatsoever
between the two items.
It's much like a welded rod
between both items as opposed
to a rod that allows
them to spin on the ends.
And we have also added
a pin attachment type.
This one is similar to the
fixed attachment where you start
by specifying an anchor
point between two items.
But this type allows two
items to rotate with respect
to each other, about
this anchor point.
And this allows you to
specify a rotatable range,
which by default would be
unbounded but we could bound it
down to something
smaller like so.
And finally we have added
a sliding attachment.
Now the sliding attachment is
a little bit more complicated.
We'll look at an
example in just a second.
but just like the fixed
and the pin types,
we first specify this
attachment anchor point that's
in the coordinate space
of the reference view.
But unlike those
types, we also need
to specify an axis
of translation.
And this is where
all relative movement
between two items will be
along the axis of translation.
And this type prevents
all relative rotation
of the two items.
So they are really fixed
rotationally with respect
to each other and they can
only move along the axis
of translation.
But just like the pin type,
you can limit this
translatable range.
So if you do specify
a translatable range,
it needs to include the
attachment anchor point,
where the anchor
point is defined
as the point zero in the range.
So if we set this system up
with this type of attachment,
we can have linear motion
between the two items,
like that.
So that's pretty complicated.
Let's look at a basic example.
And to do that, I want to return
to our sliding example
one more time.
Now, I mentioned in the
past, that had we tried
to make this slidable
behavior, we would have had
to add a collision on the
bottom and on each side
and somewhere off the
screen above on the top,
to constrain the motion
of the sliding view
along the vertical axis.
Well, with UI attachment
behavior, we don't need to do
that anymore, we can use a
sliding attachment to do that.
So we limit the system
to one collision,
making the performance better,
and the code actually
quite a bit more readable.
So if we enable our
debug view here,
you can see the sliding
attachment depicted
by the straight line
along the vertical axis.
It expands and contracts
as we slide the view,
but there's also
another attachment there,
and that's a distance
attachment that we use to attach
to an anchor point
that's manipulated
by a pan gesture recognizer.
So, unlike David's demo,
this one's entirely
within the dynamics system.
We don't disable
or enable anything.
We just stay in dynamics.
Pretty cool.
So, finally, let me give you a
quick update on UISnapBehavior.
If you recall, UISnapBehavior
is a higher level behavior.
And it can be used to move
a view from one location
to another with a
snap-like effect.
And SnapBehavior allows you
to customize the damping
of the snap, which can
really adjust, you know,
the snappiness of how it feels.
In iOS 9, we've added
the ability
to customize the snap
point after init time
as well, which is pretty cool.
So let's look at a
quick example, here.
So if we try to pan the view,
here, with our debug on,
it will fall back to the screen,
like the original snap point.
If we tap in another location,
it will snap to the new point
and that's just adjusting
the snap point
on an existing dynamic behavior.
Pretty cool.
And you will also notice
that with the debug overlay,
this is actually a
composite behavior of its own.
There's four attachments
here, configured as springs,
just that snap the view
to the new position.
It's really quite cool.
So that's what's new in
UIKit Dynamics and iOS 9.
I would like to turn
it over to David
to talk about visual effects.
[Applause]
>> DAVID DUNCAN: Good
evening, everybody.
So we are going to talk
about using visual effects
to add style to your
application.
So we are going to motivate this
with just a simple image viewer
application, where what we want
to do is show the user
some extra information
about the photo they are
currently looking at.
And so as you see right
there, this image happens
to have a little overlay
that tells us what the
file name is of the image.
So we are going to walk through
how we actually create that.
And so, the first
step is that you need
to create a blur effect.
And we have three different
styles, the extra light,
light, and dark styles.
And then you create a blur
effect from those styles.
And that's just how you
do that right there.
And finally, you create
your visual effect view
with that blur style.
Then you just add whatever
layout you need to do
and you can get the blur
that you see on screen there.
The next step is we are going
to add a vibrancy effect.
And what vibrancy does is, it
really makes something pop,
stand out from when
it's over a blur.
And so what we are going to do
is we are just going to create
that vibrancy effect
from a blur effect.
As mentioned, it's really
intended to be overlayed
from a blur, so we start
with that blur effect
to create the vibrancy effect.
We create our vibrancy effect,
just like we did
before with the blur.
And then, in this case
we're going to add it
to the content view
of the blur view.
Now, it doesn't have to be
directly added to the blur,
but there should be a
blur that you see behind
that visual effect view.
And finally, we add the label
to the content view
of the vibrancy view.
And the reason we are adding
these things to the content view
of the visual effects view,
is because that ensures
that we get the correct
effect for all the content
that you are presenting.
And so, when you have
done all of that,
you get the lovely
label on top of the blur
as you see on the screen.
So what's new in iOS 9 here?
Well, the first thing we have
done is we have made it really
easy to cleanly animate
the bounds of your view.
So that you can show more
information in that blur view
to the user without having to
do anything really complex.
But, in addition, we
have made it possible
for you to animate the blur.
And so now, if you have a night
load in your app, for example,
you can do a really clean
animation from day to night
in your application and
move the user along.
Now, the next thing we are
going to talk through, briefly,
is how do we actually get
these effects to the screen?
What does it do and why
do you need to know?
It's important because
this all has impacts
on both performance
and correctness.
So little baby Sophia
here is going to walk us
through adding a little
overlay to her little UI here.
So the first thing
to do is figure out,
where are we capturing?
Whenever we see a visual effect,
we figure out what the capture
content we need for it is
and we move it offscreen.
So we copy that little
piece out.
And now that it's offscreen,
we can actually work with it,
but why did we take
it offscreen?
Well, for one reason is
that we need to make sure
that we get the correct
effects and in this case
that we capture everything
we need to blur
for that blur effect, but
also we often do these things
offscreen so that we don't mess
up the content that's already
on screen when we are
doing effects like this.
So we apply the blur to it.
And finally we copy
it back into position
where the effect
view desired it,
and all of this is
the definition
of something you might
have heard before called an
offscreen pass.
It's whenever we take content,
we copy it into an offscreen,
do work, and then bring
it back on screen.
So what are some other ways that
we can get offscreen passes?
Well, as you can see,
we have got alpha,
and you can see the
way you do that because
if you have a complex view
hierarchy that needs alpha
in it, then we can't just apply
the alpha to individual views,
because you won't get
the correct effect.
Instead we need to take the
entire complex hierarchy
offscreen, render it,
and then apply the alpha
to the whole thing.
Masking has a very similar
reasoning behind it,
in that we need to have all
the pixels for the mask.
As we just mentioned, blur and
vibrancy also go offscreen,
but snapshotting,
why is that up there?
You might ask yourself.
Well, first off,
what is snapshotting?
We have got these two UIView
methods, snapshot view
after screen updates and draw
view hierarchy in rect and
and the UIScreen method snapshot
view after screen updates,
and these all hand you back
content from a snapshot.
Well, a snapshot is
basically doing the same thing
as an offscreen pass but giving
you control over the final step
of copying it back to screen.
We take all content that
you asked us to snapshot,
render it offscreen, and
then hand you back a view
or pixel content
representing that image.
But, again, what does this
have to do with making sure
that your effects are correct.?
Well, unfortunately, if you get
a visual effect caught in all
of this, as you can see,
Sophia has lost her blur.
And that's what you will see on
screen if a visual effect ends
up getting caught
in an offscreen
that you didn't expect
it to go into.
So back to motivating this,
I'm sure you have all been
to the multitasking sessions
this year, and if not,
you should watch them
on video afterwards.
But one the key things
that you need
to have a great app
participating
in multitasking is good
performance on screen.
Because now the performance
of your app also affects
the other side app.
And so, since we don't
have any scrolling
in this particular example,
we have decided, let's instead
of keeping the blur
rendering all the time,
let's just take a
snapshot of it.
And so we decided
to take a snapshot
of that particular
visual effect view.
But then what happens
is the capture area is
happening offscreen.
And since you only snapshotted
the visual effect view,
there's nothing in
that capture area.
And so the capture
gives you back nothing,
and the blur has
nothing to blur,
and you get the broken
effect you saw before.
So, now that we have seen how
you can have your effect broken,
what can we do to fix it?
Well, first thing is, we
have this handy method
on visual effect view, called,
what's wrong with this effect?
[Laughter]
[Applause]
Just like with the dynamics
debugging flags this isn't
available in the SDK as
such, but you can call it
from in the debugger,
just like this,
and you will get back a string
that looks kind of like this.
In this case, we found that
there was a mask view somewhere
up in the hierarchy that was
causing the visual effect
to go offscreen, and thus
not capture as much content
as it needed to,
to render properly.
So how can you fix this?
First way that this works,
if you are using either alpha
or masking, is to rearrange
your view hierarchy.
What we have here is just some
container, maybe the window,
and a container view
that contains a blur
and further contents.
Well, in this case the
blur doesn't actually need
to participate in the
alpha or masking we have,
so we just rearrange to have
the blur as the first subview,
the container as the second
subview, and thus the container
and everything in it will
render on top of the blur,
and we can apply alpha or
masking to the container view
without messing up our blur.
A second thing that we
can do for masking is,
instead of masking the container
view, we can move that mask
down into the content that
we actually need masking for.
Now, as we mentioned before,
masking will often
take an offscreen pass,
so you should be very
careful about performance
when do a transformation
like this.
Finally, with snapshotting,
as we mentioned before,
snapshotting is only going to
capture what you tell it to.
So, in this case, that
content view that we are asking
to snapshot has transparency
in it.
So we can see things behind it.
But if we snapshot just that
view, we aren't going to get
that in the blur and it is
going to look a little funny.
So if we move the snapshot up,
all the way to the window is
usually the easiest thing to do,
but sometimes you might need
to move it all the
way up to the screen.
So if you are going to snapshot
blurs, you should make sure
that you snapshot as far
away from the blur content
as possible so that you are
sure you get everything you need
for it.
And so with that, let's switch
over to some best practices
with dynamics and AutoLayout.
So, the first thing you might do
is you might have fairly complex
view hierarchies working
inside of dynamics.
And what you want is for the
outer view to participate
in the dynamic system
but not the inner views.
They are just going to be laid
out like you would
with any other thing.
So you can use UIKit
Dynamics for the outside view,
just by turning translate
auto resizing mask
into constraints to true.
And, yes, in the only slide
at WWDC that says true.
And then you can use AutoLayout
to just position
everything else inside,
just like you always have,
or using the new syntax
as shown on the slide.
Another thing you can do is,
often you will have items
in the dynamic system but you
might have labels for them
that shouldn't participate,
but they need to follow.
And so Lola here
has her little tag
that says what the file name
is, and we just have this anchor
that represents our
AutoLayout constraints,
and then when dynamics comes in
and wants to move Lola around,
the label moves with it,
but the label does not end
up interacting with dynamics.
Finally you can work
with dynamics
by creating a custom
dynamic item,
just as Mike mentioned earlier.
You just subclass NSObject
or some other appropriate
object class,
conform to the UI
Dynamic Item protocol
and provide the required
methods.
A bounds some of size --
it can't be 00, or the
dynamic system is going
to throw an exception -- and you
implement center and transform,
and you use the values
of those in order
to construct AutoLayout
constraints
or otherwise change something
outside of your system.
And so to close out, we are
going to show you a demo
of how you can do just that.
So what we have got here, is,
again, a simple application
that just shows a photo.
But we want to be able to
show the user the faces
in the photo with some style.
And so when we click our dynamic
item system stretches out
and animates in that blur.
And if you click again,
of course, it will move
out with a nice little effect.
But if you keep clicking,
then you can see
that it responds very
fluidly to the dynamic system
and doesn't have
very set, rigid path.
So it's very reactive to
exactly what the user is doing.
So how do we get that to work?
So, the first thing we do is
we have this face layout guide,
and that's just a subclass
of UI layout guide,
and inside of it is a
little bit of dynamics.
We have this face layout guide
dynamic item, that, again,
subclass as NSObject and
conforms to UI Dynamic Item,
and it's going to
manage a constraint,
and by setting the constant of
that constraint to either the x
or y value of the center
point, whenever that changes.
And then in here, when you
set up the layout guide,
it's got a centerrable position
and it creates four
additional dynamic items
that represent the
top, left, bottom,
and right in that system.
We assign it the constraints
and the constraints just work
from the top left corner
of the dynamic item,
of the dynamic item
reference view,
and we use slider
attachments to limit
where those four
dynamic items can go
with respect to the position.
And this keeps it from
flying outside of the system
or collapsing to too
small of a position.
Now, in the view controller,
the way we get this behavior is
we have a gravity behavior along
with the face layout guide,
and we center them
on top of each other.
So when the gravity changes,
the layout guide will
move appropriately,
and we get the blur
effect from our storyboard,
so that we don't have to
constantly twiddle with it
if we decide we want to
change the style we are using.
And we use constraints
to attach that blur view
to the face layout guide.
So that when that
guide changes size,
the blur view will
also change with it.
Now, in order to make it look
like the blur view is cutting
out everything but the faces,
we actually have a little trick.
We make imposters from
the original image,
just cut out the images that
we want, apply a mask to them,
and create additional UI
Image Views to place on top
of the one that's already there.
And so it looks like the blur
is just dodging the faces
but what is actually happening
is you're seeing the views
that were placed on top that
have the faces cut out on them.
Finally, we have this tap
gesture recognizer that we set,
and it will be the thing
that causes our dynamic
system to change.
When we want to expose
the faces,
we just change the gravity.
So normally the gravity is
causing everything to be pulled
into the center, but
then when we flip it,
it wants to push everything
out like a repulsor.
And then we take
advantage of the fact
that we are always laying
out subviews during this,
to actually trigger the
blur animation in or out.
And that's all it takes in order
to build this really nice effect
from something that
both autolayout
and dynamics can both
provide easily for you.
And so we will go back
to slides to finish out.
So in summary, we want you
to use these technologies
to really improve
the user experience.
So when you add a
blur, you add it
so that you can put
additional information offset
from your content.
When you use dynamics, it's
so that you can have a user
interface that responds nicely
and as the user expects
to their input.
But you also want to
consider performance
when you are doing these things.
Because if you have a lot
of dynamic items on screen,
that can really bog
down the user interface,
and you don't get the nice
physics that you were expecting.
So use it with caution.
But also for visual effects,
if you have a lot of them,
you will end up with
lots of offscreen passes
and that can incur
quite a cost as well.
So these are all
the related sessions
that we have got for you today.
Unfortunately most of
them have occurred before.
There's only one that hasn't
and that's occurring with us,
called "Building Responsive
and Efficient Apps with GCD."
And we will be in the lab
after this to take all
of your questions and
help you get the most
out of what you have
got for this year.
We have got various
documentation, and assemble code
for the StickyCorners
sample that you saw earlier
in the presentation should be up
and available, and, of course,
Curt Rothert to take your
questions through email.
And I'm glad you stuck
with us on Friday.
I hope you had a great
WWDC and a safe trip home.
[Applause]