[ Applause ]
>> MIKE HESS: Thank you.
Good afternoon!
I'm Mike Hess and I'm a software
engineer on the iOS Apps
and Frameworks team and I'm here
with Johannes Fortmann to talk
to you about how to make your
document-based apps top notch.
Now we have written some
sample code for you today
which is going to show you how
to build the two main components
of a document-based app.
First, we're going
to show you how
to build a great
Document Browser
which will let your users
quickly find the documents
that they're interested
in working on.
Second, we're going
to show you how
to build a great document
editor that interacts properly
with file coordination to
deal with concurrent readers
and writers such as the
iCloud drive daemon.
We're going to get into
this a little bit later.
First, let's focus on
the Document Browser.
So what is a document-based
app anyways?
Well, we think of a document
as a single, standalone entity
and it is understood to the
user as a single entity.
A document-based app is
just going to be an app
which manages a list of these
documents and presents them
to the users so that
they can view them
or edit them or rename them.
Keynote, for example,
manages a list
of Keynote presentation
documents.
Numbers manages a list of
Numbers spreadsheet documents;
even Garage Band manages a list
of Garage Band song documents.
So we would consider all of
these to be document-based apps.
Now let's get into
how we're going
to build our Document Browser.
There are four main components
of a great Document Browser.
First, we want to
list our documents
in a way that's meaningful
to our users such as here
in our sample code we sort
our documents by file name.
Our user understands
the flow of our app.
Second, we think you
should use thumbnails
for greater document
visibility so that just
at a glance your users can
quickly identify the document
that they're interested
in working on.
Third, we want to display all
documents that are available
to our app, including
documents that exist
in other apps' containers such
as this document in the sample
which exists in the shared
iCloud Drive container.
And fourth, we think
it is a good idea
to store a recently accessed
list of your documents
so that users can quickly
get back to the documents
that they're currently
working on.
Now let's go into how we're
going to discover our documents
for our Document Browser.
Now, a naive approach might
be to use NSFileManager to try
to list your documents
in the cloud
but these results
are incomplete.
For example, in iCloud there is
a notion of document promises
where there's a document
that exists there
but content has not been
made available locally,
it has not been downloaded
to disk yet,
and NSFileManager does not pick
up these documents properly.
In addition, if you're trying
to list your documents
using NSFileManager,
external documents
are not included
so you're not listing all of the
documents available to your app.
Let's take a quick look at this.
Let's say you're using
the NSFileManager APIs.
If you're using NSFileManager,
you'll properly pick
up document one and
document two here,
which are completely downloaded
to disk in our app's container.
But you're missing the
result of document 3
which is a document
promise from iCloud,
and you're also missing
document 4 which exists
in another app's container
but our user has granted our
app access to that document.
So you don't really want to
use the NSFileManager APIs
when you're listing
your documents.
Instead, you want to
use NSMetadataQuery.
Let's take a look at how
NSMetadataQuery works.
NSMetadataQuery will pick up all
the documents that are available
to your app, including document
3 which is the document promise,
and document 4 which exists
in another app's container
but the user granted
our app permission
to view that document.
Now it is important to note
here that document 5 which is
in another app's container
but the user has not
granted our app permission
to view is still not included
in the NSMetadataQuery results
because that would be a
privacy leak if we showed
that document to the user.
So let's use NSMetadataQuery
for discovering our
documents in the cloud.
Now how does this flow
work from your app?
Well, first of all you're going
to create your NSMetadataQuery.
Then NSMetadataQuery
is going to go
through an initial gather
phase where it lists all
of the documents that are
currently available to your app.
Once this initial gather
phase has completed,
you will get a notification
and then you just have
to display these
initial documents
on your main queue
in your app's UI.
But NSMetadataQuery
doesn't stop there.
In addition, you will receive
update notifications as state
in the cloud changes such as
here the iCloud Drive daemon
downloaded a new document
to our app's container
and we were notified
in our NSMetadataQuery
about this document.
Then you just need to compute
the animations from the changes,
such as here we may want to
insert a CollectionView cell
into our CollectionView,
and then just display this
updated UI on our main thread.
Now that we know how to
discover our documents,
let's get into how we're
going to make our UI better
with document thumbnails.
Now, we think it is a good idea
to display thumbnails in your UI
because it gives visual
context to your user.
That way your user can just at
a glance identify the document
that they're interested
in working
on because they have
a great thumbnail
so they can quickly identify it.
Now new in iOS 9, thumbnails
are actually generated
for you automatically for
certain document types
that are well-known, such as
large image files, for example.
Now let's get into the
workflow of how you might want
to load your thumbnail for
display in your app's UI.
It is important to note here
that loading thumbnails involves
loading a potentially large
amount of data into
memory, which can be slow,
so you don't want to block your
main queue while loading your
thumbnail data.
Let's take an example
workflow, which would work,
which is how our
sample code app does it.
So first in our sample code
we have a CollectionView
and the CollectionView asks us
to load a CollectionView cell.
We're going to go ahead and
schedule a fetch thumbnail job
on a background queue because
we don't have the thumbnail
cached yet.
Now, we're not going to wait
for this fetch thumbnail
job to complete.
We're going to immediately
return a CollectionView cell
with a placeholder image
so that the user knows
that there is something there.
At some point in the future,
the fetch thumbnail job is going
to finish and then we'll just
notify our CollectionView
that it needs to
reload that cell
and then we'll just
display the cell
in our UI with our thumbnail.
All right.
Now that we know how to find
our documents and display them
with great thumbnails,
let's get into how
to manage a recents list.
Now we think you want
to use a recents list
because recently accessed
documents are often the
documents that a user
is currently working on,
so it is a good idea to store
a list of these documents
that your user can
quickly get back to them.
Now, a naïve approach,
again, might be to use NSURLs
to store a recents list of the
recently accessed documents,
but this suffers from
many similar pitfalls
as NSFileManager did earlier.
Let's take a quick look at this.
So let's say we store a list
of NSURLs to our documents
which are the recently
accessed documents.
But then the iCloud Drive daemon
moves the document while our app
isn't running, such as here,
it moved it into a new folder.
The NSURL is now a broken
reference and will not resolve
to the updated location
of our document on disk
so we can't really rely on
this to store our recents list.
The correct way to
store a recents list is
with security scoped bookmarks.
Here, if we store a security
scoped bookmark to this document
and again the iCloud Drive
daemon moves this document
into a folder, the bookmark will
update automatically to resolve
to the document's new
location on disk so we want
to use security scope bookmarks
when managing our recents list.
And with that, I would like
to get into a quick demo
for how we're going to
manage our recents list
and how to load thumbnails.
All right.
Let's go ahead and launch
up our sample code here.
And we haven't loaded
thumbnails yet into our app.
But for example, if I open the
iCloud Drive app using the new
Multitasking feature, we
can tell that the thumbnails
for these documents are
actually there, so we just need
to load them to display
in our app's UI.
Let's go ahead and
look at this in code.
All right.
So first of all, let's
talk about how we're going
to manage our recents
list in code.
The important thing here is
when we're saving our object
here we are bookmarking this
document using the 'bookmark
data with options' method
and it is important here
to pass the 'suitable
for bookmark file' option
so that we can resolve
it properly later.
Then on our app launch
we just have
to call the NSURL
Constructor method
of 'by resolving bookmark
data' with the bookmark
that we have saved
previously, and we'll get a URL,
which is the updated location
of our document on disk.
Now, it is important here that
with this returned URL we need
to call 'start accessing
security scope for resource,
in case this document
is a document
in another app's container,
or we won't be able
to read this document because --
read properties from
this document
because this will
extend our Sandbox
to have access to this document.
Now for thumbnails we've written
this great thumbnail cache class
for you in the sample
code, which is going
to cache our thumbnails
for our app.
It takes care of a lot of
the heavy lifting for us,
such as scheduling, thumbnail
loading on background queues,
et cetera, and notifying
our CollectionView
that we need to reload cells.
Now the only thing we
have not implemented
yet is just this block
of code right here,
which will load our
thumbnail from disk.
All we have to do is
call the NSURL method
of 'get promised item resource
value for key' on the URL
of the document with a
thumbnail dictionary key,
and we'll get a dictionary
of thumbnails.
Then we just need to extract
the UIImage from the dictionary
and return it to our thumbnail
class so that we can display it.
Now it is important here
to use the 'get promised item
resource value for key' instead
of the 'get resource
value for key' method
because the document may not
have its content available
locally yet, so we can
display our thumbnail even
if it is not downloaded yet.
Then all we have
to do is redeploy
and we have some great
thumbnails in our app,
which load in the background so
they don't block our scrolling
as we scroll through
our sample code.
All right.
Let's get back to the slides.
So what have we learned about
building a Document Browser?
First, we learned that we want
to discover our documents using
NSMetadataQuery as opposed
to other methods so that we
can discover all the documents
that are available to our app.
Second, we have learned that
we want to display thumbnails
in our app's UI so that we
can build some great UIs
and our users can just quickly
identify the documents they're
working on.
And finally, we have
learned we want
to store our recents list
using bookmarks as opposed
to other methods so that
users can quickly get back
to the documents that
they're currently working on.
And with that, I would like
to welcome Johannes Fortmann
to the stage to talk to you
about building the
document editor.
[ Applause ]
>> JOHANNES FORTMANN:
Thank you, Mike.
Now, Mike has shown you how
to build a beautiful Document
Browser in your application.
And of course that's something
that's very nice for our app
but equally as important
or possibly even more important
is the part of your application
where your user can go and
load and edit documents.
After all, that's why they're
trying to use your application.
Now, before we go into the
whole loading and writing
out change documents, we
have to take a quick detour
into a concept called
file coordination.
Now, what am I talking
about here?
Well, in our new modern
multitasking-based world we have
this concept of multiple
apps being able to access
and display the same file.
As an example we could have the
iCloud Drive app displaying an
overview of all the files that
are in your document container
at the same time as
your app is running
and the user is actually
editing this document.
Or as a more conservative
approach,
even if your user is not
actually using this two-up view
of Multitasking, there is
always going to be the case
that the iCloud Drive
syncing daemon may want
to access the document
to sync it
up to the cloud while
your user is editing.
In fact, that is a
really, really common case,
because the user is in the
middle of editing the document,
they're saving this
document to disk,
and of course now it is changed,
so the iCloud Drive daemon wants
to make sure that it is
up-to-date in the cloud.
So that's a really common case.
Let's have a look at this
specific case where your user is
in the middle of editing
the document on disk.
And the way this looks is that
your app is, of course, running.
And the user is making
some edits
and in the meantime your
application is going
through auto-saving,
do periodical writes
of this document to disk.
So we're going to have
a write at some point,
and at a later time we're going
to have like the user's editing,
and changing the document, we're
going to have another write.
Cool. Now let's just
assume for a moment
that our user is
taking full advantage
of the multitasking feature
and is at the same time
as they're editing
this document,
also launching another
application,
and this other application
might have a previous reference
to this document, and will
now immediately doing state
restoration for example, try to
read this document from disk.
Now as you can see here,
this is a bad situation
because we're reading this
document at the same time
as the other application
is writing it.
Well, that's our
application actually.
So we're going to get this
inconsistent read which,
of course, is very unfortunate.
We're in the middle of
writing this document
at the same time the other
application is reading it.
The data is halfway
written to disk.
The other half is not.
And the other app may
not know what to do
with this weird,
inconsistent data.
That's a bad situation.
And likewise, even if we somehow
manage to live around this,
after our second
write, remember,
we're still in the first
application editing
this document.
The other application will
now still be displaying your
document and this document
is now being displayed
in an old version in
the other application,
so we have got this issue
of having a stale display.
And that is, of course,
very unfortunate.
Now conveniently we have
two solutions for you here.
And that is, first of all,
we have this concept
of file coordination.
File coordination is a
distributed reader/writer
lock mechanism.
And what that means is
that, while there can be
at any time multiple
readers for a document,
there can only ever
be one writer
and the one writer excludes
all other readers from reading.
That means that if both our
applications are using proper
file coordination as they will
if they're using UIDocument,
which implements
these mechanisms,
then our read will
be moved to a time
after our write has
finished and in
such a way we have always
a consistent picture
of this document.
That's very nice.
Now, there is another
mechanism I promised you too.
And the other mechanism
here is NSFilePresentation.
NSFilePresentation
is a distributed
modification mechanism.
What that means is that our file
coordination will automatically
tell every other file
presenter that's been registered
for your document that it
has been written to disk
and that this file presenter
has to go and update itself.
That way we immediately
get a notification
after our second write and we
can be sure to update our UI.
Cool. So that's how we
can be able to make sure
that we have always a consistent
picture of our documents.
But what documents?
Of course, we first need to
create some documents to be able
to actually display and
have the user edit them.
So let's have a look at that.
What are our goals in
creating these documents?
Well, let's imagine as
our sample app implements,
we have this little plus
button in the top right corner,
and this plus button,
well, the user taps it,
we will maybe show a
template dialogue, something,
but in any case at some point
we'll create a new document.
And our main goal here is
to give the user a consistent
display that's up-to-date
at all times.
So it wouldn't help a lot
if the user tapped
this little plus button
and now we wouldn't get an
update in our Document Browser
and the user is confused and
doesn't know what happened
and will possibly tap the
plus button a few more times
and now we have five
different new documents.
Not good. Now that's the
situation that we might end
up in without using file
coordination because, of course,
what this means is that we
create a document on disk
and at some point later the
iCloud Drive daemon notices
that there is a new document
here and informs our app.
But this delay can be half
a second or something,
possibly even more if the
daemon is busy at this time.
And this exact delay is
what we want to avoid.
Now, conveniently, if you're
using a coordinated operation,
this is done directly for you.
The coordinated operation
works in conjunction
with the NSMetadataQuery
that you're using
to display documents in your
browser, and basically loops
around after the
coordination has finished
and immediately tells
your running query
that there's a new
updated document.
That way we get rid
of this ugly delay.
Of course, there's
another slight caveat here,
which is that since
we're writing to disk,
we're writing anything to disk,
it can take a bit of time.
And of course doing any
operation that can take a bit
of time on the main
queue is unfortunate
because it can block the
main queue and thus look
like a stutter in your
application to the user.
Now, the solution to
this is, of course, easy.
We want to use a
background queue
to dispatch this coordinated
operation and make sure
that our operation is not
blocking the main thread.
Now conveniently we're still --
since we're using this
coordinated operation --
we're still getting the
immediately updated display
in our UI because our
NSMetadataQuery is still
updated directly.
You don't even have to
bounce this information back
to the main queue
because we're updating the
NSMetadataQuery directly.
Cool. Now, another common
operation is deleting a file.
That's a totally reasonable
thing for your user to do.
They're done with this document.
They want to get rid of it
so it doesn't clutter
up their workspace.
And the basic idea behind
deletion is exactly the same.
We'll coordinate a write
on our background queue,
perform the deletion during this
write, and immediately loop back
to the main queue through
the NSMetadataQuery
to update in time.
Cool. So that's how you manage
creating and deleting documents
on your background queue.
So let's have a look at
what you actually want
to do with these documents.
And that, of course, is
you want to display them,
meaning you want to
read and write them.
Now, we strongly,
strongly, strongly suggest
that you use UIDocument for
reading and writing documents.
UIDocument implements both
the NSFileCoordination calls
to make sure that at
any time you are reading
and writing documents
in a coordinated manner,
as well as implementing
NSFilePresentation to make sure
that you can be immediately
informed
that this document has changed
and can update it
in your display.
So let's have a look at
how to read a document.
You create a UIDocument object
and simply call the 'open
with completion' method on
this UIDocument instance.
And what this method does is it
will take out a coordinated read
on a background worker queue.
That way your application
stays perfectly performant
and responsive, while
at the same time your document
is going to read itself in.
Now all that is there
that's left to do for you,
is that you implement the
'load from contents' method.
And this method will
simply get called
within the coordinated
read so it is encapsulated
by this coordinated read,
meaning it is totally safe
to read anything
you want in there,
from the document, mind you.
And all you have to do is
basically take the contents
and fill in your
document data from them.
Now, there's another method here
that you can alternatively
choose to implement,
which instead of taking a blob
of data, it takes an NSURL
and you can use that method to,
for example, stream document,
there may be situations where
that's more reasonable for you
to do, because, for
example, the document format
on disk is very different
than what you want in memory.
Now, after this is done,
we will simply loop back
to the main queue and
call the completion block
that you provided for us.
And in that completion block,
you can go and, for example,
push your new interface
updated for your document.
Cool. So that's how
reading a document works.
But as you remember,
Mike told you
about this concept
called promises.
And a promise is
basically a file
that the iCloud Drive
daemon promises
to your app is actually there,
but it is not yet downloaded.
And what that means
is that a read
on this document may
trigger a download.
Now, of course if you've
lived in the real world
as we all have, obviously,
downloads can be terribly slow
at times, and depending how
your document size looks,
this may take a while.
And your user may perceive
this download as a failing
of your app, which is totally
unfair, it is not your fault
that this download is being done
over a slow network
connection and takes a while.
And so, for you, new in
iOS 9, we expose a way
to display progress
on UIDocuments using the new
NSProgressReporting protocol.
Now, implementing
this is very simple.
The NSProgressReporting protocol
exposes a progress property
on your UIDocument instance, and
this progress property is filled
in by us to display to you
what kind of progress we have.
So it is basically
a simple percentage
of the download state.
Now, we expose this NSProgress
property through a state change,
so the way that you display
this is that you listen
for a state change notification
on your document state,
and when the state changes you
look at the new flag that says,
'hey, I have a progress
that I'm exposing here.'
And then you simply
display this progress.
Now, displaying a progress on,
for example, a UIProgress view,
used to be a little
bit complicated
because it exposes a
property that you have
to key value observe to put
it into this progress view.
And also we realized that, of
course, and also new in iOS 9,
we exposed an observe progress
property on the UIProgress view
that will enable you to just
plump the NSProgress directly
into the progress view.
You simply assign the NSProgress
to the progress view's
'observe progress' property
and it will automatically
update its count [applause].
That's very convenient for you.
Thanks. All that's left
for you to do is to listen
for the next state change
which signals, 'hey,
we're done with this progress.'
And at that point you want
to probably undisplay your
UIProgress view and get ready
for displaying the new
document controller.
Cool. So that's reading
documents.
Of course, we also want
to write documents.
And writing documents is very
symmetric to reading documents.
The way we write documents
is that we also take
out a coordinated
file coordination
on a background queue.
Now, this one is
slightly different
in that you're not starting it
but rather UIDocument
will automatically notice
that now is a convenient
time to save the document.
For example, because for a while
there have not been any edits
incoming, or it has been a time
since the document
was last saved,
or the user is putting your
application into the background
so now would be a
really convenient time
to save the document.
But basically the way this
is done is very symmetrical
to reading a document, we
simply call the 'contents
for type' method on your
UIDocument instance,
and you fill in the
NSData instance
that you then return from there.
Very nice.
There is one additional
thing here,
and that is that this
is a convenient time
to write a thumbnail.
As Mike told you, for some very
specific document formats we'll
automatically generate
thumbnails, but chances are
that you're not building the
exact thing that we're building,
and thus if you're not
building, using any of our very,
very well-known formats
like images or simple text,
then you will want to out
write thumbnails on your own.
Now, the way you do this is
that we will call the
'file attributes to write
to your own' method
on your UIDocument.
And in that method you simply
return a UIImage instance
as part of your attribute
dictionary.
And this instance we'll
write out contained
in the same coordinated write
that's writing your document.
That means that if the user has
at this time the Document
Browser up in a separate pane,
they'll not see an
inconsistent state.
Cool. The important thing
here is to keep in mind
that this is being called
on a background queue.
And what that means
is that you cannot
under any circumstances
use UIViews to write --
to render your thumbnail.
UIViews are not thread safe
so you have to make sure
that your thumbnail rendering is
being done using, for example,
Core Graphics, or textKit,
or any of the other thread
safe rendering mechanisms
that we provide on our platform.
In iOS 8, the only mechanism
to access a document
was through a copy.
And the reason for that
is that applications
in general do not have access
to each other's Sandbox.
So if we have two application
Sandboxes, the only way
to move a document from a
Sandbox to another Sandbox was
that the first application
caused a copy to be made
in the other application
Sandbox.
Now, we relaxed this thing
a little bit through the use
of the 'UIDocument
Menu View Controller,
which allowed your application
to do a pull of a document
in another application's
container.
But in general you could
not simply open a document.
And every open of this
document would cause a copy.
Now, of course, doing all
of these copies is
very inconvenient,
because now you have a
copy of your document
in the other application's
container and the user is going
to modify it so you have a
second version of this document.
And now, for example,
the user is going to want
to open this document
back in your application
and that causes a
third copy to be made.
Now you have these
three different versions
of documents floating around.
And that's very unfortunate,
because the user gets confused
and doesn't know which
version is the most recent.
And it is just not
a great situation.
Now in iOS 9, we have this
nice new mechanism called 'Open
in place.'
And what this means is
that your application,
through use of the document
interaction controller,
can grant another application
access to a document.
And this document is
the exact same document,
this is not a copy but rather
a reference to this document.
What that means is, of course,
that the other application
is able to simply make edits
that are then, through the
magic of file presentation,
are directly reflected in your
application, which, of course,
is very nice for the user.
And this includes
files that are open
from the iCloud Drive
app and from Spotlight.
That means that any time your
user browses their documents
in the iCloud Drive app, we
will directly be able to open
that document in place.
The mechanism behind
this is very similar
to the mechanism used by the
'Document Menu View Controller.'
That means that if your
application is already
supporting that, it
is super easy for you
to also support this mechanism.
And even if you're not
currently supporting the
UIMenuViewController,
it is super easy for you
to adopt this, because there
is really no big magic here.
You get a URL and put it
into a UIDocument instance
that's you then display.
Let's have a quick look at
how you want to support this.
As I said, it is super simple.
First of all, you have to
tell us that you support it.
Your app, remember,
is not actually,
possibly it may not be launched
at the time we're trying
to figure out whether we want
to open this file in place.
So you have to tell
us beforehand.
And you do that by adopting the
'LS Supports Opening Documents
In Place' key in
your Info.plist.
You simply set that
to yes or true,
depending on whether you
are Objective-C or Swift.
And that tells us that
your application is able
to handle this.
Now there is also a bit of
code you'll have to write,
and that comes in the form
of a new delegate method.
How does that look?
Well, let's say you already
are opening documents here.
And it is a reasonable
assumption because, well,
you're a document-based app.
So you must be implementing
a method very similar
to the one that we see here.
Your method currently
must be getting an NSURL,
and since that NSURL
is a temporary copy
that the system made for
your app, you have to be able
to copy this into
your own container
and then open this copied file.
And this is what this small
chunk of code here does.
Now, the first thing is to
adopt our new method here.
And this new method is very
similar to the old one.
It simply takes an
options dictionary
that encapsulates the parameters
that the previous method has.
And, importantly, one of
these parameters is the 'open
in place' key.
Now, all you have to do is have
a look at whether this 'open
in place' key is actually
true, and if this key is true,
then your application should
open this file in place.
That means it should
not make a copy.
Simple, you just
stop doing something
that you must have
been doing before.
And then now that you have
this URL, all you have
to do is go ahead and open it
whichever way you were opening
it before.
And that's how simple it is
to support open in place.
Cool. Let's summarize what
we have learned today.
We have seen how to make your
app very performance responsive
and beautiful using
NSMetadataQuery to display a set
of documents and to update
these documents in time
when changes come
in from the cloud.
We have seen how
to use bookmarks
to implement a recents
mechanism that allows your users
to quickly go back to the
state that they were before --
that they were in before.
And of course, something
we didn't talk about,
but which is entirely
reasonable,
you can also use bookmarks to
implement state restoration,
which allows your users
to directly go back
to the previous state
that they were in.
We have seen how
to use thumbnails
to make your application
beautiful,
and how to implement
progress display to make sure
that your user is always
aware of what happens
in their applications.
And last but not least, we
have seen how easy it is
to implement open-in-place.
Open-in-place is a great new
mechanism that allows your users
to directly open documents in
your application without having
to make multiple copies.
Now all of these concepts
are beautifully displayed
in a sample code that
we published today.
And the sample code is
basically the application
that Mike showed you
previously in the demo.
It implements all
of these features
that are creating documents,
displaying documents
in a Document Browser, animating
changes on these documents, and,
of course, writing thumbnails,
and, of course, open-in-place.
For technical support, we would
like to direct you
to our forums.
And we also have
amazing documentation
under the link that
you see here.
If you're interested
in learning more
about using the 'UIDocument
Menu View Controller'
to implement the pull mechanism
as opposed to the pull mechanism
that open-in-place implements,
so that your application
can pull documents
from another application's
container,
or if you're generally
interested in how
to implement UIDocument-based
applications,
we'd like to point you to
our session from last year,
that's session 234 last
year, and, of course,
that's online as well.
And with that, thank
you for your time
and have a great afternoon.
[ Applause ]