[ Applause ]
>> DAVE VAN TASSELL:
Good morning.
Welcome to What's New
in iTunes Connect.
I am Dave Van Tassell,
Engineering Manager
here at iTunes Connect.
I am excited to tell you what we
have been up to this past year
and where we are headed.
As many of you have noticed,
we started localizing iTunes
Connect over the past year.
We've added languages such
as Chinese, German, Japanese,
French, Spanish, Korean.
Just this week we added our
fourteenth language, Thai.
This is a long process, and
we are just getting started.
We can clap for localization.
That's okay.
[ Applause ]
As you sign in to
iTunes Connect,
we come to our Home page,
and I want to start today
by talking briefly about a few
of the areas we made changes in.
We are making changes
across the whole site.
We don't have time
for everything.
So let's start with
three to begin with.
The first is App Analytics.
We launched it earlier
this year,
and it's become the best place
to measure acquisition
to engagement.
And it requires no
code from you,
all the while protecting your
and our customers' privacy.
If you have more questions
about App Analytics, what it is,
how it can help you, and
where we are going with that,
there's a great session right
after lunch, Getting the Most
Out of App Analytics,
with Tristan and David.
I highly recommend it.
The second area is
agreements, tax, and banking.
As you may have heard,
we've unified our agreement.
With one agreement,
you have access
to both the Mac and iOS SDKs.
You go to the dev
portal, sign in,
you agree to the
single agreement.
Come into iTunes Connect,
and you set up your tax
and banking information
just for that one contract,
letting you set up paid apps
and paid in-app purchases
for both Mac and iOS.
The third area I want to talk
about is resources and help.
We are overhauling our
support part of the site,
and the best part is
an integrated search.
This will work not only
across FAQs and guides,
but also the news
and announcements
for iTunes Connect,
both past and current.
And to make this even better,
we are integrating our guides
as web pages as opposed
to downloadable PDFs.
We are going to move all
of this content outside
of the iTunes Connect login
so you can access it and link
to these pages from
wherever you want.
[ Applause ]
For the rest of the
presentation, we want to focus
on two other areas, My
Apps and users and roles.
Let's start with My Apps.
We are introducing a cleaner
organization to the tabs inside
of My Apps, as well
as a pricing redesign,
and some TestFlight updates.
So starting with
the organization.
Today iTunes Connect is broken
into seven distinct tabs:
Versions, Pricing, Prerelease,
In-App Purchases, Game Center,
Reviews, and Newsstand.
And we want to simplify
this a little bit.
First off, we are going
to create a new tab called App
Store, and we are going to put
in your version information,
pricing information,
as well as reviews.
Then we are going to move
all the In-App Purchases,
Game Center, and
Newsstand features
into a tab called Features.
Second, we are going to
take Prerelease and split it
into its two distinct areas:
TestFlight for managing
your internal
and external tester
information as well
as your TestFlight
builds, and also Activity,
where you can get information
on all of your builds,
whether they went
through TestFlight or not,
as well as your version status
history and Resolution Center.
Looking more into App Store,
in your version information,
there's a lot of metadata
to get your app ready
for the App Store.
Some of this information, it
changes from version to version
to version, such as
your What's New text,
your description,
or your screenshots.
Other information
tends to stay the same,
your app name, categories, EULA.
We want to break this into two
separate lists, your app info
and your version information.
Both of these lists
will be reviewed
with each version
submission, but we are going
to separate two distinct
areas under App Store,
App Info and Versions.
Next under Versions, I want
to talk about version release.
When you submit your
app to App Review,
you decide what happens
after it's approved.
You can have automatically
release as soon
as App Review has
approved your version.
We begin processing for
App Store right away
and enter Ready for Sale.
Alternatively, you can choose
to manually release your app.
When you do this, after App
Review has approved your app,
it goes into Pending
Developer Release.
At this point, you can
continue to invite internal
and external testers
through TestFlight;
you can request promo codes,
and they will download this new
and improved version as
opposed to the one live
in the App Store; and if
you find any critical bugs,
you can dev reject your app,
fix the bug, upload and submit,
and put it back into the system.
Whenever you are ready
to release your app,
you log into iTunes
Connect, and you decide
at what point it begins
processing for App Store
and enter ready for sale.
We are adding a third
new option,
which is called Scheduled
Release, and for this,
you can choose the date and
time when your app will move
through processing
for App Store.
[ Applause ]
So just like manual
release, after it's approved,
it's going to go into
Pending Developer Release,
but instead of you logging into
iTunes Connect, we'll move it
for you at that given
date and time.
And iTunes Connect is
going to look like this
under the Version tab.
Come in here and
select which option
of version release
control you want.
So we now have three choices.
Automatically release goes
as soon as it's approved.
The second is a manual release,
you log into iTunes Connect
and click "release
this version,"
and the third is a scheduled
release, where after approval
and after your selected date
and time, then we release it
for processing to App Store.
Let's talk about
some pricing updates.
Longtime users of
iTunes Connect,
you know we haven't made
a lot of changes to the UI
on the pricing section.
So along with a general redesign
of this page, I want to call
out some more subtle
features we are adding.
The first is in selecting
your tier.
We are going to add in the
customer price into the tier
in your preferred currency.
What is a preferred currency?
This is an iTunes Connect user
setting where you can choose
which currency we are going to
show in that tiered drop-down.
We are going to start it based
off of your contract location,
but you can log into iTunes
Connect and change it anytime.
Once you've selected your
currency, you can view
that same tier and all
the other currencies.
We've also made a
change to the All Prices
and Currencies section.
Here you can select up to
five different currencies
and see them side by side on the
screen, across all of the tiers
for these five currencies.
With that, I want to invite
Jennifer Stuart onto the stage,
and she is going to
give us a demo of some
of these new features
in iTunes Connect.
Jennifer [Applause].
>> JENNIFER STUART: Hi.
I'm Jennifer.
I am going to walk
you through some
of the changes we have
coming up in iTunes Connect.
So I have an app in the
App Store, and according
to App Analytics, it's
doing really well in Italy,
but I think I can
do even better,
and localizing my app
will really do the job,
so I am going to
do three things.
The first thing I am going to
do is boost my marketing efforts
by localizing my app in Italian.
The second thing I am going to
do is carefully time the release
of this new version to coincide
with some other marketing
efforts I have in place.
The third thing I am going to
do is set up a special price
for the week of this
new release.
So let's get started.
Okay. So we are starting off
at the My Apps page here,
and I can see - I'm
going to go into my apps.
I can see my app here,
TouchFighter III.
I will click on it.
As Dave explained,
app information has
the metadata fields
that get updated
less frequently,
so these fields are
now on their own page.
Our first task is to
create a new localization.
I am going to click on the
locale here on the right,
and that will show
us localizations
that we have been set up for.
You will see that Italian
is not in this list,
and I can't create it just yet.
I will need to create
a new version.
So on the left nav here, I am
going to click on New Version.
We get a modal asking for
a new store version number.
I am going to give it 1.0.3,
and then click Create.
This will create the
new version for my app,
and I will also be brought right
to the version's
specific details.
I have my English text
ready for What's New.
And now I am ready to create
my Italian localization.
I will click on the
locale here and scroll
down and find Italian.
And that adds my localization.
I have my What's New text
also for that ready to go.
So the next thing I wanted
to do was carefully time the
release of this new version.
So I am going to scroll
down to version release,
which is towards the
bottom of the page.
So before we just had the two
options, manual and automatic.
With manual release, after my
app was approved by App Review,
I would need to remember to
come in on the day I wanted
to release my app
to the App Store.
With automatic, it would release
automatically, but maybe not
on the exact day
I had planned for.
So with this new option, I
can set up a date and time
for when I want it to release,
and it will move to Processing
for App Store on
that date and time.
After App Review.
So I am going to select July
1 here in the date drop-down.
And this is based on my local
date and time, just so you know
that when you are setting
that up for your app.
So I think everything
looks good here,
so I am going to click on Save.
And the last thing I wanted to
do was set up a special price
for this new version's
launch date.
To do that, I am going
to click on Pricing
and Availability
in the left nav.
You will see we have
this All Prices
and Currencies link
on the right.
I am going to click
and open that up.
So I can take a look
at all the price tiers
and what the price tier
will be in each storefront,
and I can change what
storefronts I'm comparing
by clicking on the
storefront name at the top.
I am going to go and
select Italy here
to see how the different tiers
compare in that storefront.
And I can see my
proceeds as well.
So I think I know which
tier I am going to move
to for my special price.
I am going to close this window.
And now I am going to click
on Plan a Price Change.
And here, under Price, I
am going to select Tier 1.
And you will see that we have
this Other Currencies link here
below, and now I can see what
this tier will look like,
what the price will be, and
what my proceeds will be
in each storefront
for this tier.
So again, we have our marketing
plan going on for July 1,
so I will go ahead and select
July 1 here, and we are going
to run this special
price for a week.
So I am going to go
and select July 8
and the end date
and then click Done.
So you can see that the app
will go on sale on July 1
and then return to its original
price at the end of the week.
This all looks good to me,
so I am going to go ahead
and click Save at
the top corner.
So that completes
all our main tasks.
And just so you are aware,
everything I've done just now
can also be done via XML feed.
If you'd like to learn more
about how to make these kinds
of updates via XML, check
out the session called
iTunes Connect: Development
and Distribution at 3:30
in the Mission Room.
There will be a portion
of that session
that covers this process.
Now I will walk you through
some additional changes we have
in iTunes Connect.
I am going to go
under Features tab.
If I have an in-app
purchase that I want
to also add a localization
to, I can go to Features
and In-App Purchases, and this
will list my in-app purchases
that I have for this app, and I
can create new ones by clicking
on the plus symbol next to
the header, or I can click
on the name to add
the localization.
As well, we have Game Center
under Features as well.
And here I can see my
leaderboards and achievements
and create new ones by
clicking the plus symbol next
to the header.
We also have Newsstand
in this section.
If this was a Newsstand app,
I can manage my Newsstand
issues there.
I can also see the builds I
have uploaded under Activity.
These are the builds
I have uploaded
for each version
would be shown here.
As Dave mentioned, we've
also updated the Resources
and Help section, so
let's take a look at that.
So you don't even need to be
logged into iTunes Connect now
to access this content.
There's four main sections here.
In the News section, you
can read about updates
to iTunes Connect and the latest
information about the App Store.
There's a Video section
where I can watch tutorials
and feature walkthroughs.
You can find style
guides, checklists,
and sample content
in the Guide section.
Lastly, look for your answers to
your questions in the FAQ area.
Most recently updated
questions will get badged,
so you can easily find those.
The great thing is we
have a Search field here
that will search
across all the areas,
and you can find exactly what
you need easy and quickly.
So I am going to type in
Trends and see what we got.
So you can see we get responses
from all the different areas.
So that gives you a little
preview of what we have coming
up for iTunes Connect,
and with that,
I will give the floor
back to Dave.
[ Applause ]
>> DAVE VAN TASSELL:
Thank you, Jennifer.
We are excited about
these changes
that we're making
to iTunes Connect.
Let's talk a little
bit about TestFlight.
One person likes TestFlight.
[Applause] There we go.
We launched TestFlight
last year,
and it quickly became
the best place
to beta test your iOS apps.
No provisioning profile
is required.
We automatically generate
the sandbox accounts
for your in-app purchase
testing.
And with the release of
Apple Watch this year,
TestFlight also supports
Apple Watch.
And there's two kinds of
testers for TestFlight.
You have your internal
and external testers.
I want to talk a little bit
about the differences
between those.
So your first is internal.
Internal testers are your
fellow iTunes Connect users.
They are part of your team.
You invite them to TestFlight
with their iTunes
Connect user name.
But when they accept their
invitation, they accept it
with their personal
App Store account.
It doesn't have to be the same
as their iTunes Connect
user name.
There's no beta app review
for internal testing.
For external testers, all
you need is an email address,
and again, when they accept
their TestFlight invitation,
they will do so with their
personal App Store account,
which can be a different email
than the one you
invited them with.
With external testing,
we do require beta app
review with new versions.
What are new versions?
Let's talk about that.
There are two keys that are
important in Xcode when talking
about TestFlight,
versions, and builds.
The first is your CFbundle
short version string.
This is your version.
And the second is the CFbundle
version, or your build.
So when you select a build
to go into external testing,
let's go with version 1.0,
build 100, this is going to go
through beta app review.
As you upload and
submit subsequent builds
to the same version, we ask,
have you made any
significant changes?
And if you haven't made
any significant changes,
then the beta app review
process is much quicker
for these builds.
Once you are ready to start
inviting external testers
to a new version -- in
this case, version 1.1 --
this version will go through
the same kind of beta app review
that your initial build on
version 1.0 went through.
Another difference between
internal and external testing is
which build is available
for your testers.
So for internal here,
we have version 1.0,
and it's the latest build, build
101, that is always available
for your internal testers.
As we switch to testing
version 1.1,
the last build we've uploaded,
103, is what's available.
If I upload a new build, it will
automatically be distributed
to the internal testers.
Whereas for external
testers, you get to select
which build they see, so we
can start with build 100,
move on to build 102, all the
while our internal testers were
a little bit later
on in build 103.
I'd like to turn the time
over to Jason Gregori.
He is going to give us a
demo of TestFlight and talk
about some new features there.
Jason?
[ Applause ]
>> JASON GREGORI: Thanks, Dave.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Jason.
I am going to give you a
quick preview of what's coming
with TestFlight in iOS 9.
Okay. Let's get started
with the new TestFlight tab
in iTunes Connect.
To get there from the My
Apps page, click on your app,
and then click on
the TestFlight tab.
Right away, you can see internal
and external testing
have been broken
into their own separate
sections.
Not only does this help with
clarity, it also allows you
to give two completely
different versions of your app
to your internal and
external testers.
Here in the internal
testing section,
you can see the current
build being tested,
your internal testers,
and their current status.
After you've selected the
version of your app you want
to beta test, internal testers
will always get the latest build
sent to them automatically
without beta review.
That means once you set internal
testing up, you don't even have
to come to iTunes
Connect at all.
New builds uploaded to iTunes
Connect just automatically go
out to your internal testers.
To change the current version
you want your internal testers
to see, click on the Select
link over on the right.
Here you can choose
which version
of your app internal
testing gets builds from.
Remember that the
version number comes
from your app's CFbundle
short version string,
and the build number comes
from its CFbundle version.
Down below you can
see your testers.
You can see a little
information about them
and whether they've
accepted your invite
or installed your app.
You can also add or
edit testers from here.
Let's add another tester.
Everyone eligible for
testing but not yet invited
to the app shows up here.
Remember, you only have
up to 25 internal testers,
and for someone to be
eligible, they must be
on your iTunes Connect team.
Let's add Eric.
After I add and save, Eric
will get an invite sent right
to his inbox.
Over on the external
testing side,
you'll see your currently
testable builds as well
as your external testers.
The great thing about
external testing is
that you get a thousand tester
slots, and to add a tester,
all you need is an
email address.
There are some new changes
to external testing.
One, you can now give your
external testers a completely
different version of your app
than your internal testers.
Which is great for letting
external testers test the latest
minor update while
internal testers are
on the next big release.
And two, you can now
submit a version of your app
to beta review while your
external testers continue
to test a different
version of your app.
[ Applause ]
Okay. Let's look at adding
a new version to test.
Clicking the Add link brings
me to the build chooser.
Notice I am specifying exactly
which build external
testers will get.
Let's add this build.
We are immediately taken
to a submission page
for this specific build.
Unlike for internal testing,
external testers always get What
to Test information,
an app description,
and a feedback email address.
Next up, export compliance.
Don't you wish you could
just skip this page?
Well, now you can.
Dave will show you later
in this presentation.
But for now, I will just
answer the question.
After submitting,
we are taken back
to the external testing page,
and we can see our new
build is in review.
Notice how even though I have
a new build in beta review,
my testers still have access
to the build they were
previously testing.
I can even swap out the build
for one that's already
been approved.
Let's add an external tester.
I'm going to add my friend Ben.
All I need to add Ben
is his email address.
I want to again point out here
that the email address you use
for a tester does not
have to be their Apple ID.
Any email address
they have access
to on their iOS device
is perfectly valid.
Once they accept the invite,
your app will become linked
to their logged-in Apple ID.
What this means for
you is don't worry
about which email
address you use.
Now, I just save,
confirm, and I am done.
The invite is sent.
Now, you might be
asking yourself,
where do all the old builds go?
I am glad you asked that.
[Laughter] They go to the
TestFlight build section.
The build section includes
not just the old builds
but every single build
you've added to TestFlight.
You can view each build's
current internal status,
external status, and the number
of times it was installed.
Click on a build, and you can
see even more information,
including who tested it and
detailed technical information.
All right.
Let's move on to
the TestFlight app.
Here's an invite for our app.
Right in the email, I get this
nice, big Start Testing button.
Now, if I don't have
the TestFlight app,
tapping Start Testing
will take me
to the App Store to install it.
Or if I am in a third-party
browser or email client,
I will get options to
install or open TestFlight.
Since I already have
TestFlight installed,
it's going to take me straight
into the TestFlight app,
where I can view and install the
beta, which I will do right now.
Since this beta supports Apple
Watch, I get this Watch bar app
at the top, which lets me
install the WatchKit app right
onto my Watch right
from in TestFlight.
TestFlight will support both
watchOS 1 and watchOS 2 apps
and will install the best app
supported by the user's Watch.
I am happy to report TestFlight
will also auto-install beta
WatchKit apps if
that's your preference.
We are also adding a new
screen for incompatible apps.
When a tester has a device
that doesn't support your app,
they'll now get a new screen,
which helps explain
what's going on.
Here's an iPad app with
instructions on how to get it.
Open TestFlight on your
iPad, much more obvious.
Another change we are making
is adding more control
over notifications.
Down at the bottom of this page,
there's a new Notifications
button.
Some people prefer to
get only email updates,
some prefer to get only
push notifications,
and in the new notifications
menu, you can choose
to turn push notifications
and email notifications on
or off on a per-app basis.
And there you have it.
Back to you, Dave.
[ Applause ]
>> DAVE VAN TASSELL:
Thank you, Jason.
I want to recap one of the
changes that Jason talked about,
and this is about your
internal and external testers.
The ability to let your
internal testers be working
on one version -- in
this case, version 1.1 --
and your external testers
can then be invited
to a completely separate
version, version 1.0.
Some other changes we
will be rolling out are
about the metrics
for TestFlight.
Today we support installs,
counts across your builds
and versions, and we will be
rolling out the same metrics
for sessions across builds and
versions as well as crashes
at your build and version level.
[ Applause ]
And all three of these metrics
will also be able to show you
at the tester level,
so you can then see
which testers are
having the most success
and which testers are having the
most problems, and you can reach
out to them with that same
email address they gave you
when you invited
them to TestFlight.
In iTunes Connect,
it looks like this.
You can see those numbers for
installs, sessions, and crashes.
I'd also like to talk about
some new TestFlight limits.
Currently, you can upload two
builds a day, and we are going
to bump that up to six
external builds a day.
We also want to increase the
number of apps you can have
in active TestFlight
from 10 to 100.
[ Applause ]
That one was worth
clapping about [Laughter].
Build expiration,
we are going to bump
that up from 30 to 60 days.
[ Applause ]
Internal testers, 25 unique user
names per account, we are going
to change that to
25 users per app.
And then for internal testing,
we want to go from 1,000
to 2,000 external
testers per app.
[ Applause ]
Today for TestFlight,
you can TestFlight all
of your iOS 8 apps.
Also with Monday's
C1 release of iOS 9,
you can invite your internal
testers to test those apps,
and we have Apple
Watch support 1.0.
Later this summer, we will be
extending iOS 9 beta testing
to external testers,
as well as watchOS 2,
and we will begin
supporting app thinning
and ODR support natively with
the App Store infrastructure
that you will be using when
your customers get their hands
on these same apps.
Those are our changes
to TestFlight,
but as Jason mentioned, we
have a change around encryption
and export compliance.
We have added a new
tab under Features.
Today, when you submit your
app, whether it's for beta
or for the App Store, we ask,
does your app use
any encryption?
And based on the encryption
that you use, we require upload
of export compliance
documentation.
So we are going to
add a new plist key
in Xcode called ITS app
uses nonexempt encryption.
Enter False in here, and that
will let us know what kind
of encryption that you use.
If your app does use nonstandard
encryption, answer Yes.
And then you can go back
into iTunes Connect,
tell us about the encryption,
upload the correct export
compliance ERN documents,
and we are going
to give you a code.
With that code, you can
enter that into Xcode
with the plist key ITS
encryption export compliance
code, and we will link
the encryption you told us
about in iTunes Connect with the
build that you are uploading,
and you can reuse this code
across many different builds
to let us know the form of
encryption you are using.
If you change your encryption,
log back into iTunes Connect,
let us know about it, upload
the correct documentation,
we will give you another code,
and you can use that code
with the builds that support
this new version of encryption.
And those are our
changes to My Apps.
I want to talk about
users and roles,
and there's three new features
we are going to be introducing.
The first is account switching,
the ability to use one user name
to log into multiple accounts.
[ Applause ]
The second is app siloing,
where you can separate
which apps different
users can see.
[ Applause ]
And the third are some
new users and roles
to help with these features.
Let's start with
account switching.
As you log in, you
have your user name,
you log into your account,
and as you get access to more
and more accounts, you create
new user names for each account.
With account switching,
you'll be able
to use a single user name to log
into all these different
accounts.
But with each account, you have
different apps that you see,
you have different roles.
So we will make it so that as
you log in and you can switch
which account that
you want to view,
will change those
apps that you see.
You will get those roles and
permissions that you have
for the account that
you've now moved to.
And that's account switching.
Every account starts with
one user, your admin user.
As you start adding more and
more apps to this account,
you start adding
more and more users.
Most of these users
are technical users,
but what you found is you want
some users to see some apps
and some users to
see other apps.
So what we are going to do is
we are going to separate this
into three different areas.
We also realize that Technical
User is a little bit broad,
so we are going to
deprecate Technical
with a new role called
App Manager.
This App Manager will be
able to manage these apps
in iTunes Connect for you.
We are going to add two new
roles, Developer and Marketer,
to help out with this.
Let's talk about what
these roles entail.
In App Manager, they will
be able to create users,
change pricing, invite new
people to these different roles
that we have, as well as
submit apps for review,
both beta and for App Store.
The Developer role will be able
to do developer kinds of things,
upload the binaries,
view the crash logs,
and view the store
metadata in iTunes Connect.
Marketing role will be
able to actually change
that stored metadata in iTunes
Connect, upload promo art,
as well as request promo codes
for the apps on your team.
All three of these
roles will be eligible
for internal TestFlight
users, as well as have access
to create in-app purchases,
leaderboards, achievements,
and view Resolution Center.
And these are the changes
that we are rolling
out for users and roles.
[ Applause ]
So what's new in iTunes Connect?
We have a new version release
control, a new pricing design,
separate TestFlight versions
for internal and external users,
increased TestFlight limits,
new encryption plist keys,
account switching, app siloing,
and new users and roles.
And all these features will
be coming out later this fall.
Now, each year we like to ask
App Review if they had a chance
to help explain to some
developers, such as yourselves,
what could I impart on you
to help your apps make it
through App Review better?
And they give us a list.
This year they have
gone one step better
and they have a web page
you can look up and see:
What are the common rejections?
What problems are
people are having?
Such as your demo account info.
If your app requires a login to
function, you need to provide
that in iTunes Connect
beforehand.
Or if you have an in-app
purchase that requires services
to be running before the in-app
purchase works, have that ready
at app submission time, not
just when you want your app
to go live in the Store.
This is a really great web page,
and I highly recommend
checking it out.
We also have another web page
about what makes good
information about my app.
What makes a good name?
What is a good description?
This is another great resource
for understanding your metadata
and filling that out well.
And the third page
I want to talk
about is dedicated
just to app previews.
We launched this last
year, and it's a great way
to give your customers
a dynamic feel
for what your app is
before they download it.
You want to know what it
is and how to get started?
Check out this page.
Now, for more information,
of course,
the iTunes Connect Guide
is a great resource.
The dev forums as well.
We have our Evangelist,
Mark Malone.
If you have any questions,
these are all great resources.
I want to call out
some related sessions.
We had one on Tuesday about iAd,
as well as one earlier this
morning all about app thinning.
Later today, Getting the
Most Out of App Analytics
and iTunes Connect: Development
to Distribution will
be this afternoon.
And with that, I want
to wish you a great rest
of your conference.
Have a good day.
[ Applause ]