[Applause]
>> JONO WELLS: Good morning.
Welcome to using Safari
to deliver and debug,
a responsive web design.
My name is Jono Wells.
I am an engineer on the Safari
and WebKit team with Apple,
and I'm really excited
to talk to you today.
I have a great privilege
of being able to develop
for the Development
Tools that are a part
of the Safari web browser.
I feel I'm privileged
because I love the web,
as I'm sure you do.
I think Safari is
a great browser,
a really great platform.
It deserves world-class
Development Tools,
wouldn't you agree?
Especially because we are
not just making content
in the web browser, we're making
content in our apps as well,
using web views and so
we want that content
to run great and look great.
So this morning, of course
we're going to be talking
about Web Inspector, a tool most
of you have probably
used before, hopefully.
We're also going to be talking
about a brand-new tool called
Responsive Design Mode.
With these two tools together
we're going to very rapidly
and very smartly improve
the quality of our site
and get a good solid
responsive design as a result.
Let's begin by talking
about Web Inspector.
This is Web Inspector,
of course.
This is the one you've been
working with for the last year.
We've come up with a lot
of great new features.
We've also gotten some
great feedback from you
over the last year
about the interface.
We took a lot of that to
heart and we changed things
around a little bit so
this is the Web Inspector
that we're releasing with
this release of Safari.
Here it is.
[Applause]
>> JONO WELLS: I suspect
some of you may be applauding
because there is a
dedicated elements tab
as you see up there.
We have a tab based
interface, all the tools
that you would expect in Web
Inspector are here; resources,
timeline, the debugger, the
storage tab and a console tab.
But these are tabs so of
course you can get rid of ones
that you want to
get out of your way
if there are tools
you don't work
with as often you can just
move them out of the way,
you can reorganize the ones
that are already there,
if you want to bring one back,
you just hit the plus button
on the right-hand side and open
up whichever one you want to.
We give you the ability
to customize Web Inspector
to look more like what you
want, to work the way you do.
We've made improvements
to the interface there.
Now let's talk about
what new things we can do
with Web Inspector and
how it can help us.
The first one is, it can
help us get great performance
out of our content.
It helps you get
great performance.
Now it almost dragoons you
to get great performance
and we'll talk about how.
What do I mean when I
say great performance?
The gold standard as I'm
sure most of you know,
is 60 frames per second, because
our screens are refreshing
at 60 Hertz, 60 times a second.
This means that if we are trying
to render a smooth animation,
right, for any given
rendering frame, right,
in a turn of the event loop
we need to make sure all
of our scripts, our
timers, and our layout
and rendering can happen
within 16.67 milliseconds.
If we blow this budget, then
our animation will stutter
and that's not something
that we want.
How can we get better
information
to help us debug the
performance of our content?
We have this idea.
What if you could just
look at the content
and every time a paint occurs,
we just flash a region
of the screen?
We added something
called Paint Flashing.
When you're in the elements tab,
in the upper right-hand corner,
you will see this paintbrush.
Click that, turn that on.
When that is lit up blue, every
single time a paint occurs
on your page it will light up
red with a translucent red box.
You're going to want to
try this on your content.
It going to light up
like a Christmas tree.
It is amazing!
It's going to look like a game
of Simon if you ever played
that with a kid -- as a kid.
That's going to give you a sense
that perhaps you're
painting too often,
there's too much
happening on your page.
But what about what's
happening behind the scenes?
To help you get more
information there
and get you towards 60 frames
per second performance,
we've added a great new tool
called the Rendering Frames
Time Line.
If you go to the time
lines tab you can get to it
by clicking right here
on Rendering Frames
and this is the interface
you will see.
When -- so you can
record, use your site
and we will start
drawing these bars.
Each one of these bars
represents a rendering frame.
They're segmented into
different colors based
on what is happening
in each frame.
Purple for scripts, event
timers and such, red for layout
and rendering and gray for
behind the scenes engine work
that the engine is doing.
The goal is to keep each
of these bars underneath
the middle line right here,
the 60 frames per second line.
If your bars tend
to go above that,
it means you're possibly
not going
to be getting 60 frames
per second performance
and we want to work on that.
You can select a region of
the bars just like you can
on the other timeline, and
we're going to show you a lot
of good information about that.
First of all, we're going to
show you this graph right here,
this is an aggregate of
the different activity
that is happening in
that particular region.
We're going to give you a
breakdown of each frame.
You can open up every
single rendering frame
and see exactly what's
happening.
For things like event
timers and rendering,
style and validation inside of
your code we have the ability,
of course, to click to the
relevant line of source codes
so you can see what's going on.
We also show you this table
of timing information.
One of my favorite things to
do, I have been using this
for a bit, what's been really
helpful for me is to sort
by total time for reach
Rendering Frame and then I open
up the one on the top
because it is most likely
that the most offensive
frames are at the top
and then I can see what is
holding back my performance.
This tool is going to tell you a
great story about your content.
Even if you think you're
performing well, you're going
to want to hookup
to this and see
if you can get additional
performance out of your site.
It tells you a great
story, it allows you to do
without thinking, that's really
what we want our development
tools to do.
Just to put the information out
in front of you and say here,
here it is, you don't have
to work too hard to get it.
One of the things that we've
been noticing is that you have
to jump around between
different tools
within Web Inspector a lot.
We thought it'd be great if you
could focus on a particular one.
More often if you can
just stay in one tool
that might save you time.
We've done this in a few ways.
One of the ways is for errors
and warnings we don't just
show those in the console now,
we show them in a
few other places
so that you can spot
them more quickly.
In the debugger side-bar
for instance on the left,
any resource that has an error
warning we'll just show them
underneath, they'll appear so
you can just jump right to them.
In all of the JavaScript code in
your site, we'll show the errors
and warnings in line so
you'll see those messages.
So if you're just browsing,
everything will just show up.
It's a lot nicer.
We have also improved the
way they look in the console
so errors and warnings,
they're highlighted,
the colors are easily
distinguishable.
They just look better too,
we've made the fonts
better, it's great.
We have this other idea,
and again we want to Do
Without Thinking, we want
to put important
information in front of you.
JavaScript of course, is a
dynamically typed language.
That means that the engine
itself assigns the types
for you, you don't have to.
This is what's happening
behind the scenes in this case.
Right. We have a string, we have
an integer, we have an object.
If you're working
with some code,
here's a function
that's designed
to add two numbers together,
and this is a mistake
that might happen.
We're accidentally passing in
a string, and so that is going
to lead to some unexpected
results we're going
to call a dysfunction.
This is something that you can
discover by trying to debug,
and play around with
your code, might be a,
in a more complicated case,
might be hard to
find this error.
But, what if you could
see something like this
where we just show you
as your code is running,
we show you the types
that have been assigned
to all the different variables,
passed in as parameters,
or return from functions.
We created just such a thing.
We call this the
Type Profiling Tool.
If you look in the
upper right-hand corner
when you're looking
at any JavaScript source you'll
see this T button right here.
If you click that, from
that point forward,
when your code runs, your code
is going to go from looking
like this to looking like this.
[Applause]
>> JONO WELLS: I love this tool!
It's so cool!
I've been using it a lot
working on Web Inspector.
We're going to show you as
best as we can type information
as your variables
are assigned values.
You'll also notice that some
of the code is grayed out.
Since we're tracking what
code has been covered,
any code that hasn't
been reached
yet will be grayed out for you.
So this also serves as a
great code coverage tool.
Right. It going to
allow you to see
if a function isn't being run
or if an else condition isn't
being reached, things like that.
You'll also notice that we
show you the return value
from a function.
In this case I have a function
that's returning something
called a DeveloperPerson,
it's a class I wrote.
You'll also notice that
we're showing you the name
of that object.
If you have constructer
functions, right, like this one,
if you're using this classical
model using prototypes
and you construct an object that
way, we will show you the name
of the constructer function.
We'll do the same
thing of course,
if you're using ES6
classes which just landed
in this release, we'll show
you the name of the class.
Obviously parameters can
get past multiple values
over the lifetime
of your application.
What happens if you
have multiple types?
For objects here is
how we handle it.
Let's say I have a
function called register.
Right. So we're going
to register somebody
for a conference or
something like that.
Say I call it once, and I
pass in a new DeveloperPerson.
Well, we're just going to show
you that it's a DeveloperPerson.
If we pass in another object,
say a ManagerPerson,
we'll show you that.
Let's say we pass in
both a DeveloperPerson
and a ManagerPerson, then
since they both have a
common ancestor, person,
that's what we're
going to show you.
If we pass in something
else that isn't
in this inheritance chain at
all like an extraterrestrial
for instance, we'll
just show you object,
because of course everything
derives from object, right?
Now here are all the different
types that we might show you.
If there are multiple types,
a string, and a number
that get assigned to a value,
this is what you're going to see
in your code, it's just
going to show you many.
There is an exception to this,
say you have a simple type
like a double and it's a
double sometimes and it's null
or undefined sometimes, we'll
just add a question mark
to the top, that means
it's double sometimes
or sometimes it's a null value.
This is such a nice feature,
I just want to show
you a few more shots.
This is code from
the Web Inspector.
It's just really nice.
It gives you a bird's eye
view of what's happening
with your application.
You can quickly spot behavior
that isn't interesting to you.
Right. Here is an
object assignment.
Again, you can see the coverage,
you can see areas
that are grayed out.
This has been incredibly
useful in my development
with Web Inspector,
I think you're going
to find it just as
useful as well.
This is the type profiling tool.
[Applause]
>> JONO WELLS: All right.
We have also made
improvements to the console.
In a similar way
we want to be able
to put really useful
information in front of you
without you having
to work too hard.
Here are some objects that we
have launched in the console.
And you're going to
notice a few things.
The first one is that
we're creating --
we give you object preview,
so you have really good
looking object previews
so you might spot information
inside your object much
more quickly.
You're also going to
notice something else,
every time something is
output to the console,
we're going to store it
in a variable for you.
This starts at dollar sign
1 and then dollar sign 2,
then dollar sign 3,
on and on and on.
You can reference
them again just
by putting them in the console.
This is great.
The feedback that we got
from you, because these used
to represent recently selected
elements in the elements panel
and the feedback was that really
everyone was only using one
of those, which is dollar
sign 0, so don't worry,
that's still the currently
selected element, still there,
it'll still work as you
expect it to, but starting
with dollar sign one, those'll
be recently logged variables.
That can be really useful,
right, if you're paused
in the debugger and there's a
value in the scope that you want
to remember, you no longer have
to go into your source code
and create a variable just
for debugging purposes
and then save it,
and then run the app,
then delete it later, or forget.
You don't have to do
any of that anymore,
we'll take care of that for you.
What about when you open
up one of the objects.
You're going to see this.
It's a lot nicer.
First of all, we've
just improved the look
and used colors to
distinguish the different types
of information that can
be inside of an object.
Everyone of the objects
inside has its own preview.
You'll notice that this
is an array, siblings,
this one has a special
type of preview,
we've created special previews
for certain things, Maps, sets,
weak sets, weak maps, promises.
Right. We show you the types
of the objects inside the array
and the size of the
array on the right.
When you open it, we show you
the index of each object inside.
Of course, each of
those have a preview.
I want you to notice here
that we also have
made it a lot easier
to inspect the prototype
chain so I can then open
up the prototype for developer
person and for person,
and I might see something
like this.
I love this very much.
This gives me the ability to
essentially get an API view
of my object in the classes
that constructed this object.
Look at this.
I can quickly spot and see okay,
I have a function called
change name that takes
in a first name and last name.
I have a custom setter
called firstName.
I have a custom getter
called fullName.
I can tell that because
there's an eyeball next to it.
I can click on that eyeball
and it'll actually
run the custom getter.
This is almost better than the
documentation in some cases.
It is even great for
native API exploration,
and some of you are
probably thinking,
I can't remember how local
storage works, no problem,
just put it in the console.
I can see all of the functions,
it looks a lot better,
it's really nice.
Really great for
object exploration,
if you're exploring
third-party APIs, it's great.
It's not just in
the console, either.
Anywhere we show object views,
for instance, if you're paused
in the debugger and you have the
view of the variables in scope
on the right, or when
you're mousing over,
a variable in the source
view, let me show you that -
same beautiful object views
in all of those places.
Nicely organized for the type
of information that is in there,
you're going to spot
information more quickly
and that is really the
goal of all of this.
I now would like to invite my
friend and colleague Andy Estes
to come up to the stage and
he's been working on a site
that he's excited to
show you and maybe some
of these tools will
help him out.
Andy.
[Applause]
>> ANDY ESTES: Thank you, Jono
and thank you to all of you
for being here this morning.
I'm really excited to be here
and show you these new
tools in Web Inspector.
First, a bit of a confession, I
was up late last night working
on this site, I wanted
it to look good.
It's supposed to display a
bunch of photography I've taken
and I think I've introduced
a bug and if you don't mind,
I just want to see if I can
figure out this bug I introduced
and fix it real quick
so I'm just going
to go into Web Inspector.
By the way, if you never
opened the inspector before,
you do it from the develop menu
and you don't have a
develop menu in your Safari,
it's really easy to
enable, you simply go
to Safari's preferences,
and in the advanced tab
you'll see the option,
show development menu in mini
bar, I already have that checked
so I'll just go right in there.
I'm going to say Develop,
show Web Inspector.
It will open this up along the
bottom and right away I see
that I have an error
here in the console.
I can click it, it looks like
undefined is not an object,
I can jump to the debugger,
I even have the error here
in the side-bar, I can click it,
it'll take me right
to the line of code.
Let's take a look at this.
Somewhere in this line of code
I'm seeing an undefined value
where I don't expect it.
Now typically what I would do
is I would set a break point
and maybe spend some time
debugging but I don't have time
for that, instead I
think I'm just going
to enable the type
profiling to see if maybe
that can tell me
where my error is.
I'm going to click this T
to enable type profiling
and I'm going to
reload the site.
Great, so there's my error.
And now my source
code is annotated
with these helpful pills
that tell me the types
of all my variables.
Let's just see if we can
quickly work this out.
I have galleries,
which is an array.
I have current gallery
which is an imager.
The result of that
shouldn't be undefined
but I initialized
galleries up here,
and one of the things I'm
noticing is that the body
of my four loop is grayed out,
that means that code hasn't
been covered, and it looks
like that's because gallery
data itself is undefined.
That's somewhat unexpected,
I should be passing a
valid gallery data in here.
Gallery data itself comes from
this variable, this.options,
let's take a look
at where I set that.
I do that up in my constructer
for navigation galleries
controller.
And it does look like I'm
passing a valid object
to the constructer, I see
the object pill right there.
I'm not passing a null or
some other kind of type.
Let's find where I construct
navigation galleries controller
and see if that tells
me what my mistake is.
I'm going to just copy this.
I'm going to use Web Inspectors'
global search and I can get
to that by command-shift-F
and it will search all
of the resources in the site.
And I have exactly one place
where I have a navigation
gallery controller,
it's right here and I
immediately spot my mistake.
I was expecting to pass an
object that had gallery data
as a property, instead I'm just
passing gallery data directly.
Let's fix that real quick.
I can use the convenient
ES6 shorthand syntax
for declaring a new
object that's going
to have both the property
name as gallery data
and also the value as
gallery data's value.
I made that change.
When I'm editing local files
in Web Inspector I can
save those changes directly
and Web Inspector will prompt me
just to make sure I really want
to over ride a local file and
of course, I do in this case.
Once you do that once for a
file, it'll never ask you again,
it'll just save directly.
Let me reload, and
see if that worked.
There we go, so now I have
my beautiful photography
that I totally took myself.
This is looking really great.
You can see that I have these
galleries, I've laid them
out so they take up the
full width of the display,
I can hover over them to see
the name of the galleries
and I also have this logo in
the middle I can hover over that
to see a menu that comes out
to the side and you'll notice
that occasionally these
galleries rotate between photos
and I have a nice
dissolve effect to go
from one to the other.
I want to make sure that
this transition is as smooth
and as efficient as possible so
hopefully some of these tools
that Jono told us about
will help me do that.
The first thing I
want to do is I want
to turn on paint flashing.
I'm going to go to
the elements tab
and the paintbrush tab is
here, I'll select that.
Now you can see the
red rectangles
as the images transition
from one image to the next.
The first thing I'm noticing
is that for the duration
of that transition, I see
a solid red rectangle,
that indicates to me that I'm
probably painting every single
frame of the transition.
Now, I wonder if
that's too expensive?
What I'd like to use
is use the I want
to use the frames timeline
to tell me whether I'm
doing too much work
and maybe blowing my budget
for a 60 frames per
second animation.
I can switch to the
timelines tab.
And I can see that when I
reloaded it automatically
recorded a timeline for me so
I don't need to do that again.
For the most part, you know,
this is looking really good.
It's looking like I'm staying
within 60 frames per second.
But there were some frames
here that exceeded my budget
like this one right here.
I can click and drag to
select a subset of this
and then you can see that
it filters the records tab
to just include that subset.
I can expand some of these and
see the work that was done,
style and validation,
recalculation,
time refiring, things like that.
Here's one that's interesting.
It's telling me that an
animation frame is fired based
on request animation
frame, it's even telling me
that I've invalidated
a style and it's going
to let me jump right
to that line that did
that style invalidation.
That's right here.
In fact, the way this animation
is working is I'm using request
animation frame and each frame
I'm running with a duration
of one second, I can even pause
here and inspect these values.
Running for a duration
of one second
and I'm just animating the
opacity value from zero to one
over that duration
of one second.
It looks like, at
least in some cases,
this animation is
too expensive to stay
within my 60 frames
per second budget.
I've actually been
planning to transition this
to a CSS transition instead
which I think might
be more efficient.
Let's do that and see if
things get a little better.
I'll select this.
I still want to set this
current class on the image
and I'll talk about that later.
I want to comment
out the rest of this.
I can save that local resource.
I'll confirm that.
Let's go to the elements
tab and I can use the picker
to select one of
these galleries.
I'll choose this one.
Down here we can see that
there are three images
that are stacked on
top of each other.
The one with the
current class right here,
is the one that's
currently being displayed.
In the side-bar I can actually
see what style properties
that current class has.
Right now it is Z index 3.
Let's add some more
properties here.
For one I want to
animate its opacity --
or I want to set its
opacity to one then I want
to use a transition
to animate opacity
over one second using a
linear animation curve.
I'm going to make those changes.
I'm going to save again and
I'm going to reload the page.
Great. Right away you can see
that there is almost no
flashing going on here.
There is an occasional flash
in the beginning and the end,
but for the rest of the time
there is no flashing whatsoever.
That indicates I've gone from
doing software compositing
in my request animation frame
code to letting the engine do --
to composite the opacity
and hardware which is going
to be a much faster,
smoother experience.
This is looking pretty good but
I'm actually seeing a problem.
I did see one frame animate but
then none of the others did.
It looks like I might have
introduced some sort of bug.
Let's see if we can
figure out what that is.
I happen to know that
in my code I am --
that there's show
next image right here.
Show next image returns
a promise --
let me reload so we can
actually hit my break point.
Show next image is going
to return a promise,
when the promise is
resolved I'm start a timeout
for the next animation.
We can even log the promise
here, show next image
and it is going to tell me
that the state is pending.
This may not be surprising
that it is pending
because I'm pausing
the debugger,
I might not have let the code
that will eventually resolve
that promise run, so
let me resume here.
These start animating
every 2 seconds,
and so by now this
promise should be resolved
if everything is
working correctly.
Even though I'm no longer
pausing that function,
I still have that promise
bound to dollar sign 1
so I can just inspect it again.
I can see that it's
still pending.
I actually think I know
the mistake I made.
I'm going to go back
to my animation frame
and I can see here that I was
resolving the promise at the end
of the request animation frame.
The last animation
frame but I'm not doing
that with the CSS transition.
Let me just fix that real quick.
I'll use an on transition end
listener and resolve that.
Let me save that
change and reload.
And of course I hit
my brake point again.
So let me reload again.
Great. Now we see these
smooth hardware accelerated
transitions, everything
seems to be looking great.
We can see how we can use
these powerful features
like type profiling,
paint flashing,
Rendering Frames
timeline, improved console,
improved debugging to
quickly identify our issues
and fix them.
Thank you, and back to Jono.
[Applause]
>> JONO WELLS: Thank you, Andy.
So I think you're going
to find really great use
out of this tool.
You're going to want to take the
new features in Web Inspector,
make your site faster, use
the paint flashing tool,
use the rendering frames
timeline and try this in iOS,
this works of course, if
you're connected to a web view,
or Safari on iOS, you
should really try this out.
Performance is particularly
critical on those devices.
Make your code better.
Use the type profiler to get
a lot of great information,
play with the console, play
around with native APIs.
Right. Use these to work
smarter and to work faster.
That's what we have
introduced with Web Inspector.
Now let's go ahead and
talk about a new tool.
It is called Responsive
Design Mode.
It is new in this
release of Safari 9
and we'll show you what
it is in just a moment.
First I want to talk about
responsive design for a moment
and why it is particularly
important now.
I'm sure most of you know
what responsive design is,
it is making sure that your
content will automatically fit
and give a great experience
for any screen size.
It is particularly important
that you do this correctly.
Now, up until this point some
of you may have said, well,
I can just, you know, sniff the
user agent string, I can figure
out what kind of device I'm on.
I know that I'm running a
web view inside of an app,
I know exactly what
devices I'm targeting.
So I don't really need
to do responsive design
the way it was meant to be.
We've made that a bit
trickier for you now
because of multitasking.
Now web views might be resizing,
you don't exactly know how
wide they're going to be
and they're going to be resizing
without reloading your content.
Right. We want to instead
of targeting a device,
we want to make sure we're
using features like @supports,
media queries, source set,
serving different pixel
resolution images to your users,
we want to make sure that
our content will stretch
to any screen.
To help you do that
without having to go,
and open up the iOS simulator
and play around, we have brought
to you a new tool that going
to help you test your layouts
and just make sure that
they're properly responsive
and give you some ways
to test them in the sizes
for our devices as well.
That's Responsive Design Mode.
You can find it in the develop
menu and when you turn it on,
your content will
shrink to this view.
This is Responsive Design Mode.
It has a few interesting
features and the first one,
we have handles on the side so
you can stretch your content
as small or as big
as you want to.
It will actually automatically
scale so if you want
to simulate your content
on a giant 70-inch display
let's say, you can do that.
We also built in navigation with
presets for all of our devices
so that you can automatically
set it to different screens.
We actually have built in all
the multitasking configurations
in here as well, as you
will see in a moment.
For the iPads that are up there,
you can click, it will show you,
it'll automatically
resize your content
to those configurations
We also allow you to test
to make sure you're covering
1X, 2X, and 3X images.
Additionally, we
do give you a tool
to set the user agent string
because you might need
to support a very old
browser, legacy browser
and make sure you get away
from using user agent strings
to target the different screens
that your concept will run on.
Right. To be forward thinking.
This tool will help
you make sure
that you don't break anything
when the user agent string
changes and make sure
that you have properly gotten
away from that as well.
Now to show you this tool in
action and how it can be useful,
I would like to bring
Andy back up to the stage
to take his site a
little bit further.
Andy.
[Applause]
>> ANDY ESTES: Thank
you, again, Jono.
Let's just jump right in
to Responsive Design Mode.
Here we are.
I currently have a preset
set for the iPad mini 3.
Let's also explore some
of these desktop sizes.
One of the great things about
this is I can actually size it
to a resolution larger
than my monitor.
Right now you can see that I
have a width of 2536 pixels
which is definitely
larger than this monitor.
So that's useful, but I already
knew that my site looked good
on desktop Viewport sizes.
I want to make sure that
everything works well
on iOS devices as well, iPhones
and iPads, I can click these
and quickly cycle through,
here is an iPad error
in landscape mode.
Here are some of the
multitasking modes.
If I keep going it'll rotate
to portrait and I can also look
at the multitasking modes there.
I'm starting to notice
that in some
of these configurations
my site --
the Viewport is really
too narrow to be useful.
For example, I really can't
see much of these photos
if I rollover this menu,
the text is clipped.
This isn't a really
good experience.
Let's see if I can make
some changes to make this --
make my site more responsive
at these types of Viewports.
I'm going to bring the Web
Inspector back up again.
One of the great things
about this tool is
that you can use the
Inspector in conjunction
with Responsive Design Mode.
Let's dock it on the side
so that I have more
screen real estate here.
Let's turn off the
paint flashing
which is annoying at this point.
Let's do a few quick changes.
First off, let's get rid
of this logo in the middle
since the menu doesn't
have room to fit,
I don't think it's
worth displaying
and I also show the names of the
galleries on hover so let's set
that to display non-grade.
In terms of these images,
I have so little screen real
estate I'd really like them
to take up the entire Viewport.
Right now I'm specifying
that they are using 50%
of the Viewport width and
height, let's make that 100.
Great. So now I have just
one gallery per screen
which is really nice.
Now you'll notice I have these
hover effects which works great
on a desktop but on iOS
devices you won't have hover
and I also don't have my
menu it would be great
if this text is just
always there.
Let's explore doing that.
I'm going to enable the
hover pseudo class here.
You see that it displayed.
There are a few things
that happen on hover.
The first is that the
UI is capacity one,
but let's just make
that always happen.
Second, you will notice
there is an overlay
that goes to opacity 0.
Let's just make it
always opacity 0.
I have my labels all the
time which is what I want.
One more change I want to
make, I went to the What's New
in WebKit session
yesterday and I learned
about this new feature
called Scroll Snap Points,
and I would love it if as I
scroll through the galleries
if it snapped exactly
to each gallery.
I'll try to add that real
quick, I'm going to the body tag
and I'll do a WebKit scroll
snap type, make it mandatory
and then I'll do WebKit
scroll snap points
and in the wide direction
I'll repeat every Viewport.
Let's look at that.
Perfect. Beautiful,
it just snaps right
into place as I scroll.
I really like that.
There is a number of other
changes that I have decided
to make, and I have actually
baked these into a media query
that I've added right here.
I'll just uncomment that and
save it then reload my site.
You can see I added a little
text scroll to see more
at the bottom, which is nice.
I moved my icon to
the upper right,
it doesn't bring up a menu.
And now with these settings --
this is looking good
at this Viewport,
let's make sure things work
well at other Viewports.
If I go to the wider size, I
still get my original design,
and then as I go down
to smaller sizes,
I see the narrow Viewport
responsive design.
This is great.
It is really easy to use
this tool in conjunction
with the Web Inspector to
see how your contents look
at different Viewport sizes
and make quick changes
to effect the design.
Thank you, and back to Jono.
[Applause]
>> JONO WELLS: All right.
Andy, thank you for
showing us that.
That's Responsive Design Mode.
If you're not doing responsive
design for the content
of your applications or
for your web content,
now is the time to start.
It is a good idea
because, again,
something like multitasking
just come out of nowhere just
like that and mess
your content up.
You don't want that to happen.
We have added Responsive
Design Mode.
The focus is on layout, image
resolution and being able
to stay focused in Safari
in the Development Tools
so you don't have to leave and
go off to simulator or a plug-in
of an actual device
to test your layouts.
We have all the presets
for the devices we make,
you can set your own
presets as you saw,
it works right alongside Web
Inspector so you can debug
as you normally would.
This is new in Safari 9.
It is a really cool tool.
Try it out.
Along with Web Inspector you
now have a very powerful set
of tools to take your designs,
make them smooth, feel great,
make sure that they're
error free and make sure
that they work across
different screen sizes.
When you leave here please
-- first of all, get OS X,
El Capitan, get the
developer release,
if you don't have it already,
turn on the develop
menu in Safari.
Customize Web Inspector to your
liking, play with the interface,
because I think you're
really going to like it.
It is a lot cleaner, everything
is a lot easier to find.
Play around with paint flashing
and the rendering
frames timeline.
Even if you think that you
have the best performance
that web content has ever had in
the history of all web content,
this will tell you
something about your site
and how it is working on WebKit,
how it's working in Safari,
right, and you might discover
something you didn't know.
Right. The second I use paint
flashing for the first time
for instance I had a site,
I discovered I had
some painting happening
in the background I didn't want
that was stuttering the
animation for everything else,
I was able to eliminate it.
It just happened immediately.
It was great.
Use the type information
profiler.
Right. Take -- we're going to --
this tool, it takes all
of the code, makes it look
like a light bright board if you
ever played with one of those.
It's amazing, it's going to
give you great information.
Play with that.
Play in the console
with the object views,
try Responsive Design Mode.
With all of these tools, use
them to make your content shine.
Now, it is really important
that we get feedback from you.
We very much want your feedback
on these new tools and so
for that, you should send
questions or ideas to Jon Davis,
he's our web evangelist
and you can reach him
at web-evangelist@apple.com.
We also have these
resources here for information
on developing with Safari,
resources for Safari developers
and the Safari developer
library.
In the second link right now
there is a document called
What's New in Safari 9.
To learn more about
these features,
plus all of the new features
on the platform itself
you'll definitely want
to check out that document.
Also, we have two labs coming
up for Safari and WebKit,
we have win right after
this session and Andy
and I will be there along with
many developers and engineers
on the Safari and WebKit team
to answer your questions.
There is another one
on Friday at noon.
Please come, check it out.
We'll answer questions,
get help for the content.
I hope you enjoy the
rest of your conference.
Thank you very much for
being with us this morning.
[Applause]