[Applause]
>> RAV DHIRAJ: Good afternoon.
Welcome to WWDC 2015.
[Applause]
>> RAV DHIRAJ: And the first
of two What's New
in Metal sessions.
So we have a lot of Metal
content to cover this week
across three sessions.
In fact, we've added so
much new stuff to the API,
that we've decided to
break the What's New
in Metal session into two parts.
So today, I'll be focusing on
providing a high-level review
of the Metal ecosystem
over the last 12 months.
Developers like you have
already created some tremendous
applications using Metal.
I'll then talk about
some of the new features
that we're introducing
this year, and we'll end
with a specific example of
how Metal integrates well
with the rest of the system
by describing a technology
called app thinning.
In the second what's new in
Metal session, Dan Omachi
and Anna Tikhonova
will provide details
on a great new support
library that we're introducing
in Metal this year or two great
new support libraries rather,
MetalKit which provides
convenience APIs that allow you
to create a great
Metal application,
and Metal Performance Shaders
our highly optimized library
of shaders that you can call
directly from your application.
And finally in the last
session, Phil Bennett will dive
into great techniques for
taking advantage of --
for extracting the best
possible performance
out of your Metal applications.
We'll be introducing our
new GPU System Trace tool
in this session, so be
sure to check it out.
We introduced Metal at
WWDC last year for iOS 8.
Our goal was a ground-up
reimplementation of our graphics
and compute APIs to give you
the best possible performance
on the GPUs in our platform.
So we achieved this by getting
much of the software between you
and the GPU out of your way.
To better illustrate this
let's look back at an example
that we showed last year at WWDC
that describes the work done
by the GPU and The
CPU per frame.
In this example the top bar
represents the time spent
by the CPU and the bottom
bar represents the GPU time.
So as you can see, we're
currently CPU bound
and the GPU is idle
for part of the frame.
So with Metal we're able
to dramatically reduce
the GPU API overhead
and effectively make the GPU the
bottleneck in the great frame.
So the great thing is that this
allows you to take advantage
of this additional CPU idle
time to make your game better.
You can add more physics
or AI for example,
or you can issue more draw calls
to increase the complexity
of your scene.
But we didn't just stop there.
Metal also allows you to
move expensive operations
like shader compilation and
state validation from draw time
which happens many thousands of
times per frame, to load time
which happens very infrequently,
and even better in some cases
to build time, when your users
don't see any impact at all.
Additionally, with iOS 8 we
not only introduced compute
or exposed compute for the
first time on our iOS devices,
but we also provided you with a
cohesive interoperability story
between the graphics and
compute APIs allowing
to you efficiently interleave
render and compute operations
on Metal capable devices.
And finally, with Metal,
your application is able
to make efficient
use of multithreading
without the API getting
in your way, allowing you
to encode for multiple threads.
And the results have
been stunning.
So last year we showed
you Epic's Zen Garden demo
where they used Metal to
achieve ten times the number
of draw calls in the scene.
We also showed you EA's Plants
Versus Zombies technology demo
where they used Metal to bring
their console rendering engine
to the iOS platform.
Now this set a high bar for
the development community.
And over the last year
we've witnessed the release
of some truly astounding titles
that have taken great
advantage of the Metal API.
Titles like the MOBA Vainglory
by Super Evil Mega Corp
that used Metal to achieve 60
frames per second in their game.
Disney's Infinity: Toy
Box 2, Metal enabled them
to bring their console,
graphics,
and game play experience to iOS.
Gameloft Asphalt 8, they were
able to improve their gameplay
by using Metal to render
three times the number
of opponents in the game.
But it's not just about games.
With the new version
of Pixelmator
for the iPhone they're
using Metal
to accelerate image processing
in their powerful
new distort tools.
In fact, the response has been
overwhelming, with a number
of key content and game
developers now adopting Metal
on OS X.
And much of this content has
been enabled by our commitment
to bring the leading
game console engines
to the iOS platform.
This includes Unity,
Epic's Unreal Engine 4,
and EA's Frostbite
mobile engine.
Last year we also showed you how
Metal fits in the big picture
of how your application
accesses the GPU.
On the one side we
have our high-level 2D
and 3D scene graphs APIs
that give you incredible
functionality and convenience.
And on the other
side with Metal,
we provided a direct
access path to the GPU.
So this gives you an amazing
range to do what's right
for your application, and
if you choose to use one
of the higher level
APIs, the great thing is
that we can make
improvements under the covers
and you can benefit from them
without us changing a
single line of code.
Well this year, we're
happy to announce
that we've done just that,
and we're bringing the power
and efficiency of Metal to
the system-wide technologies.
We really believe
that this is going
to improve the user
experience on our platforms.
This is also a great year
for Metal capable devices.
The iPhone 5s and the iPad
Air were the headliners
at WWDC last year, and with the
introduction of the iPhone 6,
the 6+, and the iPad Air 2,
we now have an incredible
install base
of Metal capable devices.
But of course we
didn't just stop there.
We're happy to announce
that we're bringing Metal
to the OS X platform.
We have broad support for Metal
across all our shipping
configurations.
In fact, Metal is supported on
all Macs introduced since 2012.
This of course means
that we have support
for all three GPU venders:
Intel, AMD, and Nvidia.
And the other big news is that
we're bringing all the tools
that you're familiar
with using on iOS
to the Mac platform as well.
This includes the Frame
Debugger, the Shader Profiler,
and all our API analysis tools.
This is huge.
We understand the challenges
of debugging complex graphics
and compute applications,
and think that these
will be invaluable
in your development
efforts on OS X.
And of course, all of this is
available in the seed build
of OS X El Capitan that
you can download today.
So Metal on OS X is the same
API you're familiar with using
on iOS with a few key additions.
With new APIs to support device
selection, discrete memory,
and new texture formats, Metal
makes it incredibly easy for you
to bring your iOS
applications to OS X.
And here are a few examples
of developers who've
done exactly that.
So you heard in the keynote that
we've been working with Epic
to bring their iOS
Metal development code
to a Unreal Engine on the Mac.
Well, Epic used Metal and
their deferred renderer
to create this amazing
stylized look in Fortnite.
Additionally folks at Unity
brought up their engine
and demonstrated their
Viking Village demo
in only a few weeks.
It's really great to see this
content on OS X on Metal.
And we've been working
with a number
of additional Mac developers to
enable them to access the power
of the GPU through Metal.
So you also heard in the keynote
about digital content
creation applications.
Developers like Adobe, they're
using Metal to access the GPU
to accelerate image processing.
The guys at The Foundry
have also been using Metal
to accelerate their 3D
modeling application MODO.
And here today to talk about
their experience adopting Metal
in OS X is Jack Greasley
from the The Foundry.
[Applause]
Welcome Jack.
>> JACK GREASLEY: Thank you Rav.
Hi. I'm Jack Greasley.
I'm head of new technology
at The Foundry.
And at The Foundry we create
tools for digital artists.
Our software is used around
the world in games, movies, TV,
and film, including some
photo real Peruvian bears,
mutant monster hunters.
But it's not just
about the virtual.
Some of our design customers
like Adidas actually make things
and if you ask a
designer they'll tell you
that any product is a result of
thousands of little experiments.
We understand this process
and we create our tools
specifically to support it.
MODO is our premier 3D modeling
animation and rendering system.
It is used to make games,
films, product design,
lots of different things.
Our users create stunning
imagery and animations
for things both real
and imaginary.
In our latest version
of MODO 9.01,
we revamped out GPU renderer,
the aim was to provide a
fluid interactive experience
with a highest possible
quality to designers.
The benefit of this is that if
your viewport is realtime you
can make tens of decisions
in the time it would take
to do a single software render.
We had already done some
early work with Metal in iOS,
but a couple of months ago
we got a great opportunity
to start working
with Metal on OS X.
So we put together a small
team and set them a challenge,
we gave them four
weeks to see how much
of the new MODO viewport
they could bring over
and get running on Metal.
And we almost immediately
got some stunning results.
Although it's only
a small triangle,
it actually represents
a huge milestone for us.
Once we did that, we
were able to very,
very quickly make progress.
And our plan of attack was to
really work from the bottom up,
and to start bringing
the functionality
from our new viewport
over onto Metal.
So here on day one we
started with the environment.
We added a few more triangles.
A little bit of shading started
to make this look a little
bit more like a real car.
Putting in the soft shadows
and specular highlights really
added a little bit of bling,
and everybody loves shiny.
And so here we are,
four weeks later,
and you remember
that single triangle?
We got some incredible results.
Putting this all back into Metal
gave us a fully functional view
port running inside of MODO
on Metal in just four weeks.
One of the great things for us,
is this gives us a standardized
renderer across iOS and OS X,
we created a WYSIWYG workflow
between the two platforms.
So, what did we learn?
The first thing we learned is
that working with Metal is fun.
I've spent 20 years
working with OpenGL,
and I can tell you having a
nice lean easy to use API is
like a breath of fresh air.
Secondly, the debugging
and optimization tools
in Metal are absolutely
fantastic.
As I have said, if you have
done debugging on GPUs,
you know why this is important.
Metal can also be really fast.
In some of our tests, we
got three times speed-up,
and that's using exactly the
same data on the same GPU.
Going forward we have some big
plans from our new viewport
and we're actually looking
to integrate it into all
of our tools across The Foundry,
so hopefully we'll be
seeing the Metal cropping
up in interesting
places very, very soon.
So I'm going to hand you back
to Rav, and thank you very much.
[Applause]
>> RAV DHIRAJ: Thank you Jack.
That was fantastic.
Okay, so I'd like to now
talk about the new features
that we're introducing in
iOS 9 and OS X El Capitan.
And there is a lot of them.
This is a just a selection
of the features we've
added this year.
Now I don't have time to talk
about every single one of these,
so I'm going to focus
on a subset,
including GPU family sets,
our new memory model,
texture barriers, our
expanded texturing support.
Of course, as I mentioned
before, you can learn more
about MetalKit, Metal
Performance Shaders,
and our new Metal
System Trace tool
in the sessions later this week.
So let's dive right into them.
I would like to start with the
GPU, our Metal feature sets.
Metal defines collections of
features that are specific
to generations of GPU hardware.
Metal calls these GPU families.
So a GPU feature set is defined
by the platform, iOS, or OS X,
the Family Name,
which is specific
to a hardware generation,
and a version that allows us
to augment the feature
set over time.
It's really trivial to
query the feature set,
simply call supportFeatureSet on
your Metal device to determine
if that GPU family is supported.
So here is our iOS
feature set matrix.
Now you'll notice
that we have support
for two major GPU families and
versioning to differentiate
between our iOS 8 and
our iOS 9 features.
On OS X the GPUFamily1 v1
feature set represents the
features that we're going to
be shipping in OS X El Capitan.
This defines the base for
a Metal capable device
on the desktop platform.
Now I would like to talk
about two new shader constant
updates APIs that we're adding.
First a little bit
of background.
So for every draw
that you encode
into command buffer there's
some constant data you need
to send to the shader.
Now it will be incredibly
inefficient for you
to have a separate
constant buffer per draw
so generally most Metal
applications allocate a single
constant buffer that
they have per frame.
They then append the
constant data into the buffer
as they encode their draws.
So what does the code look like?
Well, first we have some setup
for the constant
buffer and the data.
Then just like in that
diagram, within your draw loop,
you send in the new
constant data
or you pen the new constant
data into your constant buffer.
Now it's worth noting that the
setVertexBuffer call here is
actually doing two things.
It's setting the
constant buffer,
and it is updating
the offset in it.
Now, of these two
operations, it's that call
to set the constant buffer
that's the most expensive.
So Metal now has
APIs that allows you
to separate these two operations
and move that expensive call
to set the constant buffer,
or the vertex buffer,
outside of your draw loop.
If you have thousands
of draw calls per frame,
this can be a significant
savings.
But if you only have a small
amount of constant data,
it might be more
efficient for Metal
to manage the constant
buffer for you.
So Metal now has the
setVertexBytes API,
you can use this to append new
constants at every draw call.
Actually there is one more
thing I want to say about that.
So that API is great if you only
have a small number of constants
as I said, and that's tens
of bytes of constants.
If you have larger constant
sets you really want
to use on of the other APIs.
There's a good chance that
it'll be way more performant.
All right let me talk about
the new memory model now.
So, our goal with the
new memory model was
to support both unified
and discrete memory systems
without you having
to make much change.
Now Metal supports
discrete memory now,
and that's high speed
memory that the GPU
on some desktops have access to.
So the way we've
achieved this is
by introducing new storage
modes that allow you to specify
where the resource
will reside in memory.
So the modes are shared,
private, and managed.
So I'll talk about
each of these in turn
over the next few slides.
Let's start by talking about
the shared storage mode.
So this is the mode that's
in the existing implementation
of iOS 8.
So in a unified memory
system, the memory that you use
to store a buffer or a texture,
is shared between
the CPU and the GPU.
There's only one
copy of the memory
and the memory is coherent
at command buffer boundaries.
So this means that you
have to just be done
with the GPU before
accessing it with the CPU.
This makes it very easy to use.
But now new in iOS 9 and in OS X
El Capitan we're introducing the
private storage mode.
So private memory can only
be accessed by the GPU
through render, compute,
or blit operations.
The advantage of private
memory is performance.
Metal can store the data in
a way that's more optimal
for the GPU to access, by
using frame buffer compression
for example.
Private storage mode
also works really well
with discrete memory systems,
and you can put your resources
into the memory that the GPU
has the fastest access to.
And now new in OS X, only,
we're introducing the
managed storage mode.
With managed memory the
resource has storage
in both the discrete memory
and the system memory,
and Metal manages the coherency
between those two copies.
Now this gives you the
convenience and flexibility
of the shared storage mode, and
in most cases, the performance
of the private storage mode.
And if you have a desktop system
with a unified memory system,
you don't have to worry
about managed having
any extra overhead.
There's only one copy of the
resource that Metal maintains.
So there are a couple
other considerations
with managed resources if
you're going to modify the data
with a CPU or the GPU.
So first, if you modifying
the data with a CPU you have
to let Metal know by calling
the buffer didModifyRange
or the texture replaceRegion
APIs.
Likewise, if you want
to read the data back,
you'll need to call the
synchronizeResource API.
It's also worth noting that you
need to wait for the operation
to be complete before you
actually read the data
with the CPU.
So let's look back at that
shader constant update example I
showed earlier.
So this example is
currently using shared memory.
So in a discrete memory system,
you ideally want the constants
to be in discrete memory.
Now you could possibly do
this with a private buffer,
but you'd have to manage
the transfer to that buffer.
It's actually a lot simpler
to use managed buffers,
it makes it really easy.
There is only two
things you need to do.
First, you have to specify
the managed storage mode
when you create the
constant buffer, and then,
you have to call
didModifyRange to tell Metal
that you've now updated
the constants with the CPU.
And that's it.
The rest of the code
remains exactly the same.
It's worth noting that
buffers are shared
by default on all platforms.
On iOS, textures are
shared by default as well,
but on OS X we chose to
make the default mode
for textures managed,
because it allows you
to write portable code without
sacrificing performance.
But there are some cases
where you don't want
to use a managed texture.
This is one of them.
When you have a frame buffer
or a renderable texture,
then you want to use
the private storage mode
to get the best performance.
This is particularly important
if the GPU is the only
one accessing the data.
And that's our new
memory model in Metal.
I'd like to talk about
two new features in Metal
that are specific to OS X that
I think you'll really like.
The first is layered rendering.
So the intent of this API is
for you to be able to render
to a specific layer of a texture
for every triangle
that you draw.
So this could be the
slice of an array texture,
the plane of a 3D texture, or
the face of a cube texture.
So on a per triangle basis,
you can specify which layer
to render into by simply
specifying the array index
in your vertex shader.
The game Fortnite used this
very technique to render
into the faces of
a cube map for some
of their environmental lighting.
So we think you'll find
this equally useful.
The second feature
that's specific
to OS X is texture barriers.
So by default GPUs tend
to overlap the execution
of their draw calls, and you
can't reliably use the output
of one draw call in a subsequent
one, without some form
of explicit synchronization.
Metal now has an API that
allows you to insert a barrier
between these draw calls.
So this is critical
for implementing efficient
programmable blending on OS X.
The API is really easy to use.
Simply insert the barrier
between the draw operations
that you want to synchronize.
And last, but certainly
not least, I want to talk
about our expanded texturing
support in Metal this year.
By default the max
limits for all textures
in iOS have been
increased to 8k.
We've also added cube
array support on OS X,
and bumped up the
quality of anti-aliasing
across the board in
all our platforms.
We've also significantly
flushed out the pixel formats
that you can write to, or
read from, a compute shader.
Also new is a texture
usage property.
So this allows you
to tag textures
to tell Metal how you plan on
using them, and Metal will try
to optimize for that usage.
So for example, if you
have a renderable texture,
you want to set the renderTarget
and shaderRead flags.
And this will tell Metal that
you plan on both rendering
to that texture, and
then sampling from it.
By default, the usage is unknown
and Metal won't make any
assumptions about how
that texture is used,
allowing Metal
to use it anywhere
in the system.
Unlike iOS, the desktop
GPUs prefer
to have a single
depth stencil texture,
so we've added two new
combined depth stencil formats.
The 32-8 format is supported
on all our hardware,
both iOS and OS X.
The 24-8 format, however,
is only supported on some.
So if it means your
precision requirements,
you'll have to check
if it is available.
So let's talk about
texture compression.
So the type of compression
format you use depends
on the device you're
targeting and the type
of data you're encoding.
On iOS we support a number of
these formats including PVRTC,
ETC2, and EAC, and
new for GPUFamily2,
we're also supporting ASTC.
So ASTC has a very high quality
compression, better than PVRTC
and ETC at the same
equivalent size.
It also allows you to encode
a number of different formats
from photographic
content, height maps,
normal maps, and many more.
It also provides a very
fine-grinned control
between size and quality,
offering between 1
and 8 bits per pixel.
And at the low end, this is half
the storage required for PVRTC.
And finally, as I previously
noted, this is only available
on GPUFamily2 capable devices,
so you'll have to
look out for that.
Finally, in OS X we're
introducing all the native
texture compression formats
that the desktop GPUs support.
Now, these BCn formats should
all be familiar to you.
If you've worked on a desktop
platform or game console before,
you likely have assets that
are already in this format.
And that's our expanded
texturing support
and the features that
I'm going to cover today.
So I'd like to change
topics and talk
about a new technology
called app thinning.
You might have heard
about it in the last talk.
So this is not specifically a
Metal feature, but it does rely
on the GPU families I discussed
earlier in the session.
First, to set context, the
typical game development
and deployment flow
for a developer
on our platform looks
something like this.
You generally have
an art pipeline
that generates some assets.
The assets are built via Xcode
or your custom tools pipeline
into a binary and then that
binary is sent up somewhere
to the App Store,
and that specific
or that very same
binary is deployed
to the devices of
all your users.
So this works great.
But as soon as you start
having assets that are specific
to the capability of a device,
you start running
into some issues.
For example, if you have
assets that are specific
to Metal devices, and assets
specific to legacy devices,
you currently have to
download both versions
to all your users' devices.
So obviously this is not ideal.
App thinning let's you solve
this problem by allowing you
to tag assets by capability
and then only the
asset that's needed
for the device is actually
downloaded to the device.
So how do we do this?
Well, app thinning allows
you to define capability
across two axis, GPUFamily
version and device memory size.
Now this creates a matrix
that you can then use
to target specific devices.
So let's look at a
typical normal map example.
Ideally you want to store
the normal maps compressed,
and EAC is a great
format for that.
But since some legacy devices
don't support compressed
textures or EAC in
particular, you probably want
to have an uncompressed
version of the asset as well.
So app thinning allows
you to tag these assets
and only download the compressed
one to the Metal capable device,
and the uncompressed
version to the legacy device.
But app thinning is actually
a lot more capable than this.
So let's extend our example.
And that's support
for more devices.
So in this particular case we're
going to create five assets.
We'll start with a high
resolution ASTC version
for our most capable 2GB device.
And then we'll include a
slightly lower resolution
for the 1GB version
of that device.
And since some Metal capable
devices don't support ASTC,
we'll include the
EAC version as well.
And then, for your
legacy devices,
we have the uncompressed
version of the asset.
And we can extend this
example even further
by including a lower
resolution version
of that uncompressed asset
for our least capable device,
the 512MB configuration.
So you probably don't
want to create five assets
of everything, but the point
I'm trying to make here is
that you have tremendous
amount of flexibility
to target specific devices
and create the best experience
possible for your users.
So Xcode integrates a great
new UI that allows you
to tag assets in this way.
The first thing you need to
do, is define the capabilities
of the devices that
you'd like to target.
That creates that little
matrix, and then all you have
to do is drop in the assets that
match the relevant intersection
of GPUFamily and
device memory size
that you're trying to target.
It's that simple.
But of course, we realize
that not all developers have
tools pipelines that exist
in Xcode, so we have you
covered there as well.
We're supporting with app
thinning the JSON file format
that lets you specify
your asset catalogues.
So just like in Xcode, you have
to specify the GPUFamily version
and the device size
for each asset you want
to include in your catalog.
So once you have your
asset catalogs defined,
how do you retrieve
the data at runtime?
The answer is the
NSDataAsset class,
it provides the resource
matched to the capabilities
of the device that
you're running on.
Using the NSDataAsset
is really easy.
Simply allocate an NSDataAsset
object using the name
that you assigned in
your asset catalog,
and then use it in your data.
So let's tie this
altogether using the diagram
that I originally showed
and the normal map example.
So in this case, your
artist will create a bunch
of normal maps, some
compressed, some uncompressed
to target the devices
you'd like.
This gets built via Xcode or
your custom tools pipeline
into your binary, big massive
binary with lots of assets
in it, gets uploaded
to the App Store,
and then the great thing is
only the normal map required
by your user, is
downloaded to their device.
And that's app thinning.
We think that this is going
to change the way you create
and deploy content on
Metal capable devices.
So that was a whirlwind
tour of the Metal ecosystem
over the last 12 months.
We've seen developers like
you create amazing content
using Metal.
We have brought Metal to OS X.
We've also brought all our
great Metal GPU tools to OS X.
We've introduced some
powerful new APIs
that we think you're
going to love.
Finally, we also talked about
how Metal integrates well
with a system, by talking
about app thinning.
All in all, it's
been a great year,
and we're really looking forward
to seeing what you're going
to be able to build with
Metal over the next one.
So please visit our online
documentation, and you'd also
like to go to our
support forums,
and if those don't answer your
questions, you're of course free
to reach out to Allan
Schaffer our Game
Technologies Evangelist.
We have two more sessions this
week, What's New in Metal,
Part 2 on Thursday morning,
and Metal Performance
Optimization Techniques,
which is on Friday.
Please be sure to visit those.
Thank you very much.
[Applause]