[Applause]
&gt;&gt; CHRIS EDSTROM:
Good afternoon.
My name is Chris.
I'm the manager of
ICloud Web Services
and I couldn't be happier
to be here today to tell you
about the number one feature
request we received last year
for CloudKit, which
is web services.
[Applause]
So this talk expects a
little bit of familiarity
with CloudKit I will be
giving you a brief overview
of the architecture but if you
want a more deep dive we had a
couple of sessions last year.
You can go back and
review those sessions.
So in CloudKit, all of your data
is stored within a container.
Inside of this container
we have a public database
for your app data and
a private database
where your user date is stored.
In the public database,
you have the default zone,
which has records, and
in the private database,
you also have a default zone,
but you can also create custom
zones which add sync semantics
which allow you to answer
the question what has changed
since a given point in time.
Of course, you can create
records in both of these zones.
From the API perspective,
we have the CloudKit Server,
and on the native side we
have the CloudKit Framework,
which your app uses to
interface with the server.
We are introducing
CloudKit Web Services today,
which we have used to
bill the Notes Web app,
and today you can use
to build your web app.
So what exactly is the
CloudKit Web Service?
Well, it's three things.
Number one, it's a JSON
interface to CloudKit.
Number two, it's a web sign-in
with Apple ID and number three,
it's a JavaScript library.
So let's take a look at
the JSON API features.
So your full public and private
database access, you can,
of course, create, read,
update, and delete records.
You can upload and
download assets.
You can query your data.
You can create subscriptions
and receive call backs
when your data changes, you
have user discoverability
where you can find
users' real names.
You can do sync and we
provide authentication.
So this is a long list,
and in fact it means
that we have feature parity
between the native API
and the JavaScript API.
[Applause]
So everything you can do in
the native API you can do
through the JSON API and we have
gone so far to make sure things
like field names and
parameters have the same names
in JavaScript.
And JavaScript promises
to provide completions.
Your code ends up
looking similar
between JavaScript and Swift.
I know many of you
in the audience may already
have a CloudKit application,
but if you don't, let's look
quickly about how to get started
with a new CloudKit application.
So the first thing to do
is to create a container.
You can do this either
through the WWDR portal
or through Xcode.
Once you have the container
you need to create a schema.
You can do this either
through the iCloud dashboard
or your native Apple
create it on demand.
So now you have your CloudKit
application up and running.
Let's enable web access.
This is a three-step process.
Number one, you need to generate
a web service API token.
Number two, you need to set
your login call back mechanism,
and number three, you need to
define your domain restrictions.
So let's take a closer
look at these three steps.
So here is the CloudKit
dashboard.
As you can see, we have added
a new pane called API tokens
and I have already created
my first token here.
So at the top is the token
ID, which is what you pass
in when you make a
web service call,
below that I have chosen post
message as my login call back.
It is for JavaScript
applications I will get a
JavaScript call back
when the user logs in.
Alternatively I could have
chosen to have a URL redirect.
Below that I can set the
origins that are allowed
to access my CloudKit
data through web services.
I have here chosen that any
domain can access my data
but for added security
I could have restricted
to viewer domains so now we
have enabled web services.
Let's get some users to log in.
So authentication is
handled transparently.
What I mean by that is
when a user calls an API
that requires authentication,
we will return a
specially formed payload
with a redirect URL that
you can send your users to.
They then authenticate
with an existing Apple ID
or they can create a new Apple
ID right in the sign-in flow.
And to protect users' privacy
we don't provide user name
or password to your app.
Instead we give you a
stable anonymous identifier
for the user.
So let's put all of
these things together
and let's build a
quick example app.
So we are going to
build a tasks app.
It stores tasks, and the com
dot example dot tasks container.
So let's create our first task.
So what I will do is I will
call the records modify API,
and pass in a JSON body.
This JSON body says to create
a new task it has a unique
identifier task one and the
value of the task is buy milk.
Let's go ahead and send
that over to the server.
So we didn't have an
authenticated user.
So in the response
we get a redirect URL
where we can send the
user to authenticate.
Let's go ahead and
follow that URL.
So here is the sign-in UI.
You will notice it has the
app name and the app icon
and the ability to create
a new Apple ID right here.
We already have one, so
let's go ahead and sign in.
Now, once the user is signed in,
you will get a session ID back
to your application through
the call back mechanism you
defined earlier.
So we can go ahead and append
this session ID to the URL
and send the same request again.
Much better.
Now we receive back a
successful creation.
You can see that the
record name is there,
the change tag is there,
the fields are there
and some more metadata
about the record.
This is a lot of JSON
parsing and you have to worry
about error handling and
throttling and we want
to make this API as
easy to use as possible.
So we are proud to introduce
CloudKit JS a wrapper
on top of the JSON.
To talk about this I would
like to invite Onar
Vikingstad to the stage.
I'm.
&gt;&gt; ONAR VIKINGSTAD:
Engineering Manager at iCloud.
And I'm here to talk
about CloudKit JS.
CloudKit JS lets you connect
to CloudKit from JavaScript
and it's a small self-contained
library that works well
with any framework or library
you might already be using
on the web.
It's also important to note
that this is a low level
transport API which means
that it doesn't really
intend to be a data store.
It doesn't allow a lot
of abstraction on top
of the JSON API so if you are
already using a data store
please keep using that
and you should be able
to plug CloudKit JS
straight into it.
Also it allows for
an easy transition
from CloudKit Framework.
So you might already be using
CloudKit Framework on iOS
and OS X in the terms and
concepts, method names
and class names are
going to be the same
so it will be an
easy transition.
That said, there will
be some differences.
This is the web, after
all, and it's JavaScript
so there will be
a few differences,
for instance we are using
JavaScript promises for all
of the asynchronous behavior
and we will see examples
of that later on.
In terms of browser
support, we support all
of the major browsers you would
expect Safari, FireFox, Chrome,
Internet Explorer and
the new Microsoft Edge.
We support Note JS if
you want to do server
to server connections
on behalf of the user.
So before we start looking more
at the API let me
give you a quick demo.
So what we are looking at here
is the CloudKit catalog sample
code project.
This is available both as
a downloadable zip file,
you can get this on
the developer website,
but what we are looking at
here is the hosted version
which is also available.
So it is providing
live code examples
that you can execute
in any browser.
You will see a list of
features on the left.
We are looking at
the ReadMe right now.
This is giving you some
instructions on how
to get started on CloudKit JS.
Let's move to the first
section called authentication.
So you will notice each of these
sections have a description
on top and this example
is telling you how
to use authentication, and below
that you have a code example.
So this code snippet
specifically is checking
for authentication
state of the user.
If the user is not
already signed in,
it's going to present
a signed in button.
And you can actually go ahead
on top here and run this code.
So if I click this
run code button,
it's going to execute this code,
and you will see it scrolls
down through a section
and it tells us we aren
unauthenticated user
at this point and we look
at the sign-in button.
I can go ahead and click
the sign-in button.
I type in any Apple
ID and password.
And you notice the
window closed.
And that was the Apple
hosted authentication page.
So at this point your web
application is signed in.
This is the sample app and
you see we have the name
of the user, first
and last name as well
as the sign-out button
instead of the sign-in button.
This is another feature
of CloudKit
which is discoverability.
If the user has opted in, the
user can choose to share first
and last name with a developer
as well as being discoverable
in the container for
other users to find them.
So now that we have the first
and last name we are using
that here to populate
the top right corner.
All right.
So now that we are signed
in, we can do some operations
so let's go to records.
And this is showing you
how we can save a record
in the private database.
So we see a few fields
on the top here.
We have the record name,
which is the unique
identifier of the record.
We have a zone name
which is the default zone
but it will be any custom
zone that you set up,
and if you have three custom
field names that are defined
in the CloudKit schema.
So in this example,
we have a name field
which is the string value.
We have a location field,
which is the geo location value
and then we have an asset field
which lets you upload a file.
So I will go ahead
and choose a file.
I will choose this green
field landscape J Peg.
And I'm going to
go back up on top
and give this the
name landscape 1.
This is the record name which
is the unique identifier.
And I will change the name here
to just called it green field.
So now that I have the field
filled out I can run the code
and it will save the record
to the database as well
as upload assets
to asset storage.
So you see when it's completed
we are left with a result
and this is actually what
the server responded with,
effectively with the JSON
we are representing it here
in the table.
We have a few metadata
fields as well
as the three custom feel fields.
The green field, the
location and the link
to download the asset.
So just to show you this
actually got stored we can go
to fetch record and I can type
in landscape 1, run this code,
and we have the same
record again.
That's how simple it
is to save records
with CloudKit, with CloudKit JS.
Now, let's go and do another
feature called querying.
So to do that, I will first go
ahead and sign the user out.
So queries allow you
to get subset of data
from the database, and
in this code example,
we are showing you how we
can query the public database
and if you set up the
security roles appropriately
on the schema, you can
actually query for data
in the public database even if
the user is not authenticated
that we are showing here.
I can go ahead and run this code
and this example is basically
using the current location
in a Monscone center to send
a query and sort results based
on proximity to where
we are currently.
I can go ahead and run the code.
And I get back two records.
The first one being Iceland,
and the second one being Italy.
And Iceland is closer
to where we are
than Italy, so that makes sense.
And so I'm not going
to go through all
of the additional features
but we encourage
you to check it out.
You can go to
developer@Apple.com/CloudKit
and you can run this on
any browser yourself.
[Applause]
So CloudKit is the foundation
for a lot of our new services
at Apple including iCloud
drive and iCloud photo library.
This year we also
introduced a notes application
for iOS and OS X.
This is also coming to
the CloudKit platform,
but in addition to
the notes application
on native we have a notes
web application on Apple.com.
In fact, it's using CloudKit JS
in exactly the same way as you
as a developer can now use it.
There is no additional
Apple magic here.
So hopefully you are as excited
about CloudKit JS as we are
and see a lot of new
possibilities here and want
to know how to get started.
So let's take a look.
So first off, we need to make
sure you insert a script tag
on your web page, and
you do this by pointing
to the CD unhosted
version of CloudKit JS.
So this will get CloudKit JS
included, and then secondly,
you need to configure
the CloudKit instance.
So you are going to have the
CloudKit name space available
and you can call the
CloudKit configure method
and you give it a
container identifier
that your application is using.
The environment you want to
target, either production
or development, and then
you specify the API token
that you saw Chris generate
through the CloudKit dashboard.
That's all you need.
At this point you are ready to
start making CloudKit API calls.
Next, you probably want to
authenticate your users just
like we saw in the sample app.
So on iOS and OS X this is
straight forward with CloudKit.
All you need to do since
most users are already signed
into iCloud on the device is
to call the fetch user method
on the container and you
get back a user record
and this user record is going
to have a stable identifier.
So this is all you really need
to do to authenticate users
through CloudKit on
the native devices.
There is no explicit
login, there is no UI.
It's all seamless.
On the web, however, it's going
to work a little bit differently
in that the browser is not
already going to be signed
in so you have to provide a
location for the sign-in button.
Like we saw on the sample app,
clicking it will
open the new window.
There is an Apple hosted
authentication page
and you notice on this
page we have both the iCon
of the application as well as
the name of the application,
and this is coming
out of ITunes Connect
and it's published
in the App Store.
And the user types in their
user name and credentials.
This obviously only
goes back to Apple.
There is also a two-step
verification
if the account is
set up for that.
And when this process completes,
the window is going to close
and it's going to send
back a post message
to the opener window and it will
contain the CloudKit session.
So at this point
your CloudKit JS,
your web application
is going to be able
to start making authenticated
calls to CloudKit.
So to implement authentication
on your page, you first have
to provide a location
for a sign in button.
So you set a development to give
it the ID Apple sign-in button.
Secondly, you have to call
the method called set up off,
and this is going to check
for the authentication
state of the user.
So if the user is already signed
in, a user info object is going
to come back, and that's
all you need to look for.
In addition to user info object
is going to have a record name
and this is the stable
identifier
that we just looked at.
So this stable identifier
is going to be the same now
on the web as it is on iOS
and OS X so you have a way
of referencing the same user
across all of the platforms.
So in addition to checking
for authentication state,
you also need to
handle what happens
when user signs in or signs out.
So you call when user
signs in on the container,
and you get back a promise,
and it's going to resolve
as soon as the user signs in.
And it's exactly the same
for when the user signs out.
So beyond those default
capabilities in CloudKit JS
around authentication.
We also provide toggles and ways
to customize how you
handle authentication.
So this next example is showing
you how you can actually persist
the AUTH between sessions
so CloudKit is not going
to write cookies on your
domain so if you want a cookie
to be written to store
the AUTH session,
you have to set the
persist property
to true in the configuration.
Now, instead of cookies,
you might actually want
to store the session
in some other way.
So this is showing you a couple
of hooks in the configuration.
So we have a put token and a get
token method and these are going
to get called anytime for put
token anytime cloud JS receives
token from the server.
So one example here might be
you want to store the session
in local storage or perhaps
you might want to store it
in your own server so
you can make server
to server calls based
on behalf of the user.
So next let's talk
about record operations.
And just like Chris showed
you earlier with the JSON.
A record in CloudKit JS is
basically an object like this.
So we have a record with
a record named task 1.
We have record type tasks,
and we have some metadata
fields created and modified
which will contain the user that
created and modified the record
as well as the time stamp.
The record change tag, which
is the version of this record
for conflict resolution,
and then comes all
of your custom fields below
that that you have
defined in the schema.
In this example we just have one
task name, it's a type string
and the value of buy milk.
Now, obviously you might want
to store other types of fields
than strings so this is
giving you a comparison
of what those look like
compared to iOS and OS X.
So in CloudKit framework
we have a string
but in CloudKit JS we just
use JavaScript strings.
Same thing for number,
for NS data we use basic
code 64 and coded binary.
NS data we have a
JavaScript number
which is unit time
in milliseconds.
So for the more complex
objects like CL location,
we have a location object,
and a reference object
and also an asset object,
and we ask you to look
in the documentation for how
each one of these are defined.
So in terms of creating a
record, you can go ahead
and define one of
these object literals.
In this example we're just
saying record type is tasks
and we have one field task
name with a value of buy milk
and you can go ahead and
call the save record method
on the database object.
You notice though in this case
we didn't actually give it the
record name.
So the record name is unique
identifier of a record.
So by not specifying that
the server is actually going
to go ahead and generate
one for us.
Also we don't specify the string
type for this particular field,
so CloudKit JS will do
some type inference here
and it will figure out that
this value is fully a string
to you have to specify this for
all of the basic types we have.
So next we want to talk about
queries, and this is going
to work a little bit
different on the web
through the JavaScript API.
So on iOS and OS X in foundation
framework we have NSPredicate.
And NSPredicate is great but
it's not really that natural
for the web and it
doesn't really conform well
to the JSON API we are exposing
through the web services
so we have something that looks
very similar to Java literals
for records in that you just
define a query like this.
In this example we are
saying record type is tasks
and we call perform query on
the database, and we are going
to get back all of the
records of type tasks.
Now, you can do something
a bit more sophisticated.
So in this next example we
are providing some options
to the perform query method.
So we are saying this
hard key is task name.
We are only going to get
back the task name field
from every record.
We are limiting the result set
to ten and we will limit records
in the all task custom zone.
So queries also allow you
to go and specify a filter.
So in this next example, we
are saying still, you know,
we want to look for record
types of tasks but we only want
to get back tasks
of priority one.
And we call it perform query
and we get back all
task with priority one.
You notice here we are
using the equals comparators
and we have a lot more
comparators available
and it depends on the field
type you are querying on so look
in the field documentation
for where each one
of those are defined.
As you saw earlier, we were
limiting the result set
and so the question
is how do you paginate
through the results.
So this is showing
one example of that.
So results limits at 10.
So we will get back
the first 10 records
when this promise resolves but
there is more coming property
on the response object.
So this is telling
us more records
to fetch beyond the
10 we just got
so we can pass the response
object back to perform query
and CloudKit JS will do all of
the work here for us in terms
of fetching the next set of
ten records from where we are.
And in this example we are
showing should we can chain
these promises together.
So next assets.
So assets work a little
bit differently in CloudKit
than the other field types.
So assets are actually not
stored with the record itself,
assets are stored outside in
something we call asset storage.
So the record simply
has a reference
to the asset and asset storage.
The good news is CloudKit JS
handles this seamlessly for you.
In this example we have a
web page with input element
and lets users select
a file like this one
in the CloudKit catalogue app.
So when a file is selected,
the handle file select
function is going to get called,
and all we need to do is just
get a reference to the file,
and we can use that as the value
for the asset field
we are saving.
So CloudKit JS is here going
to do the work for us in terms
of uploading the asset to asset
storage and then save the record
in the database with a
reference to the asset.
Downloading assets even simpler
in that when you are asking
for a field that has
an asset, you are going
to get back a download URL.
In this example we are fetching
one record, a user record,
and you notice here the value
has a download URL property,
and you can go ahead and
fetch the bits from there
or maybe use this as the source
of your image element,
for instance.
So another great feature of
CloudKit is subscriptions
and push notifications.
And all pushes to
Apple devices go
through Apple Push
Notification Service.
Now, traditionally
you had to set
up your own third party
server for this to work.
So you had to get your own
server with your own certificate
with your own server
logic and you had to push,
send pushes through that way.
However, with CloudKit,
there is no longer necessary.
You can simply set up CloudKit
Subscriptions and these act
like triggers in a database.
So these are going to look
for changes in data and send
out pushes accordingly
when they happen.
And now with CloudKit JS the
web will be another client
in this mix.
So we are going to able to
receive the exact same pushes
to the web as we
are to iOS and OS X.
So to receive pushes you
have to set up subscriptions.
This first example is showing
you a zone subscription.
To subscription type is zone,
subscription ID is change tasks
and we give is zone
ID of all tasks.
I would go ahead and save the
subscription with the database.
So this will start
looking for changes
so any time something changes
in the all tasks custom zone.
It will send pushes
to all clients connected
to the same account.
So subscriptions also allow
you to base them on a query
so this next example we are
setting up a subscription,
a query subscription that will
fire anything that's created,
updated or deleted in
the all task custom zone
and then we specify a query
so this particular query is
like when we fetch for
records any time a task
of priority one is
created, updated or deleted,
a push will get sent out and
that's all we have to do.
So on the website, you have
to implement two things,
first you have to implement
register for notifications.
This will go ahead and fetch
a token from the server
that we can use with Apple
Push Notification Service
and also park the connection
with Apple Push Connection
Service.
And secondly, you need to
call add notification listener
which is going to get called any
time a notification is received
on a web page.
So last, let me cover a few
best practices with CloudKit JS.
So as we saw earlier, you
should dynamically link
to the CDN hosted
version of CloudKit JS.
This is important to you
get the latest updates
and security fixes as
we make them available
and it also insures a low
latency delivery of this asset
through our vast accomplished
distribution network
and it's all for
free which is great.
Secondly, you should
consider loading CloudKit JS
asynchronously on your page.
This is a good suggestion
for any third party library
you might load on the web page
and it will avoid any blocking
and impact on user experience
and last you want to make sure
you handle the request responses
so the new free limits
of CloudKit are really
generous including the limits
for requests.
That said you might be
retrieving bursts of traffic
to your website, so
you want to make sure
that your client is
properly backing up.
If it's retrieving requests
through all responses.
So you can also look into how
it can batch multiple operations
in a single request and
we do have a batch API
with CloudKit JS and
if you are interested
in topic you should go
to the CloudKit tips
and tricks session tomorrow.
They will talk more about the
request throttling across all
of CloudKit and not
just web specifically.
So that's it.
That's CloudKit JS.
We really look forward to
seeing what you are going
to be building with it.
Please stop by the labs with
any questions you might have.
And now I will hand
it back to Chris.
[Applause]
&gt;&gt; CHRIS EDSTROM: Thanks Onar.
So in summary, the CloudKit Web
Services provide a full parity
interface to interact with
your CloudKit data on the web.
They are often on a
per container basis.
We handle authentication,
metadata storage,
and asset upload and download.
You handle hosting
your static assets
and your JavaScript
application code.
And finally we have
brought you CloudKit JS
to make this as easy
as possible.
You can visit us on the web at
developer.Apple.com/cloudKit
and for any questions you
have you can visit the Apple
Developer Forums or Apple
developer technical support.
If you still have questions
beyond that you can reach us
at CloudKit@Apple.com.
There are a few related
sessions.
We had what's new in CloudKit
yesterday which is available
on line and tomorrow as Onar
mentioned we have CloudKit tips
and tricks.
I hope to see you there.
And thank you very much.
[Applause]