[Applause]
>> LUKE CASE: Good morning!
Thanks for coming
out and welcome
to "Networking with
NSURL Session."
I'm Luke Case and I'm an
engineer on the CF Network team.
We have got some
great stuff lined
up for you guys this morning.
First, we're going
to talk a little bit
about app transport security
and following that we will talk
about some new protocol support
we've added in NSURL Session.
Now, we all heard about
watchOS on Monday.
We'll talk about the NSURL
Session features we've added
for watchOS.
Following that, we will wrap
things up with some API changes
and some new additions we've
added to the NSURL Session.
Now, to begin, I would like
to start with a little bit
of background on NSURL
Session and the HTTP protocol.
NSURL Session is a networking
API that is mainly used
to download content, HTTP
content, from the web.
It has a rich set of delegate
methods that can be used
for authentication and other
important event handling.
And one of the greatest
features about NSURL Session is
that it allows you
to do networking even while
your app is not running via the
background download APIs.
Now, for those of you
that aren't familiar
with NSURL Session,
it's recommended
that you go back a few years
to the previous WWDC sessions
on the introduction
of NSURL Session.
So now let's talk a little bit
about the hypertext
transfer protocol.
It's a very well-known
protocol and many
of you x probably
are familiar with it.
Essentially at its core,
what you are doing is you are
making requests to the server
and you are pulling
in data in response.
Now, HTTP in itself, as
some of you may know,
is sent out over cleartext.
So it's inherently insecure.
And in today's environment,
there's many hostile
parties going
after the data that's
leaving your app
and going out onto the network.
Now, there was a time when
using cleartext HTTP alone was
perfectly reasonable.
But that time has passed.
Now, fortunately for all of us,
this problem has been solved
for many years and
there's a tried
and true solution
known as HTTPS.
Now, HTTPS is essentially
HTTP layered on top
of another protocol known
as transport layer security.
And transport layer security
performs a multi-leg handshake
using public key
cryptography and, when complete,
creates a secure connection.
Now this connection
is considered secure
because of three properties.
The first being that the data
that's leaving your app goes
over the network encrypted.
So it can't be read.
The second that it
provides message integrity
so the message can't be
altered without detection.
And finally, the third,
it provides authentication
so you can actually prove
the identity of exactly
who you are talking to.
Now, NSURL Session has
excellent HTTPS support embedded
within in it, and so often in
your client code, it's as easy
as using HTTPS instead
of using HTTP.
Now, do note that some
additional server support is
required, but HTTPS is supported
by most server vendors today.
Also keep in mind that most data
should be considered sensitive,
and this is because even
if you might not think
that the data that's
leaving your app going
out onto the network
is not sensitive,
your customer may,
in fact, think it is.
For example, if you
have a TV streaming app,
you may think, well,
it's just TV.
You know? He's just watching TV.
He or she is just
watching TV, but to them,
it may mean that they
don't want people
to know what they are
watching, essentially.
Let's put it that way.
[Laughter]
So -- now, why is it
important to use HTTPS?
Well, it's essentially,
it comes down to this:
your customers trust you with
their data and their privacy.
And we at Apple, we really want
to work together with you guys
to make sure that we build
upon and maintain that trust.
And today, I'm proud
to introduce App
Transport Security.
Now, App Transport Security
is a new feature from Apple
in iOS 9 and OS X, El Capitan.
And essentially, at its core
it helps prevent accidental
disclosure of sensitive
customer data.
Now, ATS also strengthens the
default policy of NSURL Session.
And perhaps the most important
aspect of that strengthening is
that now NSURL Session,
by default,
will disallow cleartext
HTTP loads.
It'll only use HTTPS
connections.
Now, these connections that
it does make uses today's
best practices.
So ATS places restrictions
on TLS versions,
cipher suites used,
certificate trusts,
and certificate key sizes that
are used in that transaction.
Now ATS is simply configured
via your apps Info.plist.
And you can see an example here.
Essentially what we
are asking you to do is
to declare your intended network
behavior within your app.
So at its core, ATS wants you to
really describe what you intend
to do with the network, and we
really want you to worry less
about the security of your
app and rely more heavily
on the system to
do the right thing.
So describing your network
transaction is, of course,
easiest when it's all secure.
So if your app exclusively
uses secure connections,
and they only use best
practice properties,
then there's nothing
else you have to do
to configure ATS
within your app.
So if you are writing a
new app, this is exactly
where we want you to start,
and if you have an existing app
or you are supporting
legacy code,
this is where you
should aim to be.
Now, we understand that this
may not be always the case
that you have a server
that can comply
with these new restrictions on
TLS versions or cipher suites,
so we allowed that to --
through the use of exceptions.
And essentially, with ATS
you can declare exceptions
and let us know what versions
of TLS you want to use,
or if you want to opt
out of forward secrecy,
or other options.
Now, we do understand
that existing apps may
have different constraints.
Let's say for the most part
you do use secure connections,
but in some cases,
you have servers
that just don't support
HTTPS or the best practices.
So, for example, if
you have a media server
that doesn't support
HTTPS and only HTTP,
you can easily describe this
behavior using an exception.
Essentially all you have to do
is declare which domain needs
to load over HTTP and NSURL
Session will still allow
that cleartext load.
Now we also know that some
of you may be supporting a
general purpose web browser
or another app that loads URLs
based off dynamic user input,
and we've allowed for that case.
In this case here, you can't
possibly describe what secure
connections you need ahead of
time, and so you can simply opt
out by declaring an
allow-all policy.
Now the allow-all policy can
be used to allow NSURL Session
to load any HTTP
or HTTPS resource.
Now, do note that this is
a useful tool for debugging
that I believe is already
out on the Internet.
So we ask, if you do
use it for debugging,
to do it temporarily
for obvious reasons.
Now, even if you
are in this state,
you can still protect
specific servers and domains.
So you are in this state where
you are allowing everything,
but you have your
own servers, say,
that you pull the configuration
data from or metadata from,
and to do this, again, is
just an exception within ATS.
You simply declare this domain
that you want to protect
as an exception to
the allow-all policy.
And this will allow
NSURL Session to continue
to protect this resource
by only loading over HTTPS
and with best practices.
Now, the SDK has been
out since Monday,
and there's probably
a few of you that woke
up at this awful hour, just to
find out what ATS is all about
and why your network
loads are failing.
Well, we understand that and we
want to work together with you
to get you up and running.
So, do note that ATS is
only active if you build
against a current SDK.
If you are targeting
the previous release,
ATS rules do not apply.
NSURL Session will transfer all
HTTP resources or loads URLs
to HTTPS automatically.
And, again, as I said earlier,
some of you already know
about the allow-all key, and we
ask you to use this temporarily
to find out if the new network
failures in your app are
because of ATS or not.
And this will kind of help
you narrow things down.
So the next step, if
you allow-all ATS loads,
or allow-all loads,
and you've determined
that the problem is ATS,
the next step would be
to log the NSURL Session
errors that you are seeing,
so you can try to
determine and narrow
down which load is
actually failing,
and what the underlying
error is.
There is also a great debugging
tool that's an environment
variable known as CF
Network Diagnostics.
If you set CF Network
Diagnostics to level 1,
all the failing URL loads --
so, all the loads that
failed will log the URLs
and the underlying TLS error.
And so what you can do
in the next step is take
that underlying TLS error, and
look up and secure transport.h,
and see exactly what
the underlying issue is.
Usually it's a failure in
negotiation between client
and server at the TLS layer.
So now, do understand
that this is a new API,
and it's still under
development.
So we strongly encourage
you guys to pay attention
to the seed notes and
release notes, and also,
please file radars so
we can track any issues
that you guys are hitting
and help you guys
get up and running.
So I hope it's clear
that the time
for secure networking is now.
And we really want to
work with you in order
to protect your customers' data.
So, again, if you are writing
a new app, start with HTTPS
and try to get your
servers up and running
with the best practices.
Now, for those of you
with existing apps,
we ask that you first start by
moving what you can to HTTPS,
and for the places where
you can't, go ahead
and use the exceptions
that are available
through your Info.plist.
Now, do keep in mind that
your customers trust you
with their data, and it is
truly sensitive in all cases.
And so Apple wants to
work together with you
to provide a more secure
environment for your customers.
So, again, please give
us feedback via radar,
come see us down at the lab
after this session and tomorrow.
We really want to work with
you to protect our customers.
Thank you all for being here and
I will be followed up by Andreas
who will talk about new protocol
support and NSURL Session.
Have a great conference.
[Applause]
>> ANDREAS GARKUSCHA:
Thanks, Luke.
Good morning, everyone!
My name is Andreas
and I'm going to talk
about new protocol
support in NSURL Session.
Yes, NSURL Session
supports HTTP/2 protocol.
Your apps are ready to
communicate using HTTP/2
and it's very easy to adopt.
Let me play it one more time.
All right!
If you are already using
NSURL Session in your code,
you are automatically
a part of all of that.
Future of the web,
major milestone
in the web's evolution, your
apps are running faster.
You don't need to
change your source code.
Everything works automatically.
So today, we are going to
talk about three things.
Why do we need a new protocol
and what are the common problems
of the current HTTP/1.1
protocol?
We will learn about the most
important HTTP/2 features.
And finally, we will talk
about HTTP/2 protocol
adoption in your apps.
So, why another new protocol?
We already have a
lot of protocols
for every kind of communication.
The reason is that most
of the protocols were
designed many years ago
for the needs of their time.
Look at one of the
first Apple websites.
Today's needs look
significantly different
than those 15 years ago.
So it is time for an update.
HTTP has been around since
the beginning of the web,
and it is not a secret
that it has many issues.
The most famous HTTP
issue is the problem
of only one outstanding
request per TCP connection.
The solution for this
was HTTP pipelining,
but HTTP pipelining
is not available
on all servers or networks.
In fact, it's disabled on most
popular desktop web browsers.
Another solution was to open
multiple connections to a host.
This could help to fetch
multiple resources faster,
but together with other things
like textual protocol overhead,
the lack of header
compression, it just adds
up to higher system requirements
and lower performance
on both the client
and the server.
Last year, we introduced SPDY
Support in NSURL Session.
SPDY was an attempt to
make the web faster.
It was an experimental
protocol, however, it was chosen
as a basis for a
new version of HTTP.
The specification for the
new protocol version went
through the IETF
standardization,
and officially got an RFC
number assigned last month.
So today, as you already know,
NSURL Session is extended
to support HTTP/2 protocol.
Let's take a look at
the key differences
between HTTP/1.1 and HTTP/2.
As opposed to HTTP/1.1,
HTTP/2 opens only one
TCP connection to a host.
It's network friendly and
requires less system resources
on both the client
and the server.
HTTP/2 is fully multiplexed.
That means that a new
request does not need to wait
until the server
sends the response
for the previous request.
HTTP/2 has request priorities,
so that more important
resources can be delivered
at a higher priority
to the client.
Let's take a look at how HTTP/2
multiplexing resolves the
Head-of-Line Blocking problem.
We have three requests for
resources on a web server.
We sent out the first
request and we get a response.
Only after this, we can
send out the second request
and get the second response.
Same happens with
the third request.
Now, with pipelining enabled, we
can send out all the requests,
one after another,
without waiting
for the previous
responses to arrive.
But we still get the
responses in the same order.
And you see that the first
response for the image in blue,
blocks the following
two responses.
With HTTP/2, we have
the same three requests,
with different priorities.
We still can send out all the
requests at the beginning,
but we are receiving all the
responses at the same time.
Moreover, the requests
with the higher priority,
I get and deliver
faster to the client.
You see that the second
response was a medium priority
and the third response for
request was a high priority,
arrived prior to the first
response even though they were
scheduled later.
The image does not block them
anymore and this is great.
Great for your applications
and the performance.
Let's continue with
the comparison.
HTTP/2 is a binary protocol.
That makes data processing
and parsing faster.
HTTP/1.1 does not use
header compression.
SPDY also could not
use header compression
because of a security exploit.
HTTP/2 uses HPACK, a
more secure mechanism
for header compression.
Let's talk about HPACK.
HPACK header compression
is based on two tables,
a static table and
a dynamic one.
The static table contains
the most used HTTP headers
and is unchangeable.
The headers, which are not
included in the static table,
can be added to the
dynamic table.
The headers from the tables
can be referenced by index.
As an example, you see a
simple HTTP/1.1 request.
Highlighted is the data which is
going to be sent to the server.
And here's HTTP/2 representation
of the same request.
So let's encode this request.
The pseudo headers,
method, scheme, and path,
can be referenced
using the static table.
The authority header is
included in the static table,
but without its value.
So to encode this request,
we need three bytes
for the first three headers,
plus an additional byte,
which tells that we want
to add the authority header
to the dynamic table
and the value
of the authority
with its length.
And this is what
is going to be sent
to the server plus additional
overhead for the header frame.
Now with the second request,
and you see that the
authority header goes
in the dynamic table.
So with the second request,
HTTP/1.1 would send the same
headers over and over again.
In HTTP/2 case, in
that particular case,
we can reference all the
headers using the static
and the dynamic table.
We are using only one
byte for each header.
It is a huge savings
of the bandwidth
and it's remarkable how
few bytes are needed
to encode a request or
response header in HTTP/2.
So let's talk about
what you need
to adopt HTTP/2 protocol
in your apps.
There's not much work to do.
HTTP/2 protocol is
seamlessly integrated
into NSURL Session API.
If you are already using NSURL
Session in your code, your apps
and OS X programs will get this
functionality automatically.
You will not need to
write any new code
or provide any additional
configuration to turn it on.
Let's take a look at
the source code example.
This source code looks exactly
like the code you guys
already have in your apps.
You see, there's no difference,
no new configuration flags.
It just works.
[Chuckles]
Yes, you only need
an HTTP/2 server.
But it's okay.
[Laughter]
Your apps are ready
to communicate using
HTTP/2 protocol.
If you do not deploy
an HTTP/2 server yet,
then your apps will
use HTTP/1.1 directly,
or the best available protocol
will be selected automatically
for the network communication.
Once you start using a web
server which supports HTTP/2,
there is no additional
work needed.
Your apps will use HTTP/2
protocol automatically.
Please keep in mind that NSURL
Session supports HTTP/2 protocol
only over an encrypted
connection.
And that your HTTP/2 server
requires to support ALPN or NPN
for protocol negotiation.
Currently at Apple, HomeKit
remote access via iCloud is
using HTTP/2 protocol
for communication
between HomeKit accessories
and iCloud.
Many big companies are
already using HTTP/2 protocol.
Google provides its
services in HTTP/2.
Twitter is using HTTP/2 as well.
There are many HTTP/2 open
source web servers out there,
and finally, some CDN
service providers are working
on the HTTP/2 protocol
support today.
We worked hard to provide
HTTP/2 protocol support
in NSURL Session so
that you guys can adopt
and use it as easy as possible.
HTTP/2 is available
today in WWDC seed.
It's seamlessly integrated
into NSURL Session API
and it's enabled in Safari,
on OS X, 10.11, and iOS 9.
Thank you.
And now I would like to
invite Dan up to the stage.
Dan?
[Applause]
>> DAN VINEGRAD: Good
morning, everyone.
My name is Dan.
I'm a software engineer on
the CF Network team at Apple,
and the first thing
I would like to talk
about today is using
NSURL Session on watchOS.
With the WatchKit SDK that was
released alongside watchOS 2
in beta earlier this
week, I'm pleased to say
that HTTPS loads are fully
supported on watchOS.
And this means that
everything we've already talked
about today, like App
Transport Security and HTTP/2,
are built into this support.
One major difference between
using NSURL Session on watchOS
and using it on other platforms
is that underneath the hood,
we actually will use the best
connectivity mechanism that's
available to us at the time.
And this means that
in most circumstances,
if the users' watch is nearby
their paired iPhone device,
then we will actually leverage
the Bluetooth connection
between them, perform the HTTP
loads on the phone itself,
and deliver the results back
to the watch over Bluetooth.
If the user happens to be out
and away from their phone,
but with their watch, and
the watch is connected
to a known Wi-Fi network,
then we can actually use
that Wi-Fi network directly.
But the good news for you is
that this is all abstracted
away from the API itself.
You can use the API just as you
have been on other platforms.
You don't need to worry
about how we are connecting.
It just works like magic.
So, with that said, there are
a few best practices and things
to keep in mind when using
NSURL Session on watchOS.
The first is that
you should really try
to just download the
minimal size assets
that are actually required
for your app to function.
Keep in mind that the watch
has a very small screen.
So if you are downloading
images you don't really need
to download the full resolution
images that you would want
to display on an iPhone 6 Plus
or a Mac with a retina display.
The screen's a lot smaller; you
can download smaller images.
And also keep in mind that the
watch has a lot less processing
power than a phone or a Mac,
and additionally will often
be limited by the bandwidth
and latency constraints
of the Bluetooth
connection to your phone.
So we're not really going to be
able to get you bytes as quickly
to the watch as we would
on other platforms.
So keep that in mind as well.
Another thing to note is that
apps on watch will generally run
for a much shorter period
of time than iPhone apps
or definitely Mac apps.
You will mostly be limited
by how long the user wants
to sit there standing with
his wrist raised staring
at the watch and
interacting with it.
So if you are using a
default session configuration
or an ephemeral session
configuration, keep in mind
that these networking transfers
will happen only while your app
is actually running.
So this is totally fine if
you are sending small amounts
of data like fetching stock
quotes or weather data
or social network
status updates,
but for any larger content
like videos, for instance,
you 'll want to use
background uploads or downloads,
which can continue
out of process while your
app is no longer running.
And for more information
on background uploads
and downloads, I highly
encourage you to check
out the WWDC sessions
on Foundation Networking
from previous years.
Next up, I would like to
talk about some API changes
that we have made in
this year's releases.
The first thing I would like to
talk about is NSURL Connection,
something we have not
talked about today so far.
So, this year, I'm announcing
that NSURL Connection
is deprecated on OS X,
El Capitan, and iOS 9.
And let's just take a moment
to think about what that means.
Deprecation does not mean
that NSURL Connection
is going away entirely.
We know that there are
a lot of apps out there
that are using NSURL Connection,
and we're not just
going to break them.
So it will still work.
Those transfers will still
work, but keep in mind
that new features are really
only going to be added
to NSURL Session at this point.
We highly encourage you to
switch over existing code
from NSURL Connection to NSURL
Session if you haven't already,
and if you are writing new
code, we would really hope
that you would only use NSURL
Session and not Connection.
Another thing to keep in mind is
that NSURL Connection is not
supported at all on watchOS.
So if you need to
load HTTP content
from a WatchKit extension,
you have to use NSURL Session.
But luckily for you, if you
haven't done so already,
switching from NSURL Connection
to NSURL Session is
actually very easy.
So I would like to walk
through an example of that now.
Here's a simple use
of NSURL Connection
to perform an asynchronous
HTTP request,
which probably looks similar
to the things that a lot
of you have in your apps.
Here, we're connecting to
www.example.com over HTTPS,
and we have an NSURL
object to represent that.
We then construct an
NSURLRequest, wrapping that URL,
and we use NSURL Connection's
'send asynchronous request'
method to fire off that
request asynchronously.
And we receive the result
in the form of this closure,
which includes an NSURL Response
object representing the HTTP
response headers that are
received, an NSData object
for the response body
data, and an error
if a transmission
error occurred.
So let's take a look
at what that would look
like with NSURL Session.
It's very similar.
You will notice that the NSURL
and NSURL request objects are
still in use and this is true
for a lot of the other
NSURL family of objects,
like NSURL Credential Storage
and NSHTTP Cookie Storage.
The main difference
here is that instead
of using NSURL Connection
to send an asynchronous
request method,
we are using the 'data
task with request' method
on the NSURL Session
shared session.
Then once we resume the task, we
would again receive the results
of that transaction,
asynchronously,
in the form of the response
data, the response headers,
and an error if a
transmission error occurred.
So that's how easy it is to
switch from NSURL Connection
into NSURL Session in your apps.
So, next I would like
to switch gears and talk
about some new additions
that we've added
to the NSURL Session
family of APIs this year.
The first thing I would like to
talk about deals with cookies.
Last year at WWDC we introduced
a great new feature called app
extensions, which
lets you embed parts
of your app's functionality
other places on the system
like notification center.
But applications and their
extensions have different data
containers by default,
which means that even
if you are using NSURL Session
and already leveraging our
great built-in cookie handling
support, those cookies
are actually being stored
in different places.
But you can use what's
called an application group
to actually get access to
a shared data container,
which both your app and
its extensions can access.
And this year we have
introduced new API
to let you create a
cookie storage associated
with that group container.
And I would like to
show you how to do that.
So what you want to use here
is NSHTTP cookie storage's new
'shared cookie storage for group
container identifier' method.
And you just simply create a
cookie storage with the passing
in the name of your
application group,
and application groups can be
configured while editing your
project's build settings
in Xcode and going
to the Capabilities tab.
Once you've created the cookie
storage, you just need to set it
as the HTTP cookie
storage property
on an NSURL Session
configuration object,
create an NSURL Session
from that configuration,
and then any tasks that you
create in that session will use
that cookie storage in
the group container.
So for the entirety of
the presentations today,
we have been talking about using
NSURL Session in the context
of loading HTTP content.
But there are some cases
where you really need a protocol
other than HTTP or HTTPS.
So if you are implementing
a chat application,
a video calling app, or
-- or something like that,
you really need -- you might
need a protocol that's not HTTP,
and you want to do
something custom directly
on top of TCP/IP networking.
So NSURL Session Stream
Task is a new API this year,
which is a Foundation
extraction,
directly over a TCP connection.
Now, in the past, you might
have used NSInput Stream
and NSOutput Stream to do
something similar, but we think
that NSUSRLSession Stream
Task has a few key advantages
over the NSStream APIs.
First of all, it
offers a very simple,
convenient asynchronous
read and write interface,
whereas with NSStream you had
to set up a delegate to listen
for events or when to read, and
the read and writes could block,
and it was kind of a mess.
But this is a lot
easier and cleaner.
Secondly, NSURL Session
has great built-in support
for automatically getting
through HTTP proxies,
and NSURL Session Stream Task
can leverage this support
so that you can connect
to a remote server even
if there's an HTTP
proxy between it,
and NSStream can't
really do this.
And there are a few
other new API goodies
that I will talk
about later as well.
We also know that NSStream
is a very pervasive API.
There are a lot of other
frameworks and APIs that accept
and work with NSStream objects.
So we also have some support
to be compatible with NSStreams
as well and I will
show you that later on.
So as I said, NSURL Session
Stream Task supports TCP/IP
connections, which you
can create explicitly
with a host name and port,
or if you are using
the NSNetService's APIs
to discover Bonjour
services in your app,
then we can actually accept
that NSNetService and resolve
that for you automatically.
Stream Task uses the existing
NSURL Session configuration
options and delegate methods to
communicate events to you, and,
of course, we support
TLS-secured connections
and you can even dynamically
change this once you've actually
established a connection
to a server.
So let's take a look at how you
would perform a read operation
with a Stream Task.
First, to create a Stream Task
you can simply use the 'Stream
Task with Host Name
and Port' method.
And you just pass in
the host name and port
that you want to connect to.
And then after resuming
the task,
you can use this 'Read
Data of Min Length,
Max Length, Timeout' method.
And what this will do is you
can pass in a range of bytes
that you want to read and a
timeout for that operation.
So if we managed to read
something within that range
or we hit an EOF, or there's a
transmission error or timeout
that occurs, we will invoke
this closure with the results.
Writing is very similar.
We -- unlike -- with NSStream we
can work directly with NSData,
you just pass in the NSData
object that you want us to write
and a timeout for that
operation, and, again,
this closure will be
invoked with a nil error
if that occurred successfully
or an error if a timeout
or a transmission
error occurred.
Enabling TLS is as simple
as calling the 'Start Secure
Connection' method on the task.
I mentioned before that we
also have some built-in support
to work with NSStream,
NSURL Session Stream Task.
So the reason we do
this is because we know
that there are a lot of
APIs out there that work
with NSStream objects
already and we want
to give you something that can
still be compatible with those.
So, you can actually convert
an NSURLSession Stream Task
to NSStreams, and I will show
you the very simple code to do
that on the next slide.
Just keep in mind that when you
do this, any pending async reads
or writes that you have enqueued
on the Stream Task will
complete before we give you
the NSStreams.
And that doing this
also detaches the task
from the session.
And so its connection,
its underlying connection will
no longer count against a limit
that you may have set on
the session's maximum number
of connections per host,
and it will no longer be
in the session's set
of outstanding tasks.
So to convert a Stream
Task to Streams,
you simply call the 'Capture
Streams' method on the Task,
and then those input streams and
output streams will be delivered
to your delegate with
a new delegate message.
We also have a few other
informational delegate messages
that we have introduced
on Stream Task.
The first is interesting.
It's a better route
discovered for Stream Task.
So let's say, you have a
Stream Task that's connected
to your server over a
cellular data connection.
If the user then
joins a Wi-Fi network,
then we would deliver this
notification to your app
to tell you that there might
be a better way to connect.
And what you might want to do in
this situation, if you want to,
is tear down your existing
Stream Task and create a new one
to that host and port,
and try to connect
over the better connection.
And we leave it up to
you to decide whether
or not you want to do this.
You know, if you are 99% of the
way through transferring a lot
of data it might not make
sense to actually tear
down the existing connection
and create a new one.
And we also have some
informational delegate methods
to tell you when to
read or write sides
of the underlying TCP
connections have been closed.
I also talked before about our
automatic support for dealing
with HTTP proxies
in Stream Task.
And the way you can do deal with
this is actually by starting
with an existing NSURL Session
Data Task, which generally deals
with HTTP content, and
converting it to a Stream Task.
And this you can do
when the response
for that Data Task is received.
So to convert a Data
Task to a Stream Task,
and let you communicate
directly over the TCP connection
without the HTTP framing,
you would simply respond
to this completion handler
in the 'Did Receive
Response' delegate method
with the new 'Become
Stream' disposition.
And then we will
inform your delegate
that the Data Task has been
converted to a Stream Task
with the 'URL Session Data Task
Did Become Stream Task' method.
Before we finish up today,
I would just like to go
over a few things that we
discussed this morning.
We first talked about how you
can use App Transport Security
to guarantee that only
secure connections are made
from your app and how you
can declare exceptions
to those as needed.
We then talked about how you
can make your apps faster
by supporting HTTP/2
on your servers,
which requires no additional
changes on the client.
We talked about best practices
for using NSURL Session
on watch apps, and went over the
new API changes this release,
the deprecation of NSURL
Connection and how to migrate
to Session, how to share cookies
between apps and extensions,
and how to get a great
foundation level abstraction
if you need to communicate
using a TCP connection
without HTTP to your servers.
As always, I would like to
refer you to the documentation
that we have available on
our website, and remind you
about the developer forums
that you can participate in,
and any questions that you
might have while you are here
at WWDC this week, Paul
Danbold is our Evangelist
and you can talk to him.
There are a few other
related sessions
that you might want to attend.
I highly encourage you
to attend "Your App
and Next Generation
Networks," tomorrow,
which will be a lower level
discussion of networking.
And the networking labs
occur this week as well
and you can talk to us directly
for any questions you have.
With that, I would like to
thank you for coming out today,
and we look forward to seeing
the amazing apps that you create
with iOS 9, OS X, El
Capitan, and watchOS 2.
Thanks.
[Applause]