&gt;&gt; ERIC BIENVILLE: Good morning.
[ Applause ]
Welcome to the vector
numerics group session.
My name is Eric Bienville
and I'm
with the vector numerics group.
Our group is providing
the accelerate framework
which you already know and
some libraries in the system.
In the accelerate framework,
you will find the image
which is a collection
of hundreds of functions
for image manipulation.
You will also find vDSP
inside accelerate which is
for signal processing
and three layers
of linear algebra libraries.
Outside of accelerate, we also
maintain the Math library, LibM,
and the string functions.
Last year we also introduced
SIMD which is a set of headers
and functions providing
vector types directly mapping
to CPU vector units
near SSC and AVX.
Today we present you three new
additions to these functions.
The first one, compression, is
a library for data compression;
then Steve will present
addition to the SIMD library,
and finally Luke will
present sparse BLAS,
linear algebra for
sparse matrices.
Let's start with compression.
What is that?
Compression is a new
library providing a unified
and simple API for
lossless data compression.
Why would you need such a
thing where if you already try
to use compression in
your app, you first have
to pick a compression
somewhere, read the manual,
write the code, test it.
If it doesn't work, you need
to pick another one,
write the code again.
That's a lot of trouble.
And also sometimes, well,
actually usually you would have
to include the compression
curve inside your app
which is a maintenance
nightmare.
So the idea is to
provide a wrapper
to common compression algorithms
and their unified API and also
with some benefits
like optimized code
and easy switch between
algorithms.
Let's start with the
algorithms we put inside.
When we speak about compression
algorithms there are two metrics
to consider.
The first one is
obviously compression ratio.
That is the ratio
between raw data size
and the compressed payload
size, and then we are interested
in the encoding speed
and the decoding speed.
So to select algorithm, we
put them in one single graph.
This graph, so on the X axis
you have the compression ratio,
and on the Y axis,
the encoding speed.
And in the middle there is a
reference, reference compressor.
So all of the algorithms are
compared to this reference.
So if you are on the
right, you compress better,
if you are on top, you
compress faster, and that's it.
So let's put some
algorithms inside here.
The center one is zlib.
That's the most used.
And so what did we do?
We chose the best compression,
this one, right, this one, LZMA,
and the fastest one LZ4.
You will see the gray line is
to show how it becomes more
and more harder when you
want more compression.
So more compression means slower
and less compression means
faster, exponentially so.
And if you look at that closely,
there is a first point here
which is above zlib, that means
faster and a bit to the right,
that means compresses better
that's LZFSE that's a new
compressor we're
introducing today
and a good alternative to zlib.
I will talk about that later.
These are the four
compressors we put
in the compression library.
And the decode looks like
that so that's the same thing,
if you compress more,
you will need more time
to decompress also.
And our four compressors are
at the same position here.
So these are the four
algorithms we selected to put
in the compression library.
LZMA for high compression,
but it's low.
LZ4 for very fast compression,
but it doesn't compress
that much, and in the middle you
have zlib and LZFSE for balance
between compression
ratio and speed.
So I'm matching different
use cases
like for software distribution
you want to use LZMA
because you will compress
once on the server and ship
that so you want the shipping
part to be as small as possible.
And then what did we do?
We optimized some of
them for Apple hardware.
What does that mean?
Like that.
So, for example, we
optimized zlib decoder,
and the performance of the
zlib decoder we provide is
compression is almost 1.6X
faster than the normal zlib.
And the same goes with the LZ4.
So that's another benefit.
And you will also benefit
from security of data
and performance update without
having to change your code.
Let me talk briefly about
LZFSE, our new compressor.
Why would would you
need a new compressor?
First, its fun.
And then, so why are
we optimizing zlib?
We came to the conclusion in
the entropy part of the zlib,
it is a bottle neck and there
is not much we can do to solve
that except replacing
it with something else.
So that's what we did.
We took the new technology
called finer state entropy
and replaced the part
of zlib with that.
And the good news is that
LZFSE is able to map better
on modern CPU architecture,
much better.
And the design goal of that was,
match the zlib compression ratio
and make this thing
as fast as we can.
So let me show you
numbers about that.
That's compression ratio.
So by design it's
the same thing.
This is energy efficiency,
both encode and decode, LZFSE.
As you can see we are
2-point something times faster
for encode and 2.5
times faster for decode,
not faster, more efficient.
What does that mean?
Suppose you have a
full battery charge
and nothing is compressing.
With zlib you will
compress, let's say,
5 terabytes of data before
the battery is empty.
With LZFSE you would be able to
compress 12 terabytes with data
with the same battery charge.
That's what energy
efficiency means.
Actually speed is
not bad either,
because we can reach 2-point
something times faster
for encoding and three
times faster for decoding
with the same compression ratio.
So that was about LZFSE.
Now, let me show
you to use this API.
There are two APIs.
There is a buffer API to use
when you have all of the data
at once in one single buffer.
And there is streaming
API to use
when receive the data in PCs.
So buffer API is quite simple.
It's like a super mem copy
thing, you give it a buffer
and the number of bytes
inside, destination buffer
and the capacity of it,
and you just give it also
which algorithms
it needs to use.
Here it says LZFSE.
You see that switching between
compressors is changing this
constant, you don't have
any code to rewrite.
The new code is compression
encode buffer function,
and it will return the
number of bytes put
in the destination buffer
of 0 if something went wrong
or there was not enough room
in the destination buffer.
Decoding, that is
the same story.
So you will pass a buffer
containing compressed payload
and a buffer to receive
the decoded data.
The difference here is it will
return the number of bytes put
in the output buffer
and if something fails actually
it will fill up the buffer.
So it will just truncate
the output.
Now, let me show
you the stream API,
which is a little more complex.
Because you will need to have
some state between the calls.
So we will call the library
multiple times with new pieces
of raw data to compress.
It's like a candy factory.
You send sugar inside and
get candies at the output.
So you will have the
stream object to initialize
and then cause a process
function many times
and at the end you will
have to call a function
to free the resources
used by the stream object.
So let me show you
in detail with code.
So first, we initialize the
stream object, you say okay,
I want to encode, I want
to use LZFSE, initialize.
Then you will have
to call process.
Before calling process usually
in other compression libraries,
you will have to tell it where
are the bytes to compress
and where to put the output.
And then you call process,
and it will, as the consumer,
input or fill out the output
and it will update
these fields for you.
Then at the end, you need
to tell it, okay, I'm done,
no more sugar, finalize.
And after that, you are not
allowed to send more data
to compress, but you may
need to call it several times
to empty the pipes
and get the output.
And at that point it will return
end, and which means in the end,
and you will need to call
compression stream destroy
to free the resources.
So encode.
Decode is actually
a bit simpler.
You need the same
initialization code.
This time that's with
decode instead of encode.
Then you send the data and
it will figure out by itself
if it's the end of
the stream or not.
So at some point it will return
end, which means you got all
of the data, and you
need to destroy again.
And that's it.
We are done with compression.
So let me wrap up, that's a new
library providing a simplified
and unified API on top
of several compressors.
LZMA, LZ4, zlib, and LZFSE,
which is to be preferred
over zlib.
And LZFSE which is our new
high performance compressor.
Thank you and let me call
Steve, who will tell us
about improvements
to the SIMD library.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
&gt;&gt; STEVE CANON: Thanks, Eric.
My name is Steve Canon.
I'm an engineer on the vector
numerics group with Eric,
and today I will talk about
SIMD, which is a library
for two dimensional,
three dimensional,
and four dimensional
vector math.
We introduced SIMD last year in
Yosemite, and iOS 8 and it works
in C, Objective-C, and C++
and it closely mirrors the
Metal shading language.
That means it's really easy
to write code that will run
on the GPU in Metal and use
the same data structures
and the same code on
the CPU using SIMD.
It closely hews to the tradition
after shading languages
and the way they work
with vectors and matrices.
So what's new this year is
that we have support
for Swift as well.
[ Applause ]
So everything from here on
in the talk or in my piece
of the talk is going
to be Swift,
all of the examples are Swift.
For the most part, everything
is about exactly the same
in C, Objective-C and C++.
If you want to see in depth the
story for those languages check
out last year's video session
and there are a few things
where there are important
differences I will call
out explicitly in the talk,
but all of the examples
will be Swift.
Why did we need to introduce
a new vector library?
There were a bunch of vector
libraries on the platform
and I have worked
on a bunch of them,
so why do we add a new one?
I will show you examples
of a few things
that were a little
bit inconvenient
with other vector libraries
and how they are much
nicer using SIMD.
BLAS is a great vector library.
It's part of the accelerate.
It's one the first
things I worked on.
Here is an example of
multiplying a vector by a scaler
and adding it to
another vector in BLAS.
So we create two Swift arrays.
Those will be our vectors.
We can call this C BLAS Saxpy
function, which will multiply X
by 2 and add to Y and
store the result in Y.
There is a bunch of other
information we need to pass
because this is an API
that takes raw coiners,
it doesn't know anything
about lengths or strides;
we need to provide
that information.
There is also inefficiency
that comes
from making an explicit
call to do this work.
We will look at GLKit, which
is another great library,
I love GLKit.
It has explicit vector
types, so you don't just have
to use raw arrays, but the
functions are very verbose.
You have to call it GLK
vector 3 multiply scaler
to do your arithmetic
and that's too wordy.
Here is what it looks
like using SIMD.
This is a lot nicer, right?
You write down the arithmetic
you want to do and it works,
you don't need to
call functions.
Life is nice.
So this is really nice.
What else can you do?
We have vectors of floats,
doubles, and 32 bit integers
of lengths 2, 3, and 4.
In C, Objective-C and C++
there are other vector types
available, for now we
have the subset in Swift,
and the reason we chose this
subset is it's what you have
to use most often
to interoperate
with other libraries for the
Metal programs you are going
to write when you want to
use model I/O, when you want
to do graphics stuff, these
are the types you want
to have available.
What can do you with
these types?
You can create them, first off.
We have a bunch of initializers
that do nice things,
you can create the zero vector,
you can explicitly specify
the elements of the vector,
you can have a vector with
all of the components equal.
There are lots of
nice initializers.
You can do arithmetic.
You have element-wise
arithmetic,
the operators just work.
So if I multiply two vectors I
get a new vector, each element
of which, the value in
that element, is the result
of multiplying the corresponding
elements of the input vectors.
Divide, same thing, I
can multiply by a scaler.
I can do a dot product,
cross product, et cetera.
I already showed
you one example.
I will show you another
simple example right now.
This is a reflect
function that I might use
in graphics frequently.
It takes 1 vector
X and it reflects X
through the plain perpendicular
to the normal vector N,
and to write this we write down
the mathematical expression.
Write X minus twice the dot
product of X and N times N,
but you shouldn't actually have
to write this function, right?
It should be available
to you already.
And it is.
We have a bunch of
geometry, shader,
and math functions available.
So we have dot product, cross
product, reflect, refract,
distances, et cetera, all of
the stuff you want to use.
If you have written
shader programs before,
you have used these
functions a lot.
This is just a standard
stuff you would use in Metal
or open CL or GLSL or whatever
your favorite shader language
is, and we also have a variety
of math functions available
from accelerate for the float
4 type so you can use V sign F,
VCosf, do Math functions
with these types.
We have matrices
as well as vectors.
Matrix types are float N
by N, and double N by M.
So N is the number of columns
and M is the number of rows,
if you are a mathematician,
this is weird.
If you are a graphics
programmer, this is natural.
So you guys will
feel right at home.
N and M can be two, three,
or four, they don't need
to be square matrixes
so, for instance,
a float 2 by 3 is a matrix with
two columns and three rows.
Again, we have a variety
of initializers for you,
so you can create a zero matrix,
you can create the
identity matrix,
you can create a
diagonal matrix,
by specifying the elements
of the diagonal if you want,
all the elements if you want,
either as an array of arrays
or as an array of vectors.
All sorts of nice things.
And I will show you a little
arithmetic example using
matrices as well.
Let's create a matrix
with 2s on the diagonal.
This is a matrix where when you
multiply it will scale a vector
by 2.
Let's modify the last column
to put some values there.
This is a transformation
matrix that scales vectors by 2
and applies an offset as
well, it translates them.
We can apply this to
a vector of all 1s.
And we can also undo
the transform
by using the inverse
property of our matrix
to get the inverse
transformation to get back
to the original vector.
When you want to
interoperate between languages,
you might have Objective-C
API like model I/O APIs
that you want to call.
The Swift vector types
are layout compatible
with the Objective-C
vector types.
What I mean by that is they,
have exactly the same
representation in memory,
and the compiler knows
that they are the same.
So you don't need to do anything
to convert a Swift vector type
into an Objective-C vector type
or an Objective-C vector type
into a Swift vector type.
So here I have an Objective-C
API that returns a vector,
a SIMD vector, and I can
use it immediately in Swift.
For matrices I have to
initialize a Swift matrix
from the Objective-C
matrix that I get.
It's a really cheap
operation, basically a copy
because the layout is
the same, but I do need
to call the initializer.
When I want to pass Swift
types to Objective-C,
the story is exactly the same.
I can pass the vectors
for matrices I use
the C matrix property
to get an Objective-C
matrix that I can pass
to my Objective-C API.
So that's SIMD.
SIMD is great for
when you want to work
with small vectors and matrixes.
Sometimes you want to work with
bigger vectors and matrixes too.
So I will talk to
you about LAPACK,
BLAS, and linear algebra.
This is the fun part of
the talk; we have a break
from the math nerdery.
So LAPACK and BLAS are industry
standard math libraries.
These are some of the oldest
APIs on the platform actually,
which means they are a
little bit cryptic looking
but there is tons of
documentation for them online
because they have been
around for 40 years,
and a lot of times you might
have some code from a library
that you get that depends
on having these available,
just link against
accelerate, it works fine.
It's pretty easy to use.
Linear algebra is a new
interface we introduced last
year that has much simpler APIs
for doing the most common
linear algebra operations.
So this is exactly the same
operation on the last slide,
it's solving a linear
system and rather
than calling a cryptic
function with eight parameters,
you call LA solve and
you give it the vector
and matrix you want
to solve for.
So that's very nice.
The past few years we have done
a little talk about LINPACK
and how fast we can
do linear algebra.
The LINPACK benchmark says how
fast can you solve a system
of linear equations?
It's exactly the operation
we saw in that last slide.
And historically, there have
been three different variations
on this benchmark.
It started out as how fast can
you solve a 100 by 100 system?
But as computers became
more powerful and faster,
it wasn't possible to actually
show how fast you were anymore
with such a small problem.
So it became a 1,000
by 1,000 system.
And today when people
talk about LINPACK,
they actually mean
no holds barred.
You get to pick however
big a matrix you need
to show off how fast you are.
When you see supercomputer
rankings, they are talking
about ratings that are
millions by millions
when they give you
LINPACK scores.
You just pick whatever
makes you fastest.
So I was reading the
internet a few weeks ago
and saw someone talking
about now amazingly fast
their iPad Air 2 was.
It got 1.8 gigaflops on LINPACK,
which sounds pretty impressive.
It's 1.8 billion floating-point
operations per second.
I know that this number is low.
So someone had written a simple
C language routine to solve it
and just taken whatever
the compiler gave them
and that was what the
LINPACK score was.
So I looked around
a little bit more.
I found someone who had
carefully optimized their
LINPACK routines; they
had written vector code,
they had cache tiled, they
had done multithreading,
and they got 5.6
gigaflops LINPACK.
It's three times
faster, nice improvement,
but rather than doing
all of that work,
you could just call
accelerate instead.
I showed you that D get RS
and LA solve function
a few slides ago.
You can write one line of code
and if you do that,
you get 25 gigaflops.
[ Applause ]
So this is what we
really want to do.
And this is what we want
to make easy for you guys.
We want to make it so you can
write one line of code rather
than having to hand
optimize everything,
and get great energy usage
and great performance
without needing to
do a lot of work.
So now I'm going to hand you
over to Luke, who will tell you
about what you can do when
your matrixes are even
bigger [applause].
&gt;&gt; LUKE CHANG: Thank you,
Steve, my name's Luke Chang.
I'm an engineer on the
vector numerics group.
I'm here today to talk
about Sparse BLAS.
BLAS stands for basic linear
algebra solve programs.
And sparse BLAS is BLAS
for sparse matrices.
It's a new library
in iOS 9 and OS X.11.
It's designed with simple
API and good performance.
It supports both single
and double precision.
Why do we need sparse BLAS?
Can I use a dense BLAS
on the sparse matrix
that I already know
how it works.
Yes, it can given
that the dimension
of your matrix is not large,
but using Sparse BLAS is
better in so many ways.
In order to demonstrate that,
let me show you a
typical Sparse matrix.
This is a typical matrix
from a machine learning.
It has more than a million
rows and 200,000 columns.
That gives us more than
300 billion entries.
However, the density of
the matrix is just 0.05%.
Here is a picture to
visualize the sparse matrix.
The darker the blue,
the higher the density.
As you can see there
is a lot of area
in this picture that is white.
They are just zeros.
We don't want to waste
memory on those zeros.
If you were to store
this sparse matrix
in a regular matrix format
so that you can use
the regular dense BLAS,
assuming just single precision
point numbers it takes more
than one terabyte of
memory, which is unfeasible.
You don't want to do that
on your phone, on your iPad.
So it saves memory, besides
sparse BLAS is also energy
efficient and faster.
We measure sparse BLAS
performance on a MacBook Pro,
13 inch at density 0.5%,
sparse BLAS is more
than 18 times more energy
efficient than dense BLAS.
Performance is 15 times faster.
As the density goes down,
performance goes up.
At 0.05%, which is the density
we saw in the previous matrix,
both energy efficiency
and performance are more
than 100 times better than
using a regular dense BLAS.
So now you see there are
many compelling reasons
to use sparse BLAS.
It saves memory, it's
energy efficient, faster.
What are available
in sparse BLAS?
We have products, triangular
solves, we can calculate norm,
L1, L2, L infinity
norms, et cetera.
We encounter trace, which
is the sum of diagonal.
It can permute rows and
columns, add new values a matrix
and extract rows and
columns from a matrix.
Before I talk about
the operations,
let's see how we
store a sparse vector.
Like I said before, we
don't want to waste memory
on the zero values, so we store
in the non-zero values
like this.
And then we need to know where
those non-zero values come from,
so we store the indices
of non-zero values.
Lastly we need to know
how many we stored
so that's the number
of non-zero values.
Those are the three things we
need to store a sparse vector.
In order to make the conversion
from regular dense vector
to a sparse vector, Sparse
BLAS provides utility functions
to help you with the conversion.
If you want to convert from
dense to sparse, you call pack.
The other way around
you call unpack.
If you just want to
know the non-zero count,
you can call get
vector non-zero count.
Now, we can look
at a sparse matrix.
How do we store it?
We can view the sparse matrix
as a collection of rows,
or a collection of columns.
So we have compressed sparse
row, compressed sparse columns,
or we just forget
about rows and columns.
Those are messy.
I want to see the matrix as
a list of non-zero values,
so for each non-zero value
we store the column index
and row index.
There are many other more
storage formats, and each one
of them has its own
pros and cons.
And there might be a
best storage format
for a particular
operation you want to do.
We decided to make
things easier for you.
We defined a sparse
matrix data type.
It is opaque pointer, so
if you want to use it,
you have to first create it
using the create function,
and you can operate on
it; after you are done,
you have to destroy it.
The benefit of doing this is
that we manage the
memory for you.
You don't have to worry
about allocating new memory
when you are trying to add
new values to the matrix,
or resize the buffer, or
freeing the buffer at the end.
We will do that.
Even better, we will pick
the best storage format.
For example, if you
insert a bunch of rows
into the sparse matrix, we
will store it as sparse row.
And we will store it as sparse
columns when you insert a bunch
of columns, and if you want
to do a particular operation
and there is a best storage
format, we will convert it
to that format automatically.
So lastly, this enables us
to hide dimension details
in our API, that
makes our API cleaner.
When you call a sparse function,
you don't have passing
the dimension
of the sparse matrix every time.
So here is an example.
First, you create
a sparse matrix.
And then you can insert a
value to a sparse matrix.
Or you can insert sparse
vectors as rows or as columns.
Then you commit the changes
to the sparse matrix.
I will talk about
commit function
in the next slide
in more detail.
After you are done,
you call destroy.
Okay. Why do we need
a commit function?
Data insertion is expensive
because we store values
in a compressed format.
Every time you want to add a
value to a compressed storage
that involves data movement,
even more memory
allocation, that is expensive.
So we want to delay all
of the data insertion
so we can do them in batch.
Good news is, even you forget
to call the commit function,
the commit function will
be triggered automatically
when you do an operation
on the matrix.
Now, you may ask, then why
do I need a commit function?
If you want to control the
performance of your code,
you will want to use the
commit function explicitly.
Let's say you want to get your
sparse matrix ready during the
startup time of your app,
so your app can respond
to the user input as
quickly as possible.
Then you add the commit
function into your startup code.
That will do the trick.
All right.
So in the interest of
time, I will only talk
about two most common
operations in sparse BLAS.
The first is product,
C equals A times B.
We support vector inner
product, vector outer product,
matrix vector products and
matrix-matrix products.
What are the types for A, B, C?
For inner product, A is
sparse, B is either sparse
or dense, C is a single value.
For outer product, A
is dense, B is sparse,
and the result C
is a sparse matrix.
For matrix vector and
matrix-matrix product,
A is sparse, B is
dense, C is dense.
It's very rare you need a
product of two sparse matrices
so it's not supported.
Here is the function
prototype of matrix product.
The naming convention
of sparse function is,
we start with sparse
underscore followed
by the operation we want to do,
in this case is matrix multiply.
Dense means B and C are
dense, float is the data type.
And you will return
success or an error code.
The argument of this function
is just like regular BLAS.
You specify the order of B and
C, column major or row major.
You say you want to
transpose on A or not,
number of columns of B and C.
The rest is just like BLAS.
The next operation
is triangular solve.
You solve the triangular
system of equations,
so T has to be an upper or
lower triangular matrix.
We support both dense and,
dense vector or matrix for B,
one note to keep
in mind that upper
or lower triangular property
must be set before you do
data insertion.
Here is the code
to highlight that.
Set matrix property is
called before you do any
data insertion.
After data insertion, you
can call triangular solve,
and the argument,
again, is just like BLAS.
In summary, sparse BLAS we
design it with simple API,
it has a wide range
of operations,
and it has good performance.
Okay. Now it's time to
wrap up our session.
We talked about three
new libraries today,
compression with our own
new compressor LZFSE.
Now, you can use SIMD on Swift,
and there is a sparse
BLAS library.
They share the same
design goals.
They are fast, energy
efficient, and easy to use.
We encourage you
to give them a try
and let us know what you think.
We would love to hear from you.
We take developer requests
and feedback very seriously.
In fact, there are
many features we add
to accelerate framework based
on developer requests,
your requests.
So if you see something
missing that you want to use,
please file a feature request.
For more information, we
have online documentation
for vDSP and compression.
If you want to know more about
other parts of accelerate,
you can check out the video
of our previous WWDC sessions.
We also have simple code
for compression vDSP.
You can join the
discussion in the forum
or any general inquiries,
Paul Dembo is our evangelist.
Here are the related sessions
we talk about model I/0, Metal,
Swift, in our talk you can check
out the videos of these sessions
if you want to learn more.
That's it.
Thank you for coming.
We look forward to
seeing you in the Lab.
Thank you very much!
[ Applause ]