[Applause]
>> ANTONIO CAVEDONI:
Hi, everyone.
My name is Antonio Cavedoni.
I am a member of the team
who designed the new
San Francisco fonts,
and I am thrilled to be here
to introduce them to you.
So on the agenda today
we are going to look
at the San Francisco fonts,
how they were designed,
and what they mean
for our platforms.
We are going to look
at some new features
and how you can make your
apps more awesome with them,
both coding-wise
and design-wise.
And lastly, we are going to talk
about some potential API
pitfalls that you may run
into when adopting these
new fonts in your apps.
So let's get started.
Text is everywhere.
And fonts make text possible.
But fonts also have a voice.
And good fonts enhance your app
content and your user interface,
and they do not get in your way.
You read fonts all the
time, and you read them
on different screens,
on different devices,
and at different point sizes.
You also read them at
different viewing conditions,
such as light conditions
or viewing distances
or screen sizes and resolutions.
So we set out to improve on
the typography of our platform,
and we came up with
a new typeface design
that we call San Francisco.
San Francisco is a new family
of typefaces designed by Apple
in California, and it is both
inconspicuous and beautiful.
San Francisco unifies
our platform
with a consistent typographic
voice and a reading experience.
So this is what it looks like.
San Francisco is what is called
in typography as a grotesque,
which is another word
for a sans serif.
And this is the family tree.
The San Francisco
design is comprised
of two main subfamilies.
We have SF, which ships on
iOS and OS X, and SF Compact,
which ships on the Watch.
Both families have two cuts
that are called optical sizes,
and they are text and
display, and I will talk
about these in a second.
And all of the fonts have six
weights for the text families
and nine for the display ones.
So again, SF ships
on iOS and OS X,
and SF Compact ships
on the Watch.
So now let's look at the
difference between these two.
SF and SF Compact
are sibling designs,
meaning they are
related but not equal,
and the biggest formal
difference
between the two is how we
handle the round shapes.
In SF, they are round,
and in SF Compact,
they are actually slightly flat.
So that achieves two main goals.
The first is stylistic, but the
second one, more importantly,
is functional, so these
flat sides allow us
to have more space
between the letters,
which means they are more
legible when they are smaller.
And this seemingly
inconsequential feature repeated
over and over and over again
in text really does
make a big difference.
So now let's look
at proportions,
which are actually similar
between SF and SF Compact.
So I will just focus
on SF for a minute.
I am going to go over some
typographic terms you may
already be familiar with,
so please bear with me.
Latin text lies on what
is called the baseline.
Lowercase letter align with
something that is known
as the x-height, which is the
height of the lowercase x.
And the uppercase
aligns at the cap height.
We also have a descender, which
is where lowercase letters
that are below the baseline
align, and an ascender.
Now, for proportions,
the SF family has
compatible overall metrics
with the previous UI
fonts that we shipped,
which means your apps
won't experience a lot
of vertical reflow.
In fact, they won't experience
any vertical reflow at all.
But within these
compatible vertical metrics,
we actually change the
proportions a little bit.
For example, we made the
uppercase shorter a little bit.
The reason we did this
is because we wanted it
to work better in
mixed-case settings.
And also, we increased
the height
of the x-height a little bit.
So we made the lowercase
go towards the uppercase.
And again, that improves
mixed-case settings
but also makes the
lowercase larger,
which is what you read the most,
and so it's for better
legibility.
And lastly, the numbers
align with the uppercase.
So SF is a pan-European font,
which means it covers the Latin
script, which includes languages
like Polish or Icelandic or
Hungarian or even languages
that need stacking
accents, like Vietnamese.
But it also covers the
Cyrillic script, which is used
in Russian, and the
Greek script.
So that's San Francisco.
It is a new family of typefaces
that we designed at Apple.
iOS and OS X ship with
a font family called SF,
and SF Compact ships
on the Watch.
The families have
different proportions --
sorry, similar proportions,
but they are different designs.
Now, both fonts are available
for download for you today --
actually, right now --
and you can get them
from the Apple fonts page,
developer.apple.com/fonts.
But please remember that
these are prerelease,
so they will get finalized
once the final OSes ship.
So before I move on to talk
to you about optical sizing,
which is the big idea in the San
Francisco family of typefaces,
I need to tell you about
some principles of design.
Visual perception is
largely about illusion.
And what I mean by that is
imagine you have two shapes.
You have a square and a circle.
And you want to make people
think that they are looking
at shapes that are
the same height.
So you put them side by side,
and you align them
mathematically,
and the circle actually
looks too short.
So to address that, you actually
have to cheat, meaning you have
to make the circle larger.
In typography, we say that
you make the circle overshoot
the square.
So in other words, if you want
to make two shapes look similar,
you often have to
make them dissimilar.
Now, this does not apply just
to the shapes themselves,
but it applies to the space
around the shapes as well --
I'm going meta here and
showing you the slides --
and what I am trying to get
at here is if I put that text
in the middle of the
slide, like this,
it would actually look too low.
So again, to make
shapes look similar,
you have to actually
make them divergent.
And as a bonus, do you guys
know what this character is,
what it's called?
The pound, the hashtag.
In Italy, we call
it the cancelletto,
which means small gate.
It is, of course,
the octothorpe,
and the octothorpe is the
intersection of four lines,
and where these four lines meet,
that area in the middle can get
very dark and actually can kind
of clog up at smaller sizes.
So if you see it small, you can
hardly notice that it's there.
So what have you to do there is
you kind of have to cheat again.
You have to not actually
make the intersection
of these four lines but
make it a larger square.
So that's the octothorpe in our
heavy weight of San Francisco,
and we do this in type
design all the time.
So again, visual
perception is about illusion.
And with that, I want to talk
to you about optical sizes.
Which is this branch of the
family tree that you saw before.
Imagine you have a piece of text
in two sizes in the same font.
By the way, this word doesn't
actually mean anything.
It's something that we type
designers use to look at fonts
and kind of judge their rhythm
because it has flat
and round shapes.
Anyway, you look at
it, and you may notice
that the smaller version of
this text is not really legible,
and the reason is in a
grotesque typeface like this,
where letters are nice
and close to each other,
if I simulate low vision
by blurring it out,
the smaller size font -- in the
smaller size font, letters start
to kind of blend, right?
So what you want to
do there is you want
to do something like this.
Meaning you want to
kind of adjust it
so it's more legible
when it's small.
So you may be thinking that all
I did there was just animate it
and make it slightly
wider, and actually,
I am changing the
outlines completely on you.
So before I show
you the differences
between these two fonts
that are called Display
and Text, by the way.
Display doesn't mean screen,
but it means typing sizes
in typography, and
text is the text sizes,
so the display font is
used for larger sizes
and text for smaller ones.
I have to tell you
about negative space,
which is the space inside
letters, around letters,
and inside the contours.
Negative space is critical
for telling shapes apart
and for reading them.
And in the example before,
actually, in the bottom --
in the text font, there was
almost twice as much the space
than in the display font.
So another thing that could be
an issue in grotesque typefaces,
such as San Francisco, is that
these shapes look beautiful
when they are really large, but
they have similar structures,
and they can become confusable.
So when you superimpose
them, you may notice
that they all have the
same overall morphology,
which means they all have
these areas at the top
and at the bottom
that are curvy.
They all have these two areas
that we call counters that are
in the same -- roughly
the same position
and roughly the same size.
They also have this
semi-horizontal area
in the middle, and they are
really defined by these areas
that we call apertures.
If you imagine air
going to the letter,
that's where it would flow in.
So you really want to
change the display --
the text fonts versus the
display one, and when we do so,
let me just show
you some examples.
In a lowercase a, for example,
we actually change the size
of the overshoots because we
want the round shapes to pop
out more from the
x-height at smaller sizes.
We also open up the
aperture right there.
And we do the same at the
bottom of the lowercase g.
In the lowercase s, we open
up these apertures as well.
We make the r nose or flag
larger, and we do the same
with the lowercase f
and the lowercase t;
they're larger and
slightly taller.
The lowercase i is
an interesting one
because what happens there is
the dot on the i visually starts
to collide with the stem
at really small sizes,
and so we actually make
it larger and higher up.
So there are two distinct font
families in SF and SF Compact.
They are called Display
and Text, and they are used
at different point sizes.
The system automatically
switches between the two for you
so you don't have to do
anything to adopt them.
And that's optical sizes.
Thank you.
[Applause]
There are two optical,
size-specific families
in San Francisco:
Text and Display.
The system switches between
the two at 20 points,
so you don't need to know
this if you are coding
for the new platforms; however,
you do need to know
the difference
if you are designing your
app because design apps
like Photoshop, or
Sketch, or other apps
like these don't
actually do this for you,
so just know you have to
switch between these two fonts.
So now that we looked at
size-specific features
such as optical sizes, I want
to tell you about something else
which is size specific,
and that is tracking.
Tracking is a modifier on the
native spacing of letters,
and if you saw that animation
and you thought, oh, yeah,
he changed the kerning on that
string, you are almost right.
There is a subtle difference
between tracking and kerning.
Tracking applies both positively
and negatively to all the glyphs
in a font, and kerning
really only applies
to a specific pair,
individual pair.
So that's kind of
the big difference.
Tracking is global,
and kerning is local.
Now, the San Francisco
fonts have inside
of them embedded per each
font a tracking table
which is size specific,
and it defines point
sizes and tracking values.
It achieves something
like this, right?
So it makes the smaller
text spread apart
and the bigger text
closer together.
And you don't need to know these
values, again, if you are coding
to the new San Francisco fonts,
but you do need to know them
if you are drawing your app
in Photoshop because, again,
they do not do this for you.
This tracking table is
available for download
with the system fonts
with the same page
that I showed you earlier.
So that's what tracking
is all about.
Next, I would like to
talk to you about weight.
Font weight is the
measure of how thick
or thin the strokes
of the letters are.
Now, the text families of
San Francisco and SF Compact
as well, SF and SF Compact, have
six weights for the text fonts
with their italics, and
they have nine weights
in the display fonts.
And you may be wondering why
it is that we have more weights
in Display than in Text.
And the reason is that
the extreme weights
of the family are really
designed for titles,
and so it wouldn't
make sense for them
to be used below 20 points.
So some of these
weights are actually new,
brand-new in our platforms, and
so previously it was hard to get
to them or the ones that
were there previously,
and now we are giving you
new APIs to actually get
to all the range of
weights and system font.
They are both in
UIKit and AppKit,
and they are a new
parameter added
to the systemFontOfSize
API call,
and these are the
arguments that are taken.
Now, you have all these weights,
and you may be wondering,
how do we actually use them?
And I don't mean from
a coding point of view,
but from a design point of view.
So you have three main goals
that you can achieve
with weight.
The first one is
differentiation.
You can create difference
in a piece of text,
and you can create a hierarchy.
The second is to
achieve similitude.
And the third is a
stylistic purpose,
so you want to achieve
some sort of voice.
So let's look at these.
Imagine you have a piece of text
and you want to call out a word,
make it active, make it a
link, make it emphasized.
Weight is a great
way of doing that.
You can also have a list of
items and create a hierarchy
in there by saying the first one
actually is the one I want to --
it is the title of the list, and
the other ones are the things
that are being enumerated.
But you can also use
weight in a more subtle way,
which is to create similitude.
Consider this example,
which is kind
of vernacular to
Watch Glances UI.
You have a bigger number and
some smaller text underneath it.
Now, if you set them both
in the same font weight,
the smaller text
might look too light.
So if you want to achieve
similitude there, what you have
to do is you have to make
the weights dissimilar
to make them similar.
So you can make the bottom
font regular rather than light.
So if you follow this principle
of larger sizes, lighter weight;
and smaller sizes,
heavier weight,
you can roughly make
things go towards each other
and be harmonious.
But lastly, you can also
use weight for voice.
To show you what I mean, I
created a new revolutionary app.
It's called Bee Weather, and
it's a weather app for bees.
I really wanted to be punchy
and bold, but what I want
to show you is that if
I just take the same --
exact same layout and I
change only the font weight,
I can create a completely
different stylistic effect,
a completely different voice.
And if you are sitting there
and you are thinking, oh,
but the color is deceiving me,
I actually made Zebra Weather
as well, which -- [Laughter]
-- proves my point better.
So you can really use weight
to achieve a stylistic effect.
However, remember that fonts
are there to serve the text,
so legibility is
our first concern.
You want to establish
a hierarchy
with consistency and clarity.
And if you don't feel
comfortable doing that,
iOS already has a
system that you can adopt
that has a hierarchy embedded
within it of sizes and weights
that go along together.
These are the text style APIs
that are used for Dynamic Type,
which also give you all the
Dynamic Type advantages,
such as users can go
in their preferences,
change their font size, and
your app will react accordingly.
When working with weight,
you also have to remember
that there is a setting
both in iOS and watchOS
to change the weight of the
fonts on people's devices,
and so if you are relying on
weights that are too bold,
you might hit a ceiling
there, and on the other hand,
if you are relying on
fonts that are too light,
text might be illegible.
So there is no hard-and-fast
rule about how to use weight.
But these rough guidelines
can give you some ideas.
So these are the weights of
the San Francisco font family.
There are new ones
available to you and APIs
that go along with them.
The same guidelines about
legibility, hierarchy,
and the elusive quality of
taste apply to their usage.
Next I want to talk to
you about another feature
of the San Francisco family,
which are typographic features.
So features make fonts active
because they are pieces
of behavior that is
embedded inside a font.
They primarily make
complex scripts possible,
but they can also be used
to access extended
glyphs inside a font.
Sometimes they can
be the only mechanism
or sometimes they can be
a convenience mechanism
to access these extended glyphs.
So to give you an example
of what features can do,
let me tell you about fractions.
So you are looking at this, and
you are typesetting in your app,
and you are thinking, actually,
I know that there is a glyph
like that in Unicode,
and I can just go see
if San Francisco has
it, which it does,
and you typeset it,
and you are done.
Great. But what happens
when you have
to typeset something like this?
Which is not in the font
and is not in Unicode?
So you could write code that
iterates through that string,
and moves along, and
creates some other versions
and repositioned versions
of all these glyphs,
and you may also change
the weight because you want
to make it look similar
to what's next to it.
Maybe you even remember
that there is a fraction
slash inside the font.
You go check it out
in San Francisco,
it's there, boom, you put it in.
And you just wrote
a bunch of code
that you could have
just thrown away
because the fraction
feature does exactly the same
for you automatically.
And it also works for
arbitrary fractions.
So the way this works is not by
having a ligature for 65/324.
I don't have that
glyph in my font.
I actually have smaller
versions of all these numbers
and of this fraction slash
that get assembled together
by the system based
off of the font.
And the great thing
about this is
that these are individual
glyphs,
which means tracking will
apply to them as well.
So features are discoverable,
and you can enable them
in the Typography
panel, which is a piece
of UI inside the
Font panel of OS X.
But you can also
enable them in code,
which is the most common
scenario for you guys.
So here I am using the new
systemFontOfSize weight API
to get the light weight.
I can get a font
descriptor out of it.
Once I have that, I can actually
modify it by adding attributes
to it, and some of the
attributes can be the features.
I can turn on one feature at
a time, I can turn it off,
I can also do groups of
features all together.
And once I have that
font descriptor,
I can create another
UIFont out of it.
Or NSFont.
So other features that are
available to you are things
like superiors and superscripts
or inferiors and subscripts.
Or also uppercase forms
that are used when you want
to typeset math symbols
or other symbols
in between numbers
or capital letters.
But there are some
features in San Francisco
that are really special to
this design, and I just want
to call them out to you.
The first one is the
vertically centered colon,
which is by default the colon
aligns with the lowercase,
so it sits on the baseline,
but when you are typesetting the
time, you really want it to be
in the middle of these
numbers vertically.
So we use this everywhere,
in our lock screen in iOS,
we use it on the title
bar of OS X, on the Watch,
we use it on our stopwatch
apps, so we decided
to make this automatic
because it's so common
to typeset the time
in UI design.
But you may want to opt
out of it if necessary.
The feature code to opt out
of it is the same as the one
to opt into it, essentially.
Another feature is alternate
shapes for numerals 6 and 9.
So these two shapes are
beautiful when they are large
in their vernacular, their
grotesque genre; however,
they do have an issue
with confusability.
They can be confused when
they are really small either
with each other or with an 8.
So for that, we actually
designed alternate shapes of 6
and 9s inside the
San Francisco fonts
that have these flat sides,
and we use them in situations
like the small dials
on the Watch.
We use them on the serial number
on the back of your Watch.
But you can also use
them in serial numbers
where the context is not enough
to tell you what
are you looking at.
So because their usage
is context dependent,
we don't actually turn it
on for you automatically.
But it's available with the --
this feature code that you see.
And next I want to kind
of combine two ideas.
The first is typographic
features that we just saw,
and the second one is optical
sizes that we saw earlier.
And so the display and text
fonts are really designed
differently, and we take into
consideration the point sizes
that they will be used at.
So if you are typesetting a
fraction in display sizes,
it's fine if you have the curly
shape of the 6, but if you are
in text fonts, you really
want the other shape
because that's -- imagine that
would be set at 12 points.
The fraction would be
probably 6 points, right?
So we actually designed
them differently
and spaced them further apart.
And we do this for a
whole host of glyphs
in our San Francisco font.
So we make them different
between text and display
on purpose to make them
either be more beautiful
or more legible.
So these are typographic
features.
They are behavior that is
embedded inside a font.
Some features are
automatically turned on for you
by System Font, and others
require you to opt into them.
So next I want to talk to you
about numbers for a second,
not the app, but actual
numbers inside the font.
So we type designers spend a lot
of time thinking about the shape
of numbers to make
them look beautiful
or functional or
all these things.
But I want to tell
you about the spacing
of numbers, their widths.
By default, on our platforms,
numbers are always monospaced,
meaning they all have the
same width, which is great
if you need typeset something
like tables, for example.
Monospaced numbers
are really handy
because they make
everything align.
You can also achieve
layouts with, like,
multiple columns with them.
However, they are
not the only numbers
in the San Francisco fonts.
We also have what are
called proportional numbers,
where each number has
its own "natural" width.
So there are situations
where, of course,
monospaced numbers are
clearly what you want.
For example, like this, when
you have proportional numbers,
they will actually
wiggle around,
and monospace numbers
actually stay put.
But you may also typeset
numbers in static labels,
such as when typesetting
a date or a phone number
or a read count in an inbox
or an email address or a URL.
In those cases, really, you want
proportional numbers instead.
So let's take a -- do a case
study with an app like Calendar,
which is fairly numbers heavy.
And if you look at how we
use numbers in this app
and how we typeset
them, you will notice
that they don't really
align with anything else,
and they really are in
line with other text,
meaning they could use
-- they should use,
and they do use proportional
numbers.
So knowing this, we decided
to take a big leap here,
and change the default
of our platforms
to actually give you
proportional numbers by default
and make you opt into
monospaced numbers.
Now, there is a precedent for
this, and that's the Watch,
which actually ships with
proportional numbers by default.
But it is a big change,
and it may affect layout.
So because of that, we
have provisions in place.
If your app is not linked
against iOS 10.11 --
sorry, OS X 10.11 and iOS 9,
you still get monospaced
numbers by default.
The system turns on the
monospace feature for you.
And -- but if you do recompile,
you get proportionals.
And there is a new shortcut API
available in AppKit that kind
of abstracts away
the feature code
that I was showing you
earlier, so it makes it easier
for you to adopt this.
So lastly, we are going to
look at some potential pitfalls
in our font APIs, both
with these new fonts
and with existing fonts.
First of all, the curious
amongst you may have noticed
that in the preview builds of
OS X and iOS, the SF fonts ship
with a name that is --
it starts with a dot.
What that dot means is that
that name is Apple private,
so please don't rely
on it being stable.
We've also seen some
framework developers
that use their own
font-loading code,
such as game framework
developers, for example,
where they rely on the fact --
on the assumption that
fonts are going to be
in a specific place
on the file system.
Now, this is very brittle,
and we would like you
to treat font paths as opaque,
meaning you can access them
through Core text -- you can
access font through Core text,
and you don't have to go hunt
for them on the file system.
Also, if you access
system font by name,
the fontWithName API is
really meant for user fonts.
So if you have your own fonts,
you can call them that way
and that's great, but if you
instantiate a system font,
later on you extract its
name and then you try
to create another font out of
that, well, now you are opting
out of all the automatic things
that system font does for you,
such as the automatic features,
the size-specific behavior,
the automatic tracking,
and all these things,
so we recommend you
don't do this.
And instead, you can
actually use font descriptors,
which completely encapsulate
the behavior of a font,
so this is the recommended
way for using font objects.
Lastly, with optical sizes,
we are really challenging
some old assumption
as to how fonts work, so for
example, if you typeset a word
at 15 points and later on you
apply a scale to your matrix
and you reuse the same
font object, well,
you are getting a font that
is designed for 15 points at,
I don't know, 120 points.
What you really want to be doing
there is actually reinstantiate
the font again for that
specific point size,
and you will get
the right behavior.
So we really want you to
treat fonts as opaque objects
if possible, so use the
system APIs to get to them.
Fonts with optical qualities
really break old assumptions.
And relying on the system font
APIs will give you the right
behavior all the time.
So that's -- please use these.
And that's all we
have for today.
So we looked at the new
San Francisco fonts,
we looked at concepts
like optical sizes,
the big idea in San Francisco.
We looked at automatic
tracking, the weights
and the features
of San Francisco.
We looked at the big
change coming up in numbers
in our platforms, which means
that they are becoming
proportional by default.
And we looked at some
potential pitfalls in our APIs.
So if you have questions, you
can get in touch with Mike
or Curt, or go on our
Developer websites.
There's also a session
about Watch Design Tips
and Tricks later and
a Text and Fonts Lab
where we can answer
your questions.
So thank you very much.
[Applause]